<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Ebook>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.01 --


            Short title and application :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) These rules may be called the Andhra Pradesh Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964.


            (2) They shall apply to every person who is member of a civil service of the State or
            holds any civil post under the state or in connection with the affairs of the state :
            Provided that nothing in the rules shall apply to:-

            (a) the judges of the High Court of Andhra Pradesh:

            (b) the members of the All India Services;

            (c) persons who are not full-time employees but are engaged by Government to do certain
            work without prejudice to the regular practice by such persons of their professions in
            other respects, subject to the exception that rules 14,15,17, 18 and 19 shall apply to
            the Advocate General, Government Pleaders, Public Prosecutors and Pleaders doing
            Government work;

            (d) the members of the Village establishment ;

            (e) persons paid from contingencies
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.02 --


            Definitions :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires.

            (i) ``District'' means a revenue district ;

            (ii) ``Government'' means the Government of Andhra Pradesh and includes any subordinate
            authority which may be declared by them, subject to such conditions as they think fit,
            to be Government for all or any of the purposes of these rules;
            Provided that the powers and functions of Government under these rules shall, in
            relation to the members of the staff of the Governor’s Secretariat, be exercised by the
            Governor of Andhra Pradesh.

            (iii) ``Government Employee'' means any person who is a member of a civil service of the
            state of Andhra Pradesh or holds any civil post under the State or in connection with
            the affairs of the State, whether he is on duty or under suspension or on leave or on
            foreign service either within or outside the State;

            (iv) ``Head of Department'' means the authority declared as such in Appendix-I to the
            Andhra Pradesh Financial code, Volume-II.

            (v) "Member of the family" in relation to a Government employee, includes the spouse,
            son, daughter, step-son or step-daughter of such employee, whether residing with such
            employee or not, and any other person related to, and residing with, such employee and
            wholly dependent on such employee; but does not include a spouse legally separated from
            such employee, or a son, daughter, step-son or step-daughter who is no longer in any way
            dependent upon such employee, or of whose custody such employee is deprived by law;

            (vi) “State” State means the State of Andhra Pradesh.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.03 --


            General :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) Every Government employee shall be devoted to his duty and shall maintain absolute
            integrity, discipline, impartiality and a sense of propriety.

            (2) No Government employee shall behave in a manner which is unbecoming of such employee
            or derogatory to the prestige of Government.

            (3) No Government employee shall act in a manner which will place his official position
            under any kind of embarrassment.

            G.O.Ms.No. 1009, GA (Ser C) Dept., Dt.18-6-65 :

            (4) No Government Employee shall, in the performance of his official duties or in the
            exercise of powers conferred on him, act otherwise than in his best judgment except when
            he is acting under the direction of his official superior, and shall where he is acting
            under such direction, obtain the direction in writing, wherever practicable, and where
            it is not practicable to obtain the direction in writing shall obtain written
            confirmation of the direction as soon thereafter as possible. It shall be incumbent on
            such official superior to confirm in writing the oral directions given by him, and in
            any event, he shall not refuse such written confirmation where a request is made by the
            Government employee to whom such direction was given.

            Explanation : Nothing, in sub-rule (4) shall be construed as empowering a Government
            employee to evade his responsibilities by seeking instructions from or approval of, as
            official superior where, such instructions are not necessary under the scheme of
            distribution of powers and responsibilities.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.03 A --


            Joining of associations by Govt. Employees :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government employee shall join, or continue to be a member of, an association the
            object or activities of which are prejudicial to the interests of the sovereignty and
            integrity of India or public order.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.03 B --


            G.O.Ms.No. 72, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt. 3-3-98.
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            "Promptness and courtesy No Government Servant shall -

            (a) in the performance of his official duties, act in a discourteous manner;

            (b) in his official dealings with the public or otherwise adopt dilatory tactics or
            wilfully cause delay in disposal of the work assigned to him."
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.03 C --


            Prohibition of sexual harassment of working women :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            ``No Government employee shall in the performance of his official duties act in a
            discourteous and discriminate manner with any working women or indulge in sexual
            harassment either directly or by implication''.

            Explanation :- For the purpose of this rule Sexual Harassment includes such unwelcome
            activities either directly or by implication have,-

            a) physical contact and advances:

            b) a demand or request for sexual favours;

            c) sexually coloured remarks;

            d) showing pomography;

            e) any other unwelcome physical, verbal or non-verbal conduct of sexual nature.
            Such conduct which amounts to a specific offence under the Indian Penal Code, 1860 or
            under any other Law for the time being in force. (G.O.Ms.No. 322, G.A.(Ser.C) Dept., dt:
            19-7-1999)
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.03 D --
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Complaints Committee will be deemed to be an inquiry committee and the report submitted
            by it shall be deemed to be an inquiry report under Andhra Pradesh Civil Services
            (Classification Control and Appeal) Rules, 1991. (G.O.Ms.No. 556, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept.,
            Dt. 14-12-2005)


            (5) ``Every Government servant holding a supervisory post shall take all possible
            steps to ensure the integrity and devotion to duty of all Government servants for the
            time being under his control and authority''.
            Explanation :- ``A Government servant who habitually fails to perform the task assigned
            to him within the time set for the purpose and with the quality of performance expected
            of him shall be deemed to be lacking in devotion to duty.’' (G.O.Ms.No. 381, G.A.
            (Ser.C) Dept., dt: 18-12-2003)

            (6) Prohibition regarding employment of children below 14 years of age:- No member of
            the service shall employ to work any child below the age of 14 years.
            (G.O.Ms.No. 555, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt. 14-12-2005)
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.04 --


            Strikes :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            No Government employee shall participate in any strike or similar activities or
            incitement thereto.
            Explanation:- The expression "Similar activities" shall be deemed to include-

            (i) absence from duty or work without permission.

            (ii) neglect of duty with the object of compelling any superior officer or Government to
            take or omit to take any official action;

            (iii) any demonstrative fast, like Hunger Strike with the object mentioned in item (ii);
            or

            (iv) concerted or organized refusal on the part of Government employees to receive their
            pay.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.05 --


            Demonstrations G.O.Ms.No. 1009, G.A.(Ser.C) Dept., Dt.18-6-65 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government employee shall participate in any demonstration which is against the
            interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India or Pubic order.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.06 --


            Gifts, Service Entertainment addresses and addresses and other forms of felicitation :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            (1) No Government employee shall :-

            (i)accept, or permit any member of his family to accept from any person any gift, the
            receipt of which, or any service the performance of which will place such employee under
            any kind of official obligation or embarrassment in relation to any person if, however,
            the offer of a gift cannot be refused without giving undue offence to the donor, it may
            be accepted and the matter reported to the Government for decision as not its disposal;
            or


            (ii) receive any address or accept any felicitation or entertainment held in his honour;

            Provided that nothing in this sub-rule shall apply to :-
            (a) gifts of flowers or fruits of trifling value.

            (b) gifts of a value, reasonable in all circumstances of the case, from relations, and
            gifts of a value of less than two hundred rupees from personal friends presented to a
            Government employee or to any member of his family on ceremonial occasions such
            weddings;

            (c) the performance of an occasional service of a trifling character;

            (d) the sitting for a group photo with officers and the members of the staff of his
            office.


            G.O.Ms.No.1093, G.A.(Ser.C) Dept., Dt.30-9-64

            (iii) stay in any Guest House owned by a private person and enjoy his hospitality.

            (2) If any question arises whether the receipt of a gift or the performance of a service
            places the Government employee under any kind of official obligation or embarrassment,
            the decision of Government thereon shall be final.

            (3) No Government employee shall receive any towel, key, scissors or other similar
            articles offered to him in connection with any ceremonial function such as the laying of
            foundation stone or the opening of a building.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.6 A --


            G.O.Ms.No.354, G.A.(Ser.C) Dept., Dt.8-8-1996 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            6-A: Every Government Employee shall intimate to the Competent Authority within fifteen
            days from the date of receipt of any foreign currency or foreign goods of value of more
            than Rs.10,000/- from any person by him or by any person of his family or by any person
            on their behalf, in the form given in the Annexure III to these rules.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.07 --


            Subscriptions :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government employee shall, except with the previous sanction of Government, ask for,
            or accept or in any way participate in the raising of, any subscriptions or other
            pecuniary assistance in pursuance of any object whatsoever.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>


            Lending borrowing and insolvency G.O.Ms.No. 224, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept Dt.23-3-74 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall, save in ordinary course of business with a bank or a
            public limited company, himself or through any member of his family or any person acting
            on his behalf.

            (a) lend or borrow or deposit money as a principal or agent, to, or from, or with any
            person or firm or private limited company within the local limits of his authority or
            with whom he is likely to have official dealings or otherwise place himself, under
            pecuniary obligation to such person or firm; or

            (b) lend money to any person at interest or in manner whereby return in money or kind is
            charged or paid ;
            Provided that a Government employee may give to, or accept from a relative or a personal
            friend a purely temporary loan of small amount free of interest or operate a credit
            account with a bonafide tradesman or make an advance of pay to his private employee;
            Provided further that nothing in this sub-rule shall apply in respect of any transaction
            entered into by a Government employee with the previous sanction of the Government.

            (1-A) When a Government employee is appointed or transferred to a post of such nature as
            would embarrass or influence him in the discharge of his official duties or involve him
            in the breach of any of the provisions of sub-rule (1). He shall forthwith report the
            circumstances to the Government and shall thereafter act in accordance with such order
            as may be made by the Government.


            (2) The prohibition in sub-rule (1) shall not apply to :-

            (i) any transaction of a Government employee with a co-operative society registered or
            deemed to have been registered under the law relating to co-operative societies for the
            time being in force in the State;

            (ii) a Government Employee who lends money while
            acting as an executor, administrator or a trustee without profit or advantage to
            himself;

            (iii) a Government employee who belongs to a Joint Hindu Family carrying on the business
            of money lending as a ancestral profession, provided the takes no active share in that
            business and is not employed in the district in which the said business of the family is
            carried on.


            (3) A Government Employee shall so manage his private affairs as to avoid habitual
            indebtedness or insolvency. A Government employee who is involved in legal proceedings
            for insolvency shall forthwith report the full facts to Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>


            Acquiring or disposing of immovable property :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall, except after previous intimation to Government,
            acquire or dispose of or permit any member of his family to acquire or dispose of, any
            immovable property by exchange, purchase, sale, gift or otherwise either by himself or
            through others.

            G.O.Ms.No.807 G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.2-12-77.

            his family accepts “Advance of Rent” from a prospective tenant for the construction or
            completion of a building to be rented, it constitutes a transaction in immovable
            property and falls within the scope of the above sub-rule.
            Provided that any such transaction conducted otherwise than through a regular or reputed
            dealer shall be with the previous sanction of Government.
            “Provided that any such a transaction conducted otherwise than through a regular or
            reputed dealer viz.,

            (i) Banking institutions, including Co-operative Banks;

            (ii) Financial Corporations set up by the State Governments which provide loans for
            house constructions ;

            (iii) Apex Co-operative Housing Finance Institutions such as Delhi Co-operative Housing
            Finance Society; and

            (iv) Public Companies formed and registered in India with the main object of carrying on
            the business of providing long term finance for construction or purchase of houses in
            India for residential purposes like the Housing Development Finance Corporation Limited,
            LIC., CANFIN and Nationalised Banks,

            Shall be with the previous sanction of the Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>G.O.Ms.No.602, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.30-11-82, G.O.Ms.No.105, G.A. (Ser.C)
            Dept., Dt.20-2-84 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Provided further that no Government employee shall acquire or permit any member of his
            family to acquire any immovable property in any area in which land developmental schemes
            are under execution by or contemplation of, the Department in which the employee is
            employed.
            ``Provided further that the Government employee shall submit the particulars giving
            prior intimation or seeking prior sanction, in the following format :-
            1) Name and Designation

            2) Scale of Pay and Present Pay

            3) Purpose of application – sanction for transaction / prior intimation or transaction

            4) Whether property is being acquired or disposed of.

            5) Probable date of acquisition / disposal of property

            6) Mode of acquisition/ disposal

            7) (a) Full details about location Viz., Municipal No., Street/ Village, Mandal,
            District and State in which situated.
            (b) Description of the property in the case of cultivable land, dry or irrigated land.
            (c) Whether free hold or leasehold

            (d) Whether the applicants interest in the property is in full or part (in case of
            partial interest, the extent of such interest must indicated)
            (e) in case the transaction is not exclusively in the name of the Government servant
            particulars of ownership and share of each member.

            (8) Sale/ purchase price of the property (Market value in the case of gifts)

            (8)(A) The Government or any authority empowered by them in this behalf may, require a
            Government servant to render a ful and true account of the cash found his possession at
            any time and such account shall include particulars of the means by which and the
            sources from which such cash was acquired. (G.O.Ms.No. 7, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept.,
            Dt.16-1-2004)
            Earlier position :-

            8(A) The Government or any authority empowered by them in this behalf may, require a
            Government servant to make it obligatory to Government Servant to account for possession
            of huge cash. (G.O.Ms.No. 381, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt 18.12.2003).

            8(B) The Government or any authority empowered by them in this behalf may, by general or
            special order require a Government servant on duty not to keep cash in his possession
            beyond a specified sum and to declare the case in his possession in the manner
            prescribed. (G.O.Ms.No. 381 G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt. 18-12-2003


            (9) In cases of acquisition, source or sources from which financed / proposed to be
            financed :-
            (a) Personal savings
            (b) Other sources giving details

            (10) in the case of disposal of property, was requisite sanction / intimation obtained
            given for its acquisition. A copy of the sanction/ acknowledgement should be attached.

            (11) (a) Name and address of the party with whom transaction is proposed to be made.
            (b) Is the party related to the applicant? If so, state the relationship.
            (c) Did the applicant have any dealings with the party in his official capacity at any
            time, or is the applicant likely to have any dealings with him in the near future?
            (d) How was the transaction arranged? (whether through any statutory body or a private
            agency through advertisement or through friends and relatives. Full particulars to be
            given)

            (12) Any other relevant fact which the applicant may like to mention.
            Declaration
            I, ……………… hereby declare that the particulars given above are true. I request that I may
            be given permission to acquire/ dispose of property as described above from/ to the
            party whose name is mentioned in item 11 above. OR
            I, ………..... hereby intimate the proposed acquisition/ disposal of property by me as
            detailed above. I declare that the particulars given above are true Station : Signature
            : Date : Designation:
            Note : 1) In the above form, different portions may be used according to requirement.
            2) Where previous sanction is asked for, the application should be submitted at least 30
            days before the proposed date of the transaction.
            Provided also that the Government employee shall submit the request to Government
            seeking prior permission duly obtained acknowledgement of having made such a request and
            if no permission is received within one month, he / she may go ahead with the
            transaction.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>G.O.Ms.No.705, G.A. (Ser C) Dept., Dt.28-11-84 G.O.Ms.No.471 G.A.(Ser. C) Dept.,
            Dt.17-9-94 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (2) A Government employee who enters into any transaction concerning any movable
            property exceeding rupees fifty thousand in value, whether by way of purchase, sale or
            otherwise, shall forth with report such transaction to Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>G.O.Ms.No. 681, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt. 11-9-07 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Provided that any such transaction conducted otherwise than through a regular or reputed
            dealer shall be with the previous sanction of Government.

            (3) Nothing in sub-rule (2) shall apply to any purchases made by a Government employee
            for the performance of weddings, religious or special functions.

            (4) No Government employee shall engage in any transaction which is of a speculative
            character relating to the purchase, sale or exchange of any immovable or movable
            property.

            (5) The provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2) shall not apply to--

            (i) the acquisition or possession of any property as trustee, executor or administrator;
            (ii) any Government land which is sold or granted on lease to any Government employee,
            in accordance with the rules in force.

            (6) Except with the sanction of Government, no Government employee shall purchase,
            directly or indirectly in a sale by auction or otherwise conducted by or under the
            orders of the Department in which he is employed, any immovable or movable property
            owned or confiscated by Government.


        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>
            G.O.Ms.No.705, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.28-11-84,
            G.O.Ms.No.52, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.4-2-88,
            G.O.Ms.No.471, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.17-9-94,
            G.O.Ms.No.681, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.11-9-07.
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (7) Every Government Employee, other than member of the Andhra Pradesh Last Grade
            Service and a Record Assistant in the Andhra Pradesh General Sub-ordinate Service, shall
            on first appointment to the Government Service submit to Government a statement of all
            immovable property/ properties irrespective of its value and movable property/
            properties whose value exceeds Rs.50,000/- owned, acquired or inherited by him or held
            by him on lease or mortgage either in his own name or in the name of any member of his
            family, in the forms prescribed in Annexure-I and II separately. He shall also submit to
            Government before 15 January of each year, through the proper channel, a declaration in
            the forms given in the Annexure-I and II of all immovable/movable property/properties
            owned, acquired or inherited by him or held by him on lease or mortgage, either in his
            own name or in the name of any member of his family. The declaration shall contain such
            further information as Government may, by a general or special order require. If in any
            year, a Government employee has not acquired or disposed of any immovable or movable
            property or any interest therein, he shall submit declaration to that effect.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>
            G.O.Ms.No.881, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.11-11-70 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Provided that every Head Constable, Police Constable and every person of the
            corresponding rank in the Armed Reserve and Special Police Battalions and every
            non-gazetted Officers of equal rank in their branches of the Police Department, shall
            submit the Statements in forms prescribed in Annexure-I and II and the declaration
            aforesaid to the superintendent of Police or the Commandant Concerned, as the case my
            be.
            (2) for the Annexure, the following Annexures shall be substituted, namely:-
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>ANNEXURE-I
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Statement of immovable property possessed, acquired and disposed of by Sri ------ --- or
            any other person on his behalf or any member of his family during year ending
            --------------- (Sub-rule (7) of rule 9 of APCS (Conduct) Rules 1964)-


            1. Nature of property

            2. Situation of property (Survery Municipal No. with extent.

            3. Held in whose name

            4. Date and mode of acquisition/disposal

            5. Price paid/ obtained

            6. source of Payment

            7. Whether information given or sanction obtained (with ref. no .and date)

            8. Annual income from property


            Note:- Details of acquisition of properties standing in the name of Hindu undivided
            family or partnership in which the officer holds a claim or share should be separately
            shown in the statement.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>ANNEXURE -II
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Statement of movable property possessed, acquired and disposed of by Sri
            ...............or any another person on his behalf or by any member of his family during
            year ending....................... (Sub-rule (7) of rule 9 of APCS (Conduct) Rules 1964)

            1. Nature of property

            a) Motor Car
            b) Motor Cycle/ Scooter any other vehicle.
            c) Electrical Goods: Air Conditioner
            d) V.C.R./Television. Refrigerator,
            e) Any other goods.
            f) Jewellery:
            g) Ornaments
            h) Vessels etc.
            i) Investment and Cash:
            j) Bank deposits/Debentures/ Shares/Bank Balances etc
            k) Furniture:
            l) Live stock
            m) Any other goods

            2. Held in whose name

            3. date and mode of acquisition/ disposal

            4. Name and addrress of person from whom acquired/ to whom disposed of

            5. Whether transaction done within the limits of Jurisdiction

            6. Price paid/obtained

            7. Source of payment.

            Note: Details of acquisition of properties standing in the name of Hind undivided family
            or partnership in which the officer holds a claim or share should be separately shown in
            the statement.

            (8) The Government, or any authority empowered by them in this behalf may, at any time,
            by general or special order, require a Government employee to submit, within a specified
            period, a full and complete statement of all immovable property and movable property, of
            the specified value, held or acquired by him or by any member of his family. Such
            statement shall, if so required by Government or by the authority so empowered, include
            particulars of the means by which or the sources from which, such property was acquired.

            (9) If a Government employee receives an order of transfer to a district in which he
            possesses, or has an interest in any immovable property, he shall forthwith report the
            fact to his immediate superior officer.

            (10) for the purposes of this rule, --- (A) In
            respect of the Government employee serving under their control, the under mentioned
            authorities are declared to be Government for each of the categories of employees as
            specified below:

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>(I) POSTS OUT-SIDE THE PURVIEW OF THE ANDHRA PRADESH PUBLIC EMPLOYEMENT
            (ORGANIZATION
            OF LOCAL CADRES AND REGULATION OF DIRECT RECRUITMENT) ORDER, 1975 (herein after referred
            to as presidential order).
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) Heads of Departments and Offices holding equivalent posts in the Department --
            Government.

            (2) All second level Gazetted posts and above except second level Gezetted posts,
            included in schedule -III of the Presidential Order. -- Head of the Department.

            G.O.Ms.No. 567, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., Dt.15-10-88

            (3) First level Gazetted posts which do not fall within the purview of the Presidential
            Order -- Head of the Department.

            (4) Posts in Secretariat:

            (a) Assistant Secretary to Government and above. -- Chief Secretary to Government.

            (b) Section Officers and Private Secretaries to Secretaries -- Principal Secretary/
            Secretary / Ex-Officio Secretary concerned.

            (c) Asst. Section Officer and all other non-Gazetted categories -- Additional/Joint/
            Deputy Secretary to Government Concerned.

            (5) Posts in the Office of the Heads of Departments/State level Offices and other
            Offices not covered by the Presidential Orders --
            (a) Head of the Department concerned
            (b) Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission.
            (c) Secretary to Governor
            (d) Sales Tax Appellate Tribunal
            (e) Labour Court
            (f)Industrial Tribunal
            (g)Andhra Pradesh Administrative Tribunal.


            (6) Non-Gazetted posts in the Offices, other than the Offices of the Heads of
            Departments and State Level Offices etc. -- Appointing Authority.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>II. POSTS WHICH FALL WITHIN THE PURVIEW OF THE ANDHRA PRADESH PUBLIC
            EMPLOYMENT (OLC and RDR) ORDER, 1975 (hereinafter referred to as Presidential
            order).
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) Second Level Gazetted Posts which have been organized into Zonal/ Multi Zonal
            cadres in pursuance of the provisions of the Presidential Order -- Heads of the
            Department.

            (2) First Level Gazetted Posts which have been organized into Zonal/Multi Zonal
            Cadres in pursuance of the provisions of the Presidential Order -- Regional Officers
            having Jurisdiction over the respective Zones/Multi Zones in respect of the relevant
            local cadres. where regional setup exists or the Officers next below the Head of the
            department in the Office of the Head of the Department where no regional set up
            exists.

            (3) Non-Gazetted categories of posts which have been organized into Zonal/Multi
            Zonal cadres in pursuance of the presidential order -- Regional Officer or other
            officers who administer the relevant Zonal/Multi Zonal Cadres.

            (4) Non-Gazetted categories of which have been organized into District or less
            than District cadres in pursuance of the presidential order -- Collectors and other
            District officers concerned or Officers who administer such District or less than
            district cadres.

            (B) in respect of Government employees serving on deputation either under Central
            Government or any State Government the appropriate Government under which the
            Government employee is serving shall be deemed to be Government.

        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.10 --

            Private Trade Business and as Investment :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall engage directly or indirectly in any trade or
            business save in the course of his official duties.

            G.O.Ms.No. 1025, G.A. (Ser.C) Department, Dt. 5-12-67

            Explanation: Canvassing by a Government servant in support of the business of
            Insurance agency. Commission agency and the like owned or managed by his wife or any
            other member of his family shall be deemed to be breach of this sub-rule

            (1-A) Every Government employee shall report to the Government if any member of his
            family is engaged in trade and business or owns or manages an insurance agency or
            Commission agency.

            (2) No Government employee shall speculate in any investment.

            (3) No Government employee shall make, or permit any member of his family to make,
            any investment likely to embarrass or influence him in the discharge of his Official
            duties.

            (4) The decision of Government shall be final in respect of any question arising
            under this rule.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.11 --


            Promotions and Management of companies in Private capacity :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government employee shall in his private capacity, except with the previous
            sanction of Government, take part in the promotion, registration or management of
            any bank or other company registered under the relevant law for the time being in
            force.
            Provided that a Government employee may, in accordance with the provisions of any
            general or special order of Government, take part in the promotion, registration or
            management of a co-operative society registered under any law relating to
            co-operative societies for the time being in force in the State:
            Provided further that no Government employee shall, without the previous sanction of
            the Government except in the discharge of his official duties, take part in
            promotion, registration or management of any co-operative society for Commercial
            purpose.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.12 --


            Private Employment :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            No Government employee shall , except with the previous sanction of Government
            negotiate for or undertake any employment or work other than that connected with the
            official duties.

            G.O.Ms.No.73, GA (Ser-C) Dept. Dt. 12-2-1968.

            G.O.Ms.No.542, GA (Ser-C) Dept. Dt. 24-8-68. Proviso

            G.O. Ms. No.911, GA (Ser-C) Dept. Dt.8-10-1971.

            G.O.Ms.No.1074, GA (Ser-C) Dept. Dt. 16-11-1971. G.O.Ms.No.1219, GA (Ser-C) Dept.
            Dt. 18-12-71.

            Provided that a Government employee may, without such sanction, participate in
            sports activities as an amateur, undertake honorary work of a special or charitable
            nature, or occasional work of literary artistic or scientific character or any
            examinership or remuneration, offered therefore by the Union Public Service
            Commission, Institute of Secretariat training and management of Government of India,
            the Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission, the State Board of Technical Education
            and training or the board of Secondary Education, Andhra Pradesh or by any of the
            Universities in the State of Andhra Pradesh, the Board of Intermediate Education,
            Andhra Pradesh, Subject to the condition that such work or examinership does not
            interfere with his official duties but he shall not undertake or shall discontinue
            such work; or examinership, if so directed by Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.13 --


            Publications of books. :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government employee shall, without the previous permission of Government, publish
            any book, which is not purely of a literary artistic or scientific character. While
            applying for permission to publish a book he shall submit to Government a manuscript
            copy thereof :

            G.O.Ms.No.1591, GA (Ser-C) Dept. Dt. 25-8-1965.

            Provided that an employee who publishes book with or without the previous permission
            of Government shall not canvass for its sale in any manner and it shall also be open
            to Government to insist on the sale of the Copyright in any such book.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.14 --


            Communication of official documents or information :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government Employee shall, except accordance with any general or special order of
            Government, communicate directly or indirectly any official document or any of its
            contents or any official information, to any Government employee not authorized to
            receive the same, or to any non-official person or the Press.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.15 --


            Connection with Press :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government employee shall except with the previous sanction of Government, own
            wholly or in part, or conduct, or participate in the editing or the management of,
            any newspaper or non-government publication.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.16 --


            Participation in Radio Broadcast contribution to News papers and Periodicals
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall, except with the previous sanction of Government or
            any authority empowered by them in this behalf or in the course of discharge of his
            official duties, participate in a Radio broadcast or Drama or Tele-serial or Feature
            Film or contribute any article or write any letter in his own name or anonymously,
            pseudonymously or in the name of any other person to a newspaper or periodical:
            Provided that no such sanction is necessary if such broadcast or Drama or
            Tele-serial or Feature Film or article or letter is of a purely literary, artistic
            or scientific character, or if such broadcast relates to a talk arranged under the
            general or special order of Government; and the Government employee may accept the
            remuneration prescribed for such broadcasts, Dramas or Tele-serials or Feature Films
            or articles or letters.


            EARLIER POSITION

            Participation in Radio Broadcast contribution to news papers and periodicals :

            (1) No Government employee shall, except with the previous sanction of Government or
            any authority empowered by them in this behalf or in the course of discharge of his
            official duties, participate in a radio broad cast or contribute any article or
            write any letter in his own name or anonymously, pseudonymously or in the name of
            any other person to a newspaper or periodical:

            G.O.Ms.No.1880, GA (Ser-C) Dept. Dt. 19-10-1965

            Provided that no such sanction is necessary if such broadcast article or letter is
            of pure literary, astistic or scientific character, or if such broadcast relates to
            a talk arranged under the general or special order of Government; and the Government
            employee may accept the remuneration prescribed for such broadcasts, articles or
            letters.

            (2) For the purpose of sub-rule (1), a Secretary to Government or a Head of
            Department may exercise the power of Government in respect of Government employees
            under his control, and may refer any case to Government for orders if he considers
            such a course desirable.

        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.17 --


            Criticism of the policy or action of Govt. or any other State Govt. or Central Govt.
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall, by any public utterance, written or otherwise,
            criticise any policy or action of Government or any other State Government the
            Central Government; nor shall he participate in any such criticism;
            Provided that nothing in this rule shall be deemed to prohibit any Government
            employee from participating in discussions, at any private meeting solely of
            Government employees or of any association of Government employees of matters which
            effect the interest of such employees individually or generally;

            (2) No Government employee shall, in any writing published by him, or in any
            communication made by him to the press, or in any public utterance delivered by him,
            make any statement of fact or opinion which is likely to embrass-
            (i) The relations between the Central Government or the Government of any State and
            the people of India or any section there of.
            (ii) the relations between the Central Government and the Government of any foreign
            State.

            (3) A Government employee who intends to publish any document or to make any
            communication to the press or to deliver any public utterance containing statements
            in respect of which any doubt as to the application of the restrictions imposed by
            sub-rule (2) may arise, shall submit to Government the draft of such document,
            communication or utterance and shall, thereafter, act in accordance with such orders
            as may be passed by Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.18 --

        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall give evidence in connection with any inquiry
            conducted by any committee, Commission or other authority:-

            (a) in India, except with the previous permission of Government;

            (b) outside India, except with the previous sanction of the Central Government;


            (2) There any sanction is accorded under sub-rule (1), no Government employee giving
            such evidence shall criticise the policy of the Central Government or of a State
            Government.


            (3) Nothing in sub-rule (1) shall apply to--

            (a) evidence given before a statutory committee, commission or other authority which
            has power to compel attendance and the giving of answers;

            (b) evidence given in judicial inquiries;

            (c) evidence given at any departmental inquiry ordered by Government or any
            authority subordinate to them
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.19 --


            Amendment to G.O.Ms.No.77, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.8-02-90
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall be a member of, or be otherwise associated with,
            any political party or any organisation in respect of which there is slightest
            reason to think that the organisation has a political aspect and takes part in
            politics; nor shall he participate in, subscribe in aid of, or assist in any other
            manner, any political movement or activity.


            (2) It shall be the duty of every Government employee to endeavour to prevent any
            member of his family from taking part in, subscribing in
            aid of, or assisting in any manner any movement or activity which is, or tends
            directly or indirectly to be, sub-versive of the Central Government or of a State
            Government, being prejudicial to national security; and where a Government employee
            is unable to prevent a member of his family from taking part in, or subscribing in
            aid of, or assisting in any other manner, any such movement or activity, he shall
            make a report to that effect to Government.


            (3) Nothing in sub-rule (2) shall apply in respect of any member of the family of a
            Government employee standing for an election to Parliament or any House of a State
            Legislature or local authority or body or canvassing for other candidates in any
            such election.


            (4) If any question arises as to whether any movement or activity falls within the
            scope of this rule, the decision of Government thereon shall be final.


            (5) No Government employee shall canvass or otherwise interfere or use his
            influence, in connection with, or take part in, an election to Parliament or any
            House of a State Legislature or any local authority or body:
            Provided that:-
            (i) A Government employee qualified to vote at such election may cost his vote but,
            where he does so, he shall give no indication of the manner in which he proposes to
            vote or has voted;
            (ii) a Government employee shall not be deemed to have contravened the provisions of
            this rule by reason only that he has assisted in the conduct of an election in the
            due performance of a duty imposed on him by or under any law for the time being in
            force.


            (6) The display by a Government employee on his person, vehicle, residence or any of
            his property, of any election symbol shall amount to using his influence in
            connection with an election within the meaning of sub-rule (5).


            (7) The provisions of sub-rules (5) and (6) shall not apply to a Government employee
            required or permitted by or under any law or order of Government to be a candidate
            at an election to a local authority or body.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.20 --


            Vindication of acts and character of a Government employee as such :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) No Government employee shall, except with the previous sanction of Government,
            have recourse to the press or any court for the vindication of his official act
            which has been the subject matter of adverse criticism or an attack of a defamatory
            character in public.


            (2) Nothing in sub-rule (1) shall be deemed to prohibit a Government employee from
            vindicating his private character or an act done by him in his private capacity.


            (3) No Government employee shall, except with the previous sanction of Government,
            accept from any person or body compensation of any kind for malicious prosecution or
            defamatory attack in respect of his official act unless such compensation has been
            awarded by a competent court of law.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.21 --


            Working with or under, near relatives in Govt. Service :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) Every member of a State Service shall inform his immediate official superior if a
            member of a State or Subordinate Service, who is his near relative is to work under him.

            (2) Every member of a State or Subordinate Service shall inform his immediate official
            superior if he is to work under a member of an All India Service or a State Service who
            is his near relative.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.22 --


            Employment of a member of the family in a private firm :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Whenever a member of the family of a Government employee who is solely dependent on him
            wishes to accept employment under any person, or with any firm or company, having
            official connection with such Government employee or Government, the Government employee
            shall obtain the prior sanction of Government for such employment.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.23 --


            Govt. employee not to deal in his official capacity with matters concerning himself, his
            relatives or dependents :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No Government employee shall deal, in his official capacity, with any matter which
            directly or indirectly concerns himself or any of his relatives or dependents.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.24 --


            Influencing the authorities for furtherance of interests :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            (1) No Government employee shall bring or attempt to bring any extraneous influence to
            bear upon any authority for the furtherance his interests.


            (2) A Government employee causing his own case to be made the subject of an
            interpellation in either House of Parliament or State Legislature or of discussion in
            the Andhra Pradesh Regional Committee shall be deemed to have contravened the provisions
            of sub-rule (1).

            G.O.Ms.No.1481, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.06-08-65.

            (3) It will be improper for a Government employee who makes any representation to the
            competent authority through the proper channel, to bother the higher authorities with
            advance copies thereof:
            Provided that a Government employee may send a copy of any representation made to the
            competent authority through the proper channel, direct to the higher authorities if the
            representation is made after exhausting such of the statutory remedies as were open to
            him and after receiving intimation that his representation has been withheld.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.25 --


            G.O.Ms.No.1009 G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.10-06-65. Bigamous marriage :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            (1) No Government employee who has a wife living shall contract another marriage without
            first obtaining the permission of the Government, notwithstanding that such subsequent
            marriage is permissible under the personal law for the time being applicable to him.

            G.O.Ms.No. 168, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.06.03.1990

            "Provided that where the personal law provides for second or subsequent marriage, the
            Government employee shall, while seeking permission to contract another marriage,
            produce documentary evidence in support of "Divorce or Talaq" in respect of previous
            marriage and the manner in which the same was secured or pronounced and intimated to the
            first or former wife".

            G.O.Ms.No. 168, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.06.03.1990

            (2) "No female Government servant, whether unmarried or widow or divorced, as the case
            may be, shall marry any person who has a wife living without first obtaining the
            permission of the Government, though the parties are governed by the personal law which
            otherwise permits contracting more than one marriage while the prior marriage is
            subsisting".


            EARLIER POSITION


            (2) No female Government employee shall marry any person who has a wife living without
            first obtaining the permission of the Government

            G.O.Ms.No.1009, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept. dt.10-06-65. Dowry

            A No Government servant shall--

            (1) give or take or abet in giving or taking of dowry; or

            (2) demand, directly or indirectly, from the parents or guardian of a bride or
            bridegroom as the case may be; any dowry.
            Explanation:- for the purpose of this rule "dowry" has the same meaning as in the Dowry
            Prohibition Act, 1961. (A Central Act 28 of 1961).
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.26 --


            DRINKING (G.O.Ms.No.513, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.19.12.2002) :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            Notwithstanding anything contained in the provisions of any Law relating to intoxicating
            drinks or drugs for the time being in force in any area, no Government employee shall -

            (i) while on duty, be under the influence of such drinks or drugs to such an extent as
            to render him incapable of discharging his duty properly and efficiently; or

            (ii) appear in a public place in a state of intoxication; or

            (iii) consume such drinks or drugs in excess.”


            EARLIER POSITION


            Drinking Substituted in G.O.Ms.No.393, G.A.(Ser.C) Dept., dt.06-09-96.

            Save as provided in any law for the time being in force relating to intoxicating liquors
            or narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances, no Government employee shall sell, buy,
            transport, possess, consume or otherwise deal with any such intoxicating liquor or
            drink, narcotic drug or psychotropic substance.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.27 --

            Interpretation :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            If any question arises relating to the interpretation of these rules, the decision of
            Government thereon shall be final.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.28 --


            Repeal :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            The Government Servants Conduct Rules, 1958, are hereby repealed:
            Provided that such repeal shall not affect the previous operation of any action taken or
            orders or instructions issued thereunder, and subject thereto, anything done or any
            action taken under the rules so repealed shall be deemed to have been done or taken
            under these rules.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.29 --


            Saving of other Laws :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            The provisions of these rules shall be in addition to, and not in derogation, of any
            other law or order of any competent authority, for the time being in force, regulating
            the conduct of Government employees in the State.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>ANNEXURE -III


            (Rule-6 A: G.O.Ms.No.354, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.8.8.1996.)
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>


            Intimation of Foreign Currency/Goods received by the Government employee Sri
            ......................................... under rule 6-A of the Andhra Pradesh Civil
            Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964.

            1. Name of the Government Servant:

            2. Designation and Official Address:

            3. Department to which he belongs.

            4. Date of receiving/accepting of Foreign Currency/Goods.

            5. Nature of the Foreign Currency/Goods received/accepted.

            6. Sources from which received/accepted.

            7. Reason/purpose for which the foreign currency/goods were received/accepted.

            8. The relationship of the sender to the recipient and name, occupation and full address
            of the sender:

            9. Whether the foreign currency/goods received/ accepted were intimated to the concerned
            authorities and customs or to the appropriate authority:

            10.Whether the foreign currency/goods received/accepted were declared to Income Tax
            Department. If so, details to be furnished.

            11.Mode and method of receipt/acceptance of the foreign currency/goods by the Government
            employee or his dependents.

            12.Whether the Government employee having any official dealings from whom the foreign
            currency/goods were received/accepted;

            13.Details of any expenditure incurred by the Government Employee in receipt/acceptance
            of the foreign currency/goods.


            Signature of the Government Employee
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>


        </para_name>
        <para_desc>
            INSTRUCTIONS
            GOVERNMENT OF ANDHRA PRADESH GENERAL ADMINISTRATIN (SER.C) DEPARTMENT
            Circular Memo No.15486/Ser.C/2007 Dated :30-7-2007


            Sub:- Public Services – A.P. Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964 – Submission of Annual
            Property Returns by employees promptly – Reiteration of instructions – Reg.

            Ref:-1. Govt. Memo.No.442/SC.E/1983-1, G.A. (SC.E) Department, Dated 27.12.1983. 2.
            Circular Memo No.76883/Ser.C/98, G.A. (Ser.C) Department, Dated 12.12.1998. 3. Circular
            Memo No.8832/Ser.C/2003-1, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dated 29.1.2003. 4. Memo
            No.94649/Ser.C/2003, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.31.7.2003. 5. Circular Memo No.695, G.A.
            (Ser.C) Dept., dated 12.10.2006. * * * In the reference 5th cited, while reiterating the
            instructions regarding submission of Annual Property Returns by the Government employees
            as per sub-rule (7) of Rule-9 of A.P.C.S. (Conduct) Rules, 1964 it was requested in para
            8 of reference as follows:- “All the Spl. Chief Secretaries/Prl. Secretaries/Secretaries
            to Government and Heads of Departments etc. are requested to list out the employees who
            have not furnished their Annual Property Returns as on 15.1.2005 and thereafter issue
            show cause notices to each as to why disciplinary action shall not be taken against them
            and if within a reasonable time thereafter the Annual Property Returns are not received,
            or if the explanation to the query raised is not given or if given, but found not
            satisfactory, then they are requested to award “Censure” to the employee concerned”.
            2. Government after careful examination have decided to amend the above para as
            follows:-
            “All the Spl. Chief Secretaries/Prl. Secretaries/Secretaries to Government and Heads of
            Departments etc are requested to list out the employees who have not furnished their
            Annual Property Returns in time, within a month after the last date for receiving such
            returns and proceed against such officers as per APCS (CCA) Rules, 1991 for violation of
            APCS (Conduct) Rules, 1964.” 3. All the Departments of Secretariat, All Heads of
            Departments and all District Collectors are requested to bring the above rule position
            to the notice of all the employees working under their control for their strict
            compliance. J. HARINARAYANA CHIEF SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT

            To All Special Chief Secretaries/Prl. Secretaries/Secretaries to Government. All
            Departments of Secretariat. All Heads of Departments. All District Collectors. All
            Services Sections of G.A.D., The Director General, Anti-Corruption Bureau, Hyd. The Law
            (E) Dept., The Secretary, APPSC, Hyd. The Secretary to Vigilance Commissioner, APVC,
            Hyd. The Registrar, Hon’ble APAT, Hyd. The Registrar, Hon’ble High Court of A.P., Hyd.
            SF/SC. // FORWARDED BY ORDER // SECTION OFFICER

        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>


        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            GOVERNMENT OF ANDHRA PRADESH GENERAL ADMINISTRATIN (SER.C) DEPARTMENT
            Circular Memo No.695/Ser.C/2006 Dated:12-10-2006

            Sub:- Public Services – A.P. Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964 – Submission of Annual
            Property Returns by employees promptly – Reiteration of Government instructions – Reg.
            Ref:-1. Govt. Memo.No.442/SC.E/1983-1, G.A. (SC.E) Department, Dated .27.12.1983.
            2.Govt. Memo.No.762/SC.D/1983-1, G.A. (SC.D) Department, Dated .21.5.1986. 3. Circular
            Memo No.76883/Ser.C/98, G.A. (Ser.C) Department, Dated. 12.12.1998. 4. Circular Memo.
            No.8832/Ser.C/2003-1, G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dated 29.1.2003. 5. Memo. No.94649/Ser.C/2003,
            G.A. (Ser.C) Dept., dt.31.7.2003. 6. From the Director General, Anti-Corruption Bureau,
            Letter Rc.No.114/RE-Cr.2/2001-S2, Dated 22-11-2005. * * * According to sub-rule (7) of
            rule 9 of A.P. Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964, every Government employee other
            than a member of the A.P. Last Grade Service and a Record Assistant in the A.P. General
            Sub-Ordinate Service, invariably has to submit his/her statement of all
            immovable/movable (values exceeding Rs.20,000/-) properties owned, acquired or inherited
            by him/her his/her family members in the prescribed proforma in the said rule as
            Annexures I and II before 15th January of each year. 2. According to sub-rule (8) of
            rule 9 of the Andhra Pradesh Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964 the Government or any
            authority empowered by them in this behalf may at any time by general or special order,
            require a Government employee to submit within a specified period, a full and complete
            statement of all immovable properties and movable properties. 3. Keeping the
            observations in the Annual Report of A.P. Vigilance Commission for the year 1996-1997,
            instructions were issued in the reference third cited directing the Controlling Officers
            or Chief Vigilance Officers/Vigilance Officers of Concerned Departments to scrutinize
            thoroughly the Annual Property Returns submitted by their subordinates and call for the
            clarifications from the Government Departments in case of doubts and to ensure
            submission of the returns by all concerned as such scrutiny would help to check the
            corruption of the Government employees to some extent at the initial stage itself.
            4. Further as per observations made in the High Level Committee Meeting held on 8-1-2003
            in the Chambers of Chief Secretary, while reiterating the instructions issued in the
            references third and fourth cited, the Controlling Officers or Chief Vigilance Officers/
            Vigilance Officers of concerned Departments were once again requested to ensure that
            every Record Assistant in the Andhra Pradesh General Sub-ordinate Service, invariably
            submit his/ her Annual Property Statement Returns every year by 15th January. 5. The
            Director General, Anti-Corruption Bureau, A.P., Hyderabad in the reference sixth cited,
            has informed that in many instances when the concerned authorities are addressed by the
            Anti-Corruption Bureau for furnishing information pertaining to the Annual Property
            Returns filed by the Accused Officers and their pay particulars, they are receiving
            replies stating that no Annual Property Returns are filed or they are not traceable with
            the Government. But the Annual Property Returns are required for the purpose of proving
            the case of assets disproportionate to the known sources of income of a Government
            Servant or otherwise. He has therefore requested to issue orders to the concerned
            authorities/ Departments for strict compliance of sub-rule (7) of rule 9 of the Andhra
            Pradesh Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964 and also requested to make the concerned
            Controlling Officers accountable for ensuring that all Subordinate Officers file Annual
            Property Returns as per the Rules. 6. While reiterating the instructions issued in the
            references third and fourth cited, Government further direct the Controlling Officers or
            Chief Vigilance Officers / Vigilance Officers of concerned Departments to ensure that
            every Government employee other than a member of the Andhra Pradesh Last Grade Service
            and Record Assistant in the Andhra Pradesh General Sub-ordinate Service, invariably
            submit his/ her Annual Property Statement Returns every year by 15th January as required
            under sub-rule (7) of rule 9 of the Andhra Pradesh Civil Services (Conduct) Rules 1964.
            It may be impressed on the employees that non-compliance of such instructions will
            attract disciplinary action. 7. The Heads of Departments concerned shall ensure that the
            employees under their control submit the Annual Property Statements and a certificate
            should be submitted to this effect by the Heads of Departments to the concerned
            Administrative Department at Secretariat level. 8. All the Special Chief Secretaries/
            Principal Secretaries/ Secretaries to Government and Heads of Departments etc are
            requested to list out the employees who have not furnished their Annual Property Returns
            as on 15.1.2005 and thereafter issue show cause notices to each as to why disciplinary
            action shall not be taken against them and if within a reasonable time thereafter the
            Annual Property Returns are not received, or if the explanation to the query raised is
            not given or if given, but found not satisfactory, then they are requested to award
            “Censure” to the employee concerned. 9. All the Departments of Secretariat, all Heads of
            Departments, and all District Collectors are requested to bring the above rule position
            to the notice of all the employees working under their control for their strict
            compliance. J. HARINARAYANA CHIEF SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT

            To All Special Chief Secretaries/Prl. Secretaries/Secretaries to Government. All Departments of Secretariat.
            All Heads of Departments. All District Collectors. All Services Sections of General
            Admiistration Department. The General Admiistration (Special.C) Department. The Director
            General, Anti-Corruption Bureau, Hyd. The Law (E) Dept., The Secretary, APPSC, Hyd. The
            Secretary to Vigilance Commissioner, APVC, Hyderabad. The Registrar, Hon’ble AP
            Administrative Tribunal, Hyderabad. The Registrar, Hon’ble High Court of A.P., Hyd.
            SF/SC. // FORWARDED BY ORDER // SECTION OFFICER.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

</Ebook>
