<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Ebook>

    <para>
        <para_name Color = "RED">P.S No.01 -- Intent and reference to Andhra Pradesh Standard Specifications:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            It is intended by these Andhra Pradesh Standard Specifications to describe:
            (a) the character of the materials to be used;
            (b) the method of execution of work; and
            (c) the contractor’s responsibilities and liabilities to the Public, Government, and his
            workmen and general contract conditions which are to be accepted by every contractor who
            executes work entrusted to him by the Public Works Department of Andhra Pradesh.
            Whenever the term “Standard Specification” or the abbreviation “A.P.S.S.” is used in
            estimates or contract documents, it shall refer to the relevant specification in the
            Andhra Pradesh Standard Specifications book and its addenda volume.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.02 -- Applicability of the Andhra Pradesh Standard Specifications:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            It shall be unnecessary to include in any contract documents a specification for any
            item of work which is defined in the tender notice or in the contract schedule of work
            to be done, by a standard specification number.
            The fact that the item is defined as standard specification shall mean that the
            contractor is to execute the work according to such standard specification, modified as
            may be necessary by an addendum specification for that particular item of work.
            This preliminary specification shall apply to all agreements entered into by contractors
            with the Public Works Department and shall form an inseparable condition of contract,
            and it shall not be necessary to append a copy of the same to agreement.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.03 -- Contractor to sign in the Divisional or the Sub-Divisional copy of
            the A.P.S.S. :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Every contractor who executes work for the Public Works Department shall carefully study
            the standard specification for all items of work which are included in the schedule for
            work to be done as standard specifications and his obligations under the “Preliminary
            Specification” which apply to all agreements, and he shall sign in the Divisional office
            copy of the A.P.D.S.S. (or the Sub-Divisional copy if so arranged by the Executive
            Engineer) as evidence that he understands clearly the conditions of contract governing
            his agreement and accepts the same.
            It shall not be necessary for the contractor to sign the Divisional office copy of the
            A.P.S.S. for every contract awarded to him, but his signature there in will be evidence
            that he accepts the conditions of contract (which includes the standard specifications)
            as detailed in the A.P.D.S.S. for every contract into which he enters. I shall also be
            the contractor’s responsibility by frequent perusal of the Divisional office (or the
            Sub-Divisional office) copy to become conversant with sanctioned alterations or
            additions made to the A.P.S.S. as soon as they are made. A separate volume of addenda to
            the Division office as the case may be) in which will be entered all sanctioned
            corrections and additions. This must also be studied and signed by every contractor
            before executing an agreement. Interleaving correction slips will not be made for this
            purpose. The contractor should purchase a book of the A.P.D.S.S. for his reference while
            executing work.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.04 -- Term “Specification” apart from “Standard Specification” :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Whenever the term “Specification” is used in contract documents apart from “Standard
            Specification”, it shall mean the specification or plan prepared for the particular item
            referred to in the document, for the instruction of the contractor in executing that
            item of work.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.05 -- Sub-Specifications :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Works of a similar nature having many common clauses in their specifications are grouped
            under one specification number with a “General”, preface thereto, and the
            sub-specifications are therefore given an alphabetical affix.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.06 -- Additions and alterations to the standard specifications In the
            A.P.S.S.:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Which do not involve legal implications will be approved by the Chief Engineer (General)
            in consultation with the other Chief Engineers. Additions and alterations to the
            preliminary specifications and standard forms in the A.P.S.S. will be approved by the
            Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.07 -- Powers of Superintending Engineers and Executive Engineers to
            supplement or alter the A.P.S.S.:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Superintending and Executive Engineers may alter the standard specifications for any
            particular contract, which is within their respective powers of sanction —, when such
            alteration is found necessary, by attachment of a correction sheet to the contract form,
            bearing the standard specification number, the corrections, and the signature of the
            Superintending or the Executive Engineer, as the case may be, together with the
            signature of the contractor. Similarly, additional specifications for items for which
            there are no standard specifications will be made by attachment to the contract
            documents of addendum specification sheets bearing the signature of the Superintending
            or the Executive Engineer as the case may be and the signature of the contractor.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.08 -- Definition of terms:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Wherever the words defined in this clause or pronouns used in their stead occur in
            contract documents (which includes the A.P.S.S.), they shall have the meanings here
            given.
            (a) Executive Engineer :—Wherever the term Executive Engineer is used, it shall be
            understood to refer the Executive Engineer for the time being in charge of the concerned
            work under execution or such other departmental assistants or subordinates to whom the
            Executive Engineer may have delegated certain duties, acting severally within the scope
            of the particular duty entrusted to them.
            (b) No delegation by Executive Engineer, Superintending Engineer or higher authority
            which affects agreement. it is, however, to be distinctly understood that the Executive
            Engineer or the Superintending Engineer or the higher authority who is vested with the
            powers of acceptance of the particular agreement under reference will make no delegation
            of powers to such assistant or subordinates which in any way affects the agreement and
            its contracts condition when such agreement is to be or has been accepted by the
            Executive Engineer or by the other higher authority respectively. The duties of such
            assistants or subordinates will be solely duties of supervision to ensure compliance
            with contract conditions.
            (c) Contractor :—Wherever the term “Contractor” is used, it shall be understood to refer
            to the particular person, firm or corporation with whom an agreement has been made by
            the Executive Engineer or higher authority as the case may be, for executing work
            defined in the concerned agreement, and for purposes of instructions regarding
            compliance with contract conditions, it shall include the contractor’s authorized agent,
            who is maintained on the work by the contractor. When two or more contractors are
            engaged on installation or construction work in the same vicinity, the Executive
            Engineer shall be authorized to direct the manner in which each shall conduct the work
            so far as it affects other contractors.

            Note :—The terms Sub-Divisional Officer, Assistant Engineer, Executive Engineer,
            Superintending Engineer and Chief Engineer used in the following clauses shall, where
            the context so requires, be construed as including officers of the corresponding grade
            in the Highways Department.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.09 -- Evidence of Experience :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Tenderers shall, if required, present satisfactory evidence to the Executive Engineer
            that they have been regularly engaged in constructing such works as they propose to
            execute and that they are fully prepared with the necessary capital, machinery and
            materials to begin the work promptly and to conduct it as required by the A.P.S.S. and
            the other specifications for the particular work tendered for, in the event of their
            tender being accepted.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.10 -- Legal address — Notices :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Tenderers should gave in their tender, their place of residence and postal address. The
            delivering at the above named place or posting in a post box regularly maintained by the
            Post Office Department or sending by letter registered for acknowledgement of any
            notice, letter or other communication to the contractor shall be deemed sufficient
            service thereof upon the contractor in writing as may be changed at any time by an
            instrument executed by the contractor, and delivered to the Executive Engineer.
            Nothing contained in the agreement and its contract conditions shall be deemed to
            preclude or render inoperative the service of any notice, letter, or other communication
            upon the contractor personally.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.11 -- Quantities approximate and contractor to verify the nature and
            amount of work :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The quantities mentioned in tender notices and given in agreement (Schedule A) are
            worked out from the relevant drawings in Public Works Department Office and may or may
            not be the actuals required for execution. The Executive Engineer does not expressly or
            by implication agree that the actual amount of work to be done will correspond therewith
            but reserves the right to increase or decrease the quantity of any class or portion of
            the work as he deems necessary. Provided there is no change in the over all scope of the
            work.
            (Amended by G.O.Ms.No. 1007, Tr. Roads and Blds. (c) Dept., Dt. 5-11-1976)
            Tenderers must satisfy themselves by a personal examination of the site of the proposed
            work, by examination of the plans and specifications and by other means as they prefer
            as to the accuracy and sufficiency of the statement of quantities and all conditions
            affecting the work and shall not at any time after the submission of their tender,
            dispute or complain of such statement of qualities, not assert that there was any
            misunderstanding in regard to the nature or amount of the work to be done nor in
            consequence apply for extension of time for completion beyond the agreement date.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.12 -- Approximate not to mean deviation from drawings and specifications :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The declaration of the approximate nature of the statement of quantities in Schedule A
            does not, however, in any way imply that the quantities will be increased for departure
            by the contractor from strict compliance with sanctioned drawings and specifications to
            suit his own given convenience or reduce
            costs.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.13 -- To compare tenders :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The quantities in Schedule A are for a uniform comparison of lump-sum tenders.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.14 -- Purpose :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contract drawings if any read together with the contract specification are intended
            to show and explain the manner of executing the work and to indicate the type and class
            of material to be used.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.15 -- Conformance :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) The works shall be carried out in accordance with the directions and to the
            reasonable satisfaction of the Executive Engineer, in accordance with the drawings and
            specifications which form part of the contract and in accordance with such further
            drawings, details and instructions, supplementing or explaining the same as may from
            time to time be given by the Executive Engineer.
            (b) If the work shown on any such further drawings or details, or other work necessary
            to comply with any such instructions, directions or explanations, be in the opinion of
            the contractor, of a nature which the schedule rate in the contract does not
            legitimately cover, he shall before proceeding with such work, give notice in writing to
            this effect to the Executive Engineer. In the event of the Executive Engineer and the
            contractor failing to agree as to whether or not there is any excess rate to be fixed
            and the Executive Engineer deciding that the contractor is to carry out the said work,
            the contractor shall accordingly do so, and the question whether or not there is any
            excess, and if so the amount thereof, shall, failing agreement, be settled by an
            arbitrator as provided in the arbitration clause, unless the subject is one which is
            left to the sole discretion of the Executive Engineer under the clauses of his
            preliminary specification, and the contractor shall be paid accordingly.
            (c) It shall be the responsibility of the contractor to give timely notice to the
            Executive Engineer, regarding anything shown on the drawings and not mentioned in the
            specifications, or mentioned in the specifications and not shown on the drawings, or any
            error or discrepancy in drawings or specifications and obtain his orders thereon Figured
            dimensions are to be taken and not those obtained from scaling the drawings. In any
            discrepancy between drawings and specifications, the latter shall prevail. In any such
            case or in case any feature of the work is not fully described and set forth in the
            drawings and specifications, the contractor shall forthwith apply to the Executive
            Engineer for such further instructions, drawings, or specifications as he requires, it
            being understood that the subject is to be dealt with under building procedure of best
            modern practice. The Executive Engineer will furnish the further instructions, drawings,
            or specifications, if in his opinion, they are required by competent workmen, for the
            proper execution of the work.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.16 -- Variations by way of modifications, omissions or additions :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) For all modifications, omissions from or additions to the drawings and
            specifications, the Executive Engineer will issue revised plans, or written instructions
            or both and no modification, omission or addition shall be made unless so authorized and
            directed by the Executive Engineer in writing.
            (b) The Executive Engineer shall have the privilege of ordering modifications, omissions
            or additions at any time before the completion of the work and such orders shall not
            operate to annul those portions of the specifications with which said changes do not
            conflict.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.17 -- Copies of drawings and specifications :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            One copy of the available drawings and specifications for (apart from the A.P.S.S. a
            copy of which the contractor should purchase for his reference) shall be furnished free
            of cost to the contractor for his own use. Such copies and copies of supplementary
            details furnished by the Executive Engineer shall be kept on the work until the
            completion thereof, and the Executive Engineer shall at all times have access to them.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.18 -- Signed drawings — No authority to the contractor :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No signed drawing shall be taken as in itself an order for variation, unless either it
            is entered in the agreement schedule of drawings under proper attestation of the
            contractor and the Executive Engineer, or unless it has been sent to the contractor by
            the Executive Engineer, with a covering letter confirm that the drawing is an authority
            for variation for the contract under reference.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.19 -- Finished sizes :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The whole of the specified or figured dimensions or drawings are to be finished sizes,
            after dressing or planning or cutting, subject however to the condition that, unless
            marked “nett,” 1.5 mm will be allowed for planning for each planed finished surface of
            wood-work, when the contractor is permitted to use carefully sawed market size cut
            scantlings. This allowance will only be permitted in the case of Sections 15mm thick or
            over. The figure dimensions of masonry walls and reinforced concrete are exclusive of
            the thickness of plaster or skirtings or cement or wall linings, unless otherwise
            specifically stated.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.20 -- To be the best quality :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            All materials, articles and workmanship shall be the best of their respective kinds for
            the class of work described in the contract specification and schedule, materials being
            obtained from sources approved by the Executive Engineer. The word “best”, as used in
            these specifications shall mean, that in the opinion of the Executive Engineer there is
            no superior quality of material or finish or articles on the market and that there is no
            better class of workmanship available for the nature of the particular item described in
            the contract schedule. The contractor shall, upon the request of the. Executive
            Engineer, furnish him with the vouchers to prove that the materials are such as are
            specified.
            Samples of materials shall be furnished at the contractor’s expense to the Executive
            Engineer when called for in the tender notice or ordered to be furnished by the
            Executive Engineer prior to execution of any work.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.21 -- Conventions for proportions :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Wherever the proportions are written by figures without further descriptions and there
            the meaning is otherwise clear as to which figures is intended to apply to each
            material, then the usual conventions will be understood to apply.
            For example :
            1:2 means 1 lime (or cement in accordance with the context) and 2 sand.
            1:2:4 means 1 lime (or cement in accordance with the context), 2 sand, and 4 broken
            stone (or other aggregate in accordance with the context).
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.22 -- Measurement and mixing :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            In the case of loose materials such as lime, sand, cement broken stone, surki, mortar,
            etc., the proportions demanded by the specifications must be measured in properly
            constructed measuring boxes, or in such other manner as shall be instructed by the
            Executive Engineer. Measurement is not to be done in loose heaps when intimate mixtures
            such as mortar, concrete, etc., are to be formed. The mixing must always be done on
            closely constructed platforms so that there will be no leakage of any of the materials
            through the floor of the platform and also so that no foreign material can be
            incorporated during the mixing. These platforms must be approved by the Executive
            Engineer. The cost of such measuring boxes and platforms and all the work referred to
            herein shall be borne by the contractor.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.23 -- Data :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The materials and labour utilized in the execution work by the contractor shall not be
            less than that given in the A.P.P.W.D. standard data for the relevant item.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.24 -- Lay-out of material stacks :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall deposit materials for the purpose of the work on such parts only of
            the ground as may be approved by the Executive Engineer. He shall submit, for the
            approval of the Executive Engineer, before starting work, a detailed site survey clearly
            indicating positions and areas where materials shall be stacked and sheds built.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.25 -- Source of purchase of materials and stores :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The Executive Engineer shall, during the progress of the work, have power to cause the
            contractor to purchase and use such materials, or supplies from Government brick-fields,
            stores or other sources as may be specified in the contract, for the purposes therein
            specified.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.26 -- Contractor liable for materials supplied by the Government :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall be responsible for all materials and other articles and things
            which may be supplied by Government from the time he takes delivery thereof and shall
            use them only for the purposes of this contract and shall make good any loss, damage,
            wastage or undue wear and tear that may take place from whatever cause and pay to
            Government, for such loss, damage, wastage or undue wear and tear such sum as the
            Executive Engineer may determine.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.27 -- Test inspection and rejection of defective materials and work :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) The contractor shall provide proper facilities at all times, for the testing of
            materials and inspection of the work by the Executive Engineer and the Executive
            Engineer shall accordingly also have access at all times to the place of storage or
            manufacture where materials are being made for use under the contract to determine that
            manufacture is proceeding in accordance with the drawings and specifications.
            (b) The contractor shall, upon demand, also forward for the Executive Engineer’s
            inspection, test certificates supplied by the vendors, when he is purchasing
            consignments of cement, steel and other materials in respect of which such certificates
            are usually available.
            (c) The Executive Engineer shall have power to reject at any stage, any work which he
            considers to be defective in quality of material or workmanship and he shall not be
            debarred from rejecting wrought materials by reason of his having previously passed them
            in an unworked condition. Any portion of the work or materials rejected or pronounced to
            be inferior or not in accordance with the drawings and specifications, shall be taken
            down and removed from the work-site at the contractor’s expense, within 24 hours after
            written instructions to that effect have been given by the Executive Engineer.
            Replacement shall at once be made in accordance with the specifications and drawings, at
            the contractor’s expense.
            In case of default on the part of the contractor to carry out such orders, the Executive
            Engineer shall have power to employ and pay other persons to carry out the orders at the
            contractor’s risk and all expenses consequent thereon and incidental thereto shall be
            borne by the Contractor.
            In lieu of rejecting work not done in accordance with the contract, the Executive
            Engineer may allow such work to remain, and in that case shall make such allowance for
            the difference in value, as in his opinion may be reasonable.
            (d) Works opened for inspections :—The contractor shall at the request of the Executive
            Engineer, within such time as the Executive Engineer shall name, open for inspection any
            work covered up; and should the contractor refuse or neglect to comply with such a
            request, the Executive Engineer may employ workmen to open the same. If the said work
            has been covered up in contravention of the Executive Engineer’s instructions, or if on
            being opened up, it be found not in accordance with the drawings and specifications or
            the written instructions of the Executive Engineer the expenses of opening it and
            covering it up again, whether done by the contractor or such workmen, shall be borne by,
            or recovered from the contractor. If the work has not been covered up in contravention
            of such instructions, or if on being opened up it be found to be in accordance with the
            drawings and specifications or the written instructions of the Executive Engineer, then
            the expenses aforesaid shall be borne by Government and shall be added to the contract
            sum, provided always that in the case of foundations, or any other urgent work so opened
            up and requiring immediate attention, the Executive Engineer shall, within reasonable
            time after the receipt of a notice from the contractor that the work has been so opened,
            make or cause the inspection thereof to be made and at the expiration of such time if
            such inspection shall not have been made, the contractor may cover up the, same and
            shall not be required to open it up again for inspection except at the expense of
            Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>


    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.28 -- Defects, shrinkage, etc., after completion :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Any defects, shrinkage or other faults which may appear within six months from the
            completion of the works arising, in the opinion of the Executive Engineer, from faulty
            materials or workmanship not in accordance with the drawings and specifications or the
            instructions of the Executive Engineer, shall, upon the directions in writing of the
            Executive Engineer and within such reasonable time shall as be specified therein, be
            amended and made good by the contractor at his own cost, unless the Executive Engineer
            shall decide that the contractor ought to be paid for the same at the rates agreed or
            such reduced or other rates as the Executive Engineer may fix and in case of default,
            the Executive Engineer may employ and pay other persons to amend and make good such
            defects, shrinkage or other faults or damage and all expenses consequent thereon and
            incidental thereto shall be borne by the contractor.
            [In the event of Government taking over portions of the works as and when they are
            completed, the liability of the contractor shall be limited to the period of six months
            from the date of taking over the portion or portions of the work, provided that the
            portion or portions taken over has no connection with the remaining portions of the main
            work and is independent of it].
            [Subs. by G.O.Ms.No. 1007, Tr., R. and B.(Cl) Dept., Dt. 5-11-1976]
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.29 -- Executive Engineer’s decision :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            To prevent disputes and litigation, it shall be accepted as in inseparable part of the
            contract that in matters regarding materials, workmanship, removal of improper work,
            interpretation of the contract drawings and contract specifications, mode of procedure,
            and the carrying out of the work, the decision of the Executive Engineer shall be final
            and binding on the contractor, and in any technical question which may arise touching
            the contract, the Executive Engineer’s decision shall be final and conclusive.
            [In the case of any difference between Executive Engineer and contractor on matters
            regarding materials, workmanship, removal of improper work, interpretation of contract
            drawings and contract specifications, mode of procedure and the carrying out of work,
            the contractor shall have a right of appeal to the next higher authority viz., the
            Superintending Engineer of the Circle, and the decision of the latter shall be final and
            conclusive].
            [Added by G.O.Ms.No. 1007, Tr.,Rds., and Blds. (Cl) Dept., Dt. 5-11-1976]
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.30 -- Dismissal of Workmen :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall, on the request of the Executive Engineer, immediately dismiss from
            the works any person employed thereon who may, in the opinion of the Executive Engineer,
            be incompetent or misconduct himself, and such person shall not be again employed on the
            works without the written permission of the Executive Engineer, but the contractor may
            appeal to the Superintending Engineer of the Circle against such dismissal.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.31 -- Contractor’s maistri or agent and Contractor’s staff :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall, in his own absence keep constantly on the works a competent
            maistri or agent, and any directions or explanations given by the Executive Engineer or
            his representatives to such maistri or agent shall be held to have been given to the
            contractor.
            The contractor shall further provide all staff which is necessary for the supervision,
            execution and measurement of the work to ensure full compliance with the terms of the
            contract.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.32 -- Government maistries or agents :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The Government may be represented on the works by an agent, clerk of the works, or
            maistri who is not borne on the official list of officers and subordinates of the Public
            Works Department. He (if appointed) shall, in the absence of the Executive Engineer,
            furnish the contractor with the Executive Engineer’s or his representative’s
            instructions and directions as to the progress and execution of the works and the
            contractor shall duly comply with such instructions and directions and shall, on the
            written requisition of the maistri, clerk of works or agent, stay the further progress
            of any portion of the works which in his judgment is being constructed with unsound or
            improper materials or workmanship, until the opinion and determination of the Executive
            Engineer shall be obtained thereon, but such maistri, clerk of works or agent, is to
            have no power whatever to order any extra works or deviation from the specifications and
            drawings.
            E. — Included in the Contract Rates :-
            The items mentioned in this Section ‘E’ are to be provided by the contractor and are
            therefore to be allowed for in his contract rates for the various items of work in the
            contract schedule, notwithstanding any contrary manual procedure claimed by the
            contractor, unless there are definite superseding instructions in the specifications
            relating to the contract in question.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.33 -- Defining Contract Schedule Rates :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The rate entered in a contract schedule for any class of work shall be for finished work
            in site and shall include all contingent expenses whether direct construction expenses
            involved in the building in place in accordance with the drawings and specifications, or
            whether they be expenses imposed by an outside authority such as a local body Such
            contingent expenses shall not entitle the contractor to claim an extra in respect
            thereof.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.34 -- Carriage :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Rates for finished work shall always include the cost of conveyance and all leads,
            lifts, loading, unloading and stacking in the manner and at the place ordered by the
            officer in immediate charge of the work, unless circumstances necessitate provisions for
            a separate schedule item, in which case such will be specified in the tender notice or
            schedule. When materials are supplied by Government, the place of supply shall be
            specified in the Descriptive Specification Sheet mentioned in the Tender Notice and no
            extra payment will be stacking. If the place of supply is not so specified, the parties
            intending to tender should obtain the information from the Executive Engineer before
            tendering. Otherwise, the absence of information in regard to place of supply will not
            entitle the contract to any extra payment.
            (b) Whether the term “carriage” or “conveyance” is used in a schedule item, it shall, in
            the absence of other schedule provision or modifying description in the specification,
            be taken to include all leads, lifts, loading, unloading and stacking in uniform stacks
            to the satisfaction, of the Executive Engineer, with careful attention to close packing
            in the case of materials which are to be measured in stacks as a basis of payment for
            finished work.
            Note :—In the case of important leads and lifts as may occur in River Conservancy and
            other such works, where lifts over flood banks and long leads may be involved, it is
            usual to make separate schedule item provision with a specification defined the exact
            work to be done for each tendered rate.
            Payment for carriage will ordinarily be by bulk or weight at a mileage rate between
            specified places and on the basis of the method adopted in the standard schedule of
            rates for carriage of materials. The distance will be measured by the nearest
            practicable and cheapest route, whether metalled or unmettalled road or cart- track.
            (c) When carts or vehicles of any sort are engaged by the day, the quantity of material
            to be converted, the distance to be travelled and the number of trips to be made shall,
            if he considers it necessary, be fixed by the Executive Engineer.
            (d) The contractor is responsible for making good all loss in transporting material
            entrusted to him or his agents, whether caused by wastage, breakage, theft, or any other
            cause.
            (e) No payment shall, in any case, be made for the return trip with carts empty. Where
            there are loads also for the return trip, the agreement rates should allow for the
            reduced cost thereby on each set of materials so conveyed.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.35 -- Construction Plant :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall include in his tendered price, and shall provide and install all
            necessary construction plant and shall use such methods and appliances for the
            performance of all the operations connected with the work embraced under the contract as
            will secure a satisfactory quality of work and rate of progress which, in the opinion of
            the Executive Engineer, will ensure the completion of the work within the time
            specified. If at any time before the commencement, or during the progress of the work,
            or any part of it, such methods or appliances appear to the Executive Engineer to be
            insufficient or inappropriate for securing the quality of the work required, or the said
            rate of progress, he may order the contractors to increase their efficiency, or to
            improve their character, and the contractor shall comply with such orders; but the
            failure of the Executive Engineer to demand such increase of efficiency or improvement
            shall not relieve the contractor from his obligation to secure the quality of work and
            the rate of progress required by the contract, and the contractor alone shall be
            responsible for the efficiency and safety of his plant, appliances and methods.
            [If the department intends to supply any tools and plant to the contractor on hire, the
            details of such tools and plant, the hire charges leviable and the terms of hiring them
            should invariably be specified in the tender schedules and in the agreement, and the
            same should not be varied during the contract period. If, however, the department is not
            able to supply any of the tools and plant indicated in the agreement, the contractor
            shall claim no compensation but can only claim reasonable extension of contract tine. If
            any other tools and plant, that are available with the department but are no indicated
            in the agreement, are supplied to the contractor during the course of the work, the hire
            charges and conditions of hire prevailing in the department at the time of actual supply
            shall be applicable].
            [Subs. by G.O.Ms.No. 1007, Tr., R and B (C) Dept., Dt. 5-11.1976]
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.36 -- Scaffolding instructions :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            All requisite scaffolding shall be provided at the contractor’s expense and shall be
            double, i.e., it must have two sets of upright supports. Care must be taken to ensure
            the safety of the workpeople and the contractor must comply with such instructions as
            the Executive Engineer may issue to ensure such safety. The contractor will be entirely
            responsible for any damage or injuries to persons or property resulting from ill-erected
            scaffolding, defective la4ders, or -otherwise arising out of his default in this
            respect.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.37 -- Temporary instructions :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall erect and maintain at his own cost temporary weather-proof sheds at
            such places and in a manner approved by the Executive Engineer for keeping materials
            under cover. The contractor shall also provide and maintain at his own expense such
            temporary fences, guards, bridges and roads as may be necessary for the execution of his
            contract work or for safeguarding or accommodating the public. If the Executive Engineer
            shall order any departure from any arrangements made by the contractor, the contractor
            shall comply with such orders as the Executive Engineer may issue to safeguard or
            accommodate the public. Sheds for housing workmen shall be provided at the contractor’s
            expense, if in the opinion of the Executive Engineer such are necessary or desirable.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.38 -- Water and lighting :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall pay fees and provide water and light as required from Municipal
            mains or other sources, and shall pay all charges therefor (including storage tanks,
            meters, etc.) for the use of the works and workmen, unless otherwise arranged and
            decided on, in writing, with the Executive Engineer. The water for the works shall be,
            so far as practicable, free from earthy, vegetable, or organic matter, and from salts or
            other substances likely to interfere with the setting of mortar or otherwise prove
            harmful to the work.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.39 -- Latrines for Work-people :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall provide and erect, prior to the commencement of work, sufficient
            latrines for the use of the work people, male and female, and shall keep the same
            disinfected and clear at all time during progress of the works, and shall remove the
            same, disinfect the ground and make good all damage on the completion of the work.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.40 -- Sun protection, keeping dry and pumping :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall at his own expense arrange all requisite protection of the work and
            materials against sun or rain effects and shall keep all portions of the work free from
            water to the satisfaction of the Executive Engineer and shall use his own plant for the
            purpose, unless otherwise specifically provided in the contract specifications.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.41 -- Tools and seigniorage :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall, unless otherwise specially stated in the tender notice and
            subsequently on this basis in the contract be responsible for the payment wherever
            payable of all import duties, tolls, octroi duties, seigniorages, quarry fees, etc., on
            all materials and articles that he may use.
            The contractor shall be solely responsible for the payment of sales tax under the
            provisions of the Andhra Pradesh General Sales Tax Act, as in force for the time being
            and the rates for the various items of work shall remain unaffected by any change that
            may be made from time to time in the rate at which such tax is payable.
            Notwithstanding anything contained in Section 10 of the Indian Tariff Act of 1894 the
            rates for items involving the use or supply of articles obtained by the contractor from
            outside India shall remain unaffected by any charges that may be introduced in the
            Customs duties.
            Note :—For works carried out on behalf of the Government of India seigniorage fees,
            etc., referred to in this clause will have to be levied in every case.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.42 -- Setting out works :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall be responsible-for the correct setting out of all works, providing
            at his own cost all labour3 materials and staff required for so doing.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.43 -- Cleaning up during progress and for delivery :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            All rubbish shall be burnt or removed from the site as it accumulates. All floors,
            stairs, landings, doors, windows, surface and soil drains shall be cleaned down and put
            in a thoroughly complete, clean, sound and workman like state to the satisfaction of the
            Executive Engineer before the work is finally handed over, all rubbish and surplus
            materials not required by the Executive Engineer having first been removed by the
            contractor. The contractor shall give notice in writing to the Executive Engineer when
            the work is so ready to be handed over, and shall be responsible for its maintenance
            until it is taken over by the Executive Engineer.
            [The Executive Engineer should take over the work within one month of such notice from
            the contractor, if the work has been satisfactorily completed in terms of the
            agreement].
            [Added by G.O.Ms.No. 1007, Tr., Roads and Blds. (Cl) Dept., Dt. 5-1 1-1 976]
            F. — Responsibilities and Liabilities of the Contractor
            Explanation :—This section sets forth some responsibilities which the contractor shall
            assume in addition to those mentioned in other sections of this “Preliminary
            Specifications” under every contract which he enters into, with the Andhra Pradesh
            Public Works Department and he should therefore calculate his unit prices for schedule
            items of work accordingly.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.44 -- Observance of Laws — Local regulations and notices — Attachments :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall conform to the regulations and bye-laws of any local authority
            and/or of any water or lighting companies with whose systems the structure is proposed
            to be connected and shall, before making any variations from the drawings or
            specifications that may be necessitated by so conforming, give to the Executive Engineer
            written notice, specifying the variations proposed to be made and the reasons for making
            them, and apply for instructions thereon. In case the contractor shall not receive such
            instructions within seven days, he shall proceed with the work, conforming to the
            provision; regulation or bye-law in question; and any variations in the drawings or
            specifications so necessitated shall be dealt with under clause 63. The contractor shall
            give all notices required by the said Acts, regulations or bye-laws and pay all fees in
            connection therewith, unless otherwise arranged and deciding on in writing with the
            Executive Engineer. He shall also ensure that no attachments are made against materials
            or work forming part of or for the use of the contract. In every case referred to in
            this clause the contractor shall protect and indemnify Government against any claim or
            liability arising from or based on the violation of any such law, ordinance, regulation,
            order, decree, or attachment whether by himself or by his employees.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.45 -- Accidents — Hoarding, Lightings, Observations — Watchmen :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) When excavations have been made or obstacles have been put in public through fares
            or in places where there is any likelihood of accidents, the contractors shall comply
            with any requirement of law on the subject, and shall provide suitable hoarding,
            lighting and watchmen as necessary.
            [(b) it shall be the Contractor’s sole responsibility to protect the Public and his
            employees against accident from any cause and he shall indemnify Government against any
            claims for damages for injury to person or property, resulting from any such accidents,
            and shall where the provisions of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, apply, take
            steps to properly insure against any claims 3hereunder. The contractor shall execute the
            ‘Indemnity pond’ in the prescribed form noted below for the payment of claims coming
            under (a) Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, (b) Minimum Wages Act, 1948, (c) Payment of
            Wages Act, 1936, (d) Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 and all other
            such Acts in force and that may be enacted from time to time during the currency of the
            agreement.
            The following Indemnity Bond is to be executed by the Contractor while entering into an
            agreement in respect of contract Works:
            Indemnity Bond
            Name of the Works:
            Agreement No.
            I, …………………………………. Contractor, s/o ……………………………………………..
            Aged ….. Resident of …………………………………………. do hereby bind myself to pay all the
            claims which may come (a) under Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, with any statutory
            modification thereof and rules thereunder or otherwise for or in respect of any damage
            or compensation payable in connection with any accident or injury sustained, (b) under
            Minimum Wages Act, 194, (c) under Payment of Wages Act, 1936, (d) under the Contract
            Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 by any workmen engaged for the performance
            of the business relating to the above contract i.e. ……………………………………………………
            ………………………………………………………………………………………………
            failing such payment of claims of workmen engaged in the above work I abide in accepting
            for the recovery of such claims affected from any of my assets with the Department.]
            (Subs. by G.O.Ms. No. 85, TR and B (B.I.(2) Dept. Dt. 12-2-1986)
            (c) On the occurrence of an accident which results in the death of any of the workmen
            employed by the contractor or which is so serious as to be likely to result in the death
            of any such workmen, the contractor shall, within 24 hours of the happening of such
            accident, intimate in writing to the concerned Section Officer of the Public Works
            Department, the fact of such accident. The contractor shall indemnify Government against
            all loss or damage sustained by Government resulting directly or indirectly from his
            failure to give intimation in the manner aforesaid including the penalties or fines if
            any payable by Government as a consequence of Government’s failure to give notice under
            the Workmen’s Compensation Act or otherwise confirm to the provisions of the said Act in
            regard to such accident.
            (d) In the event of an accident in respect of which compensation may become payable
            under the Workmen’s Compensation Act, VIII of 1923 whether by the contractor or by the
            Government as principal it shall be lawful for the Executive Engineer to retain out of
            monies due and payable to the contractor such sums of money as may, in the opinion of
            the said Executive Engineer, be sufficient to meet such liability. The opinion of the
            Executive Engineer shall be final in regard to all matters arising under this clause.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.46 -- Blasting :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Blasting executed by contractors in connection with Government works shall be carried
            out in the manner described under “Blasting operations - Instructions to contractors” of
            the A.P.S.S.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.47 -- Protection of adjoining and existing premises :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor is to protect the whole of the adjoining and, where necessary, the
            existing premises, and all works and all fittings to all buildings on and adjoining the
            site against structural and decorative damage caused by the execution of these works and
            make good in all respects all such damage done or occurring to the same, and leave such
            reinstatement in perfect order. He is also to make good any damage done in the execution
            of the work to existing public or private footways or roadways.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.48 -- Permit other Workmen — Co-operation — Afford facilities :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The Executive Engineer shall have full empower to send workmen upon the premises to
            execute fittings and other works not included in the contract, for whose operations the
            contractor is to afford every reasonable facility during ordinary working hours,
            provided that such operations shall be carried on in such a manner as not to impede the
            progress of the work included in the contract, but the contractor is not to be
            responsible for any damage which may happen to or to be occasioned by any such fittings
            or other works, provided he complies with the Executive Engineer’s Instructions in
            connection therewith, and provided that the damage is not caused by himself or his
            workmen.
            The contractor shall, to all times, co-operate, assist, attend on, and afford facilities
            for such specialist as may be employed by the Executive Engineer or other works in
            connection with the building, allowing them, free of charge, the use of all plant, light
            and water installed in the works. The contractor shall also cause such special work or
            protect it as instructed to avoid injury during progress of the works. For failure so to
            protect, the contract or must make good any damage caused.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.49 -- Holes for water service, gas, electrical and sanitary fittings :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall leave all holes in masonry and floors for the insertion of water
            services, gas and electrical connections and sanitary fittings in the exact positions
            indicated by the Executive Engineer during the progress of the work. These holes must be
            properly built up, in a workman like manner, at the contractor’s cost, as soon as the
            fittings have been installed, in cases where the installations are made during the
            construction of the building and where, in the opinion of the Executive Engineer, delays
            in settlement of accounts will not thereby occur.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.50 -- Contractor’s risk and Insurance :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The work executed by the contractor under the contract shall be maintained at the
            contractor’s risk until the work is taken over by the Executive Engineer. The contractor
            shall accordingly arrange his own insurance against fire and other usual risks during
            such period unless otherwise specified:
            Provided however that the contractor shall not be liable for all or any loss or damage
            occasioned by or arising out of acts of God, and in particular unprecedented flood,
            volcanic eruption, earthquake or other convulsion of nature, invasion, the act of
            foreign enemies hostilities or warlike operations (before or after declaration of war)
            rebellion, military or usurped power.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.51 -- Holidays :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The work executed by the contractor under the contract shall be maintained at the
            contractor’s risk until the work is taken over by the Executive Engineer. The contractor
            shall accordingly arrange his own insurance against fire and other usual risks during
            such period unless otherwise specified:
            Provided however that the contractor shall not be liable for all or any loss or damage
            occasioned by or arising out of acts of God, and in particular unprecedented flood,
            volcanic eruption, earthquake or other convulsion of nature, invasion, the act of
            foreign enemies hostilities or warlike operations (before or after declaration of war)
            rebellion, military or usurped power.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.52 -- Sand and gravel :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall not make any excavation upon the site for the purpose of obtaining
            gravel, sand or soil other than that shown on or implied by the drawings, except with
            the previous permission of the Executive Engineer.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.53 -- Old curiosities :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            All old curiosities, relics, coins, minerals, etc., found in excavating or pulling down,
            shall be the property of the Government and be handed over to the Executive Engineer.
            Should any ancient masonry, or other old work of interest be opened up, the Executive
            Engineer’s attention shall be called to the same before demolition or removal.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.54 -- Assignment or sub-letting :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The contractor shall not, without the written consent of the Executive Engineer) assign
            the contract nor sublet any portion of the same. Ordinarily no sub-letting will be
            permitted, but in case such should be permitted by the Executive Engineer, it shall in
            no way free the contractor from any of his responsibilities under any clause of his
            Preliminary Specification or of the “Articles of Agreement”.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.55 -- Specialists :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The Executive Engineer shall, during the progress of the work, have power to select,
            nominate or recommend tradesmen or specialists to supply material or execute such
            portion of the work as he may consider desirable in the interests of the Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.56 -- Ratification of the orders of the Executive Engineer :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Should the acceptance of the tender be beyond the authorized powers of the Executive
            Engineer ad laid down in the Public Works Department Code, the orders and decision of
            such Executive Engineer with regard to extension of time for completing the contract or
            the termination of the contract or of the employment of specialists for certain portions
            of the work as described in the previous clause will be subject to the ratification of
            the higher authority who entered into the agreement.
            [Amended by G.O.Ms.No. 1007, Tr. Roads and Buildings (C) Dept., Dt. 5-11-1976]
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.57 -- Order book :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            An order book shall be kept at the Public Works Department office on the site of the
            work. As far as possible, all orders regarding the work are to be entered in this book.
            All entries shall be signed and dated by the Public Works Department Officer in direct
            charge of the work and by the contractor or by his representative. In important cases,
            the Executive Engineer or the Superintending Engineer will countersign the entries which
            have been made. The order book shall not be removed from the work, except with the
            written permission of the Executive Engineer.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.58 -- Date of commencement and completion :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            On notification of possession of the site (or premises) being given to the contractor by
            letter registered for acknowledgement as provided in paragraph 10 Supra, he shall
            forthwith begin the work, shall regularly and continuously proceed with them, and shall
            complete the same (except for painting or other work which, in the opinion of the
            Executive Engineer, it may be desirable to delay) by the date of completion as defined
            in “Articles of Agreement”, subject, nevertheless, to the provisions of extension of
            time mentioned in the next clause. The contractor shall under no circumstances be
            entitled to claim any damages from Government if he incurs any expense or liabilities to
            payment under the contract before the date of commencement defined above. The contractor
            shall have the right to withdraw from the contract and obtain refund of his security
            deposit is such intimation of handling over the site is delayed more than two months
            from the date of acceptance of the agreement by competent authority.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>P.S No.59 -- Delays and extension of time :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            No claim for compensation on account of delays or hindrances to the work from any cause
            whatever shall lie, except, as hereinafter defined. Reasonable extension of time will be
            allowed by the Executive Engineer or by the officer competent to sanction the extension
            for unavoidable delays, such as may result from causes, which, in the opinion of the
            Executive Engineer, are undoubtedly beyond the control of the contractor. The Executive
            Engineer shall assess the period of delay or hindrance caused by and written
            instructions issued by him, at twenty five per cent in excess of the actual working
            period so lost.
            In the event of the Executive Engineer failing to issue necessary instructions and
            thereby causing delay and hindrance to the contractor, the latter shall have the right
            to claim an assessment of such delay by the Superintending Engineer of the Circle whose
            decision will be final and binding. The contractor shall lodge in writing with the
            Executive Engineer a statement of claim for any delay or hindrance referred to above,
            within fourteen days from its commencement, otherwise no extension of time will be
            allowed.
            Whenever authorized alterations or additions made during the progress of the work are of
            such a nature in the opinion of the Executive Engineer as to justify an extension of
            time in consequence thereof, such extension will be granted in writing by the Executive
            Engineer or other competent authority when ordering such alterations of additions.
        </para_desc>
    </para>


</Ebook>
