<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Ebook name="APLeaveRules">

    <para>
        <para_name>CASUAL LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

             Concept: A concession to Govt. Servant in special circumstances to be absent from duty
            for a short period.

             Authority: Instructions 1 to 6, Annexure VII ( Executive
            instructions regarding Casual Leave) of A .P . Fundamental and
            Subsidiary Rules vide Ruling 4 of FR 85.

             Admissibility: To all temp. / permanent employees.

            Crediting / Accounting: i) 15 days per calendar year (G.O.Ms.No.52,
            GAD(Poll.B) Dept., Dt.04.02.81). ii) If appointed in the middle of the year, CLs should
            be credited proportionately. iii) A register of CL should be maintained.

             Availing procedure:

            (1) By taking prior permission.

            (2) In-charge arrangement should be made.

            (3) HODs should intimate to the concerned Dept. in Govt.

            (4) Can be availed in combination with OH, PH and SCL.

            (5) Cannot be availed in combination with other leave, vacation and joining time.

            (6) ½ day CL may be availed from 10.30 am to 1.30 pm (or) from 2.00 pm to 5.00 pm.

            (7) For temp. employees, sanction depends on discretion of sanctioning authority based
            on the length of service. (G.O.Ms.No.999, Fin.,Dt.30.05.1959)

            (8) For each 3 or more late attendances - on permission – 1 CL will be deducted.
            (GoMsNo.574,GAD(ser-c)Dept., dt;3-7-71).

             Limitations :
            1. Total period of absence from duty should not exceed 10 days.

            2. An officer is not entitled to take full amount of CLs in a year.
            (G.O.Ms.No.2465,Fin.,Dt.23.12.1959, G.O.Ms.No.2094,Fin, Dt.22.04.1960)

            3. Frequent availing of CLs / Holidays by an individual should be avoided.

            4. Balance will not be carry forwarded to the next calendar year

             Sanctioning Authority: Head of Office.

             Effect : Treated as duty for all purposes.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>SPECIAL CASUAL LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

             Concept: A concession to Govt. Servant in special circumstances to be absent from duty
            for a short period.

             Authority: Instructions 7 to 10 Annexure VII ( Executive
            instructions regarding Casual Leave) of A .P . Fundamental and Subsidiary Rules vide
            Ruling 4 of FR 85.

             Admissibility: To all temp / permanent employees.
            Special Casual Leave(Instruction 7):

            (1) Summons to give witness in a court in which his private interest is not in issue -->
            As per the attendance Certificate.

            (2) For Family Planning operations :

            (2.a) Male-Vasectomy --> 6 working Days(G.O.Ms.No.257 F and P dt:05-01-81).

            (2.b) Female- Tubectomy --> 14 Days(G.O.Ms.No.124 F and P dt:13-4-82).

            (2.c) Male – For Tubectomy of wife --> 7 Days.

            (2.d) Female - Insertion of Intra Uterine Contraceptive Devices --> 1 Day on the day of
            insertion and reinsertion (G.O.Ms.No.128 F and P DT:13-4-82).

            (2.e) Recanalization (Both male and female employees) --> 21 Days or Actual period of
            Hospitalization which ever is less Plus Actual journey(to and fro period) Admissible to
            the employees who have less than two Children or who has lost all Male or Female
            Children after Family Planning operation.

            (3.a) Female - Salpingectomy operation after medical Termination of Pregnancy --> 14
            days(G.O. Ms. No,275 F and P (FW FRI)Dept.dt.15-05-81).

            (3.b) Male - Salpingectomy operation for Wife --> 7 days.

            (4) .Post Operative Complications:

            (4.a) Vasectomy --> Extended upto 7 days

            (4.b) Tubectomy --> Extended upto 14 days on production of Medical Certificate.

             SCL can be availed for the 2nd time for the same period on production of MC mentioning
            the failure of previous operation (in case of Vasectomy and Tubectomy).

             SCL may be prefixed or suffixed to Regular Leave or CL and not both.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>SPORTS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

             8-A) 1.For participating in Sporting events of National or International Importance –
            not exceeding 30 days in a calendar year. (G.O.Ms.No.295 Fin FR-I Dept.dt.14-09-1964).

            2.If exceeded 30 days – excess period treated as regular leave. Permitted to combine
            with Regular Leave but not with CL.

            3.The concession shall not be allowed for the Participants on his personal capacity.

            4.It is extended to Managers of Teams, Coaches and Referees(Go Ms.No.358 F and P
            (FWFR-I)Dept.dt.26-12-84).

            5. SCL not exceeding 15 days may be availed for President /Secy. of National Sports
            Bodies recognized by all India Council of Sports(G.O.Ms. No.270 F and P FWFR-I
            Dept.,Dt.30-06-1976).

             8-B) Participating in trekking expeditions approved by India Mountaineering
            Foundation,
            SCL not exceeding 30 days in a calendar year may be sanctioned.

             8-C)Disabled Ex service men re-employed as Civilian in State Govt. services for
            appearing before Medical resurvey board for the reassessment of disability and to go to
            hospital for treatment --> 15 days of SCL (G.O.Ms. No.407 F and P FW FR-I
            Dept.dt.18-09-76).

             9- A)For the recruitment in Territorial army or Auxiliary Air force.
            i) Attending for an interview, Medical exam followed by training etc. -One month or Less
            (or) ii) For participation in ceremonial Parades - One month or less.

             9-B)For Registering the name under Reserve and Auxiliary Air-force Act-1952 i)
            Attending for an interview, medical examination followed by training - One month or Less
            (or) ii) For participation in ceremonial Parades as a member of Air Defence Reserve -
            One month or less.

             10-A) AP Secretariat Cultural Association Members for enacting dramas in mofussil
            areas
            – 6 days SCL in a calendar Year.

             10-B) i) Principal Office bearers of Recognized service Associations(Represented on
            A.P. Civil Services Joint Staff Council) and 2 Office Bearers from each of the units in
            Districts and City – 21 days SCL in a calendar year.
            (G.O.Ms. No.205, Fin, Dt.08-06-1980)

            ii)It will not be sanctioned in addition to any SCL allowed under Sports ,Cultural
            Activities etc.

            iii)The competent authority will have the discretion to withhold the
            Grant of SCL in exigencies of Govt. work (G.O. Ms. No.390 Fin, Dt.26-11-64).

             10-C) Employees of vacation Dept.(Education, Judiciary etc.) -7 days of SCL in a
            calendar year Total SCL sanctioned shall not exceed 30 days if they participate in the
            Sports event. Competent authority shall have the discretion to withhold (G.O.Ms. No.47
            Fin,dt.12-02-65).

             10-D) To participate in Rallies, Camps etc. Organized by A.P. Bharat Scouts and Guides
            at State/National Level – 10 days of SCL in a calendar year (G.O.MsNo.112
            Fin,dt.22-07-69).

             10-E) Members of Institution of Engineers: (a) For attending annual Meeting at Hyd. -7
            days of SCL in a calendar year (b)For attending annual convention to any part of the
            country - 10 days of SCL in a calendar year (G.O.Ms No.44 F and P FR-I,dt.05-02-06)

             10-G) Govt. Servant participating in the cultural events in the National and
            International
            importance when he is selected by service /cultural associations recognized by Govt. -
            30 days of SCL in a calendar year. ( G.O.Ms.No.360, F and P, Dt.24.12.1980).

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>SPECIAL PROVISIONS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

             For Donation of Blood: - 1 day of SCL on the day of donation on production of M.C.
            (G.O.Ms.No.137, M and H (EL) Dept.,Dt.23.02.1984).

             Women Govt. employees for being celebrated International Women's day on March 8th -1
            day SCL on that Day (G.O. Ms. No.433 GAD(SW-II)Dept.dt.04-08-10).

             On account of presence of following infectious diseases in an employee’s house - small
            pox, plague, cholera, typhoid, acute influenza pneumonia, diphtheria, cerebra-spinal
            meningitis, measles - not exceeding 21 days of SCL on production of certificate from
            Medical Officer - extended up to 30 days ( Exe. Inst. 7 (a)(i) (ii) and Note (1) to (5))
            Rescinded Vide G.O.Ms.No.10 F and P(FR I), Dt.24.01.1992.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>COMPENSATORY HOLIDAYS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

             Concept: A Concession to a Govt. Servant in special circumstances to compensate the PH
            / OH which he has not availed due to called on to duty. Contexts: 1.attending to duty
            on a public holiday (G.O.Ms.No.917,Madras Public Dept.,Dt.16.09.1902) 2.attending to
            duty on an optional holiday already sanctioned (G.O.Ms.No.528,G.A.D, Dt.26.04.1961) 3.
            attending to duty as turn duty (G.O.Ms.No.2036,Madras Public(Pol-B)Dept.,
            Dt.11.08.1952).

             Authority: Annexure XII of A.P. Fundamental and Subsidiary Rules.

             Admissibility: To all temp. / permanent employees.

             Crediting / Accounting: Max. of 7 days or lower no. may be fixed in discretion by Head
            of Office. ( Memo. No.36/58-1, G.A.(Pol-B) Dept.,Dt.06.01.1958) Effect: Treated as duty
            for all purposes.

             Availing procedure:

            (1) by taking prior permission. (2) Can be availed in combination with CL / Holiday /
            Regular Leave. (3) Not more than 10 such holidays in a calendar year. (4) Should be
            availed
            within a period of 6 months from the duty attended on a holiday (G.O.Ms.No.942, Public,
            Dt.17.10.1903) (5) Can be availed by prefixing / suffixing. (Memo No.2690/Pol-B/64-2,
            G.A.(P.O.B.)Dept., Dt.03.10.1964).

             Limitations:

            (1) Only 10 compensatory leaves should be availed in a calendar year.

            (2) If possible, if the holiday is related to religious purpose the servant belonging to
            that religion
            should not be called upon to duty. (G.O.Ms.No.917, Madras Public Dept.,Dt.16.09.1902)

            (3) Govt. servant touring on public holidays in connection with the performance of his
            duties is not eligible for this concession (Memo No.13112, Accts / 67-2, Dt.01.03.1958).

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Provisions of Leave in A.P.Fundamental Rules and Subsidiary Rules :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

             Leave is dealt under F.R. 58 to 104, Chapter X, Part IV and Annexures of A.P.
            Fundamental Rules and Subsidiary Rules.

             Annexure III A.P. Leave Rules, 1933 (w.e.f.04.09.33)

             Annexure V Leave Calculator (Not Printed)

             Annexure V A Ready Reckoner for calculating Leave

             Annexure VI Model Leave Terms (Not Printed)

             Annexure VII Executive Instructions regarding ordinary CL and SCL.

             Annexure IX Case Law and Executive Instructions on Leave

             Annexure X Simplification and Liberalization of Leave Rules

             Annexure XI Surrender of EL Scheme. Annexure XII Compensatory Holidays.

             FR 58,59: Not printed.

             FR 60 : Leave is earned by duty only. A period spent in foreign
            service counts as duty if leave salary contribution is paid.

             FR 61,62,63,64: Omitted.

             FR 65 : Carry Forward of Leave.

             FR 66 : Leave sanctioning authorities. (in respect of other than S.D.L.)

             FR 67 : Leave cannot be claimed as a right.

             FR 68 : Prefixing or Suffixing Leave ordinarily begins on the day on which transfer or
            charge is effected and ends on the day preceding the day on which charge is resumed.

             FR 69 : No employment on leave.

             FR 70 : Recall Compulsory – leave only upto the date of
            starting the journey Optional - no concession.

             FR 71 : Physical Fitness Certificate is required to report to duty after leave

             FR 72 :A Government servant on leave may not return to duty before the expiry of
            period
            of the leave granted to him, unless he is permitted to do so by the authority which
            granted him
            leave.

             FR 73: Overstay after leave (AP LR 6 A)

             FR 74: State Govt. may make rules regarding maintenance of records of service in order
            to secure efficiency and uniformity
            of Audit.

             FR 75: Not printed

             FR 76: Leave account shall be maintained for each Govt. servant.

             FR 77 : Not printed under Ruling Leave account for fraction of day should be rounded
            off to the nearest.

             FR 78: Leave Account – Procedure of debiting

             FR 79: Not printed

             FR 80: The amount of leave due to Govt. servant is the balance of leave at his credit.

             FR 81: Leave sanctioning Limit and procedure

             FR 82 : Vacation Department

             FR 83 : Special Disability Leave

             FR 84 : Study Leave

             FR 85 : Extra ordinary Leave

             FR 86: Leave at credit – compulsory retirement

             FR 87 : Leave Salary

             FR 88 to 91: Not printed

             FR 92: Omitted

             FR 93 : Compensatory Allowances during Leave.

             FR 93A to 99: Not printed

             FR 100: Omitted

             FR 101: Maternity Leave, Hospital Leave.

             FR 102: Not printed

             FR 103: Govt. – regulation of leave

             FR 104: Apprentice persons – Leave.

             FR 55 : Leave may not be granted to a Govt. Servant under suspension.

             FR 18 : Max period of leave to be granted: 5 years

             FR 18 A: A Govt. Servant shall be deemed to have resigned from the service if he

            i) is absent without authorization for a period
            exceeding 1 year (or)

            ii) remains absent from duty for a continuous period exceeding 5
            years with or without leave (or)

            iii) continues on foreign service beyond the period
            approved by the State Govt. (G.O.Ms.No.128, Fin(FR I) Dept. Dt.01.06.07).

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>KINDS OF LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

             1. Casual Leave.

             2. Special Casual Leave

             3.Compensatory Leave

             4. Earned Leave.

             5. Half Pay Leave.

             6. Commuted Leave

             7. Leave not due.

             8. Extra Ordinary Leave.

             9.Special Disability Leave.

             10. Study Leave.

             11. Maternity Leave.

             12.Miscarriage/Abortion Leave

             13. Hospital Leave.

             14.Leave for Hysterectomy Operation

             15.Leave for Employment in Abroad

             16.Paternity Leave.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>EARNED LEAVE:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            -> Authority: AP Leave Rules 1933, Rules 8-12,17- 18,20-22  Eligibility: All temporary
            and permanent  Procedure of Earning / Crediting: a) Regular:

            (1) Earned for duty and leave period.

            (2) 15 days adv. Credit on Jan and July.

            (3) Max. Earning 30 days per year.

            (4)Credit for one complete month =2 ½ days.

            (5) Credit for fraction of month = 0.

            (6) If an employee availed EOL, 1/10th of EOL period will be reduced in the credit of
            succeeding half year subject to max. of 15 days.(G.O.Ms.No.384,Fin.,Dt.05.11.1977).

            (7) Max accumulation = 300 days. w.e.f.16-09-2005 vide G.O.Ms.No:232, Fin. (FR.I) Dept,
            dated :16.09.2005.

            (8) Previous Limits for Max accumulation for Permanent Superior
            Employees From 01.06.1964 to 30.06.1983 - 180 days From 01.07.1983 to 15.09.2005 - 240
            days.

            (9) Previous Limits for Max accumulation for Permanent Last Grade Employees From
            17.08.1967 to 30.06.1983 - 180 days From 01.07.1983 to 15.09.2005 - 240 days  b)
            Temporary :

            (9a). 8 days adv. Credit on Jan and July.

            (9b). If appointed in the middle, first 2 completed months = 1 day 3rd month = 2 days

            (9c). Max accumulation = 30 days.

            (9d). The leave account should be recast after regularization.

            -> Availment: on Medical grounds/ private affairs :

            (1). Not exceeding 180 days for
            permanent superior employees at a time subject to the balance in the account
            G.O.Ms.No.153
            fin.(FR1)dept.dt.4-5-2010.

            (2). Not exceeding 120 days for permanent last grade
            employees. G.O.Ms.No.329, Fin.,Dt.17.12.1982 and G.O.Ms.No.9, Fin., Dt.10.01.1983

            (3). Can be availed on combine with other leaves.

            (4). Public Holidays, Optional Holidays, and compensatory
            leave can be prefixed or suffixed. (Memo No.86595/1210/FR.I/7, Dt.29.05.1981).

            (5). The existing limit of 180 days at a time on availment of commuted leave in
            conjunction with EL was removed. G.O.Ms.No.384, Fin., Dt.05.11.1977.

            -> Leave Salary:
            Full basic pay prior to leave + all allowances HRA and CCA will be paid in full upto 6
            months.
            (G.O.Ms.No.28,Fin.(FR.I),dt.09.03.11).

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Surrender of Earned Leave (Introduced from 13-08-1969) Vide G.O.Ms.No.238
            dt:13-8-69 :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            -> Eligibility: Temporary / Permanent  Availment:

            (A) Permanent:

            (i) 15 days for 12 months gap

            (ii)30 days for 24 months gap based on the balance available.

            (iii) If balance is above 285 days on 30th June, gap need not be observed. Leave will be
            credited after
            deducting surrendered days. (Memo No. 50798/1063/FR-1/79-1, F and P,Dt.22.11.1979, Memo
            No.10472/C/199/FR-1/2009, Fin(FR.I), Dt.29.04.2009, Memo No.14781/C/278/FR.I/2011. Fin
            (FR.I), Dt.22.06.2011)

            (iv)Only once in a financial year.

            (v) Surrender Leave will be sanctioned from the date of application (Memo
            No.47064/1164/FR.I/91, F and P, Dt.20.01.92).


            (B) Temporary 15 days after 24 months gap (G.O.Ms.No.221,F and P(FR.I),Dt.23.08.74,
            G.O.Ms.No.316, F and P(FR.I), Dt.25.11.74(Sup.) Memo No.47774/1177/FR.I/74-1,
            Dt.07.11.74(Class IV), G.O.Ms.No.393, Fin., Dt.31.12.75(all)) • Effect : Surrendered
            days will be deducted in leave account.

            -> Validity: Sanction order is valid for 90 days from the date of issue. (Memo
            No.14423/715/FR.I/91, F and P, Dt.20.01.92 and Memo No.27/423/A2/FR.I/97-1, F and P,
            Dt.18.08.97)  Leave Salary:

            (i) Claimed by considering 30 days/per month irrespective
            of claimed month. (G.O.Ms.No.306,F and P(FWFR.I) Dept., Dt.08.11.1974)

            (ii) It includes
            Pay + OCA + HRA + AHRA + CCA. (Memo No. 64861/797/FR.I/71-1, Dt.14.07.72,G.O.Ms.No.25,F
            and P, Dt.05.02.96).

            (iii) Conveyance allowance can not be paid (iv) HRA can be claimed to those who are
            residing in Govt. quarters. (G.O.Ms.No.337,F and P(FWPC.II) Dept., Dt.29.09.94) (v) No
            Interim Relief will be paid (Memo No.31948/398/PCI/98-1,Fin, Dt.12.08.98) (vi) Debitable
            to HOA 010-018. Sanctioning Authority: As delegated.

            Others:

            1. It is extended to Municipal Employees, Public Health Workers, Non Public
            Health Workers,Zilla parishad, Zilla Granthalay, employees, Village Secretaries 

            2.Surrender Leave amount may be initially paid by the Foreign Employer for those who are
            working in Foreign Service, and the total amount have to be reimbursed by the parent
            department later on. (G.O.Ms.No.329, F and P(FR.I) Dept.,Dt.06.12.74, Memo
            No.49395/1219/FR.I/75-1,F and P,Dt.06.01.76).

            Encashment of E.L.s:
            -> The employees are permitted to encash E.L. at the time of
            superannuation / death / Voluntary retirement/Retirement on medical grounds/ compulsory
            retired as a measure of punishment under APCS(CCA) Rules and has been enhanced to, from
            240 to 300 days w.e.f. 16.09.05.(G.O.Ms.No.27,F and P(FWFR.I), Dt.19.01.76)
            G.O.Ms.No:232,Fin.(FR.I) Dept,Dt.16.09.2005, G.O.Ms.No.234,Fin(FR.I) Dept.,Dt.11.08.06
            w.e.f.16.09.05( die while in service)).

            -> EEL may be withhold for those who are facing
            disciplinary proceedings until final settlement which involves recovery of money
            (G.O.Ms.No.11,F and P(FWFR.I)Dept.,Dt.15.01.97).

            -> EEL encashment is to be sanctioned by
            the parent department for those who retired in foreign service.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>HALF PAY LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Authority : A.P. Leave Rules, 1933 Rules 13-15, 18, 23,23(a)(i)

            • Eligibility: Permanent / (Temporary employees)*

            • Crediting: 20 days for completed year No max limit
            for accumulation

            • Availment: No max limit Can be availed on private affairs and
            medical purposes, can be combined with other leave Temporary employees avail this after
            completion of two (sup.) or one (inf.) years of service.
            (Temporary Govt. servants (Emergency) appointed under rule 10(a)(i) are not eligible to
            avail.) ( Memo No.20584/302/FR.I/74-1, F and P(FR.I),Dt.12.09.1974).

            • Leave Salary: Half Basic Pay + Proportionate D.A. HRA and CCA in full upto 6 months
            No compensatory allowances after that. • Sanctioning Authority: as delegated.

            • Leave Encashment: Encashment of EL and HPL shall be limited to 300 days.
            Superannuation pensioner, death cases, invalid pensioners are eligible. Amount will be
            paid as per formula (G.O.Ms.No.154, Fin(FR I)Dept.,Dt.04.05.2010)

            • --[Formula =( Half pay + Prop DA)/30 * No. of days. ]--

            • No compensatory allowances are admissible.

            • If a Govt. servant suffering from TB/Cancer/Mental illness/Leprosy/Heart disease/Renal
            failure(kidney), HIV AIDS, he may avail HPL upto 6 months with full pay • Compensatory
            allowances will be paid in full upto 8 months.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>COMMUTED LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            -> Authority:AP LR Rules 15-B, 18-B  Admissibility: Permanent/ (Temporary Employees)*

            -> Availment: On medical grounds (MC) only Temporary employees after two/one year of
            service.

            • Limitation: 240 days in entire service.

            • Effect: Twice the amount of HPL will be deducted.

            • Leave Salary: Double the half pay + all allowances in full

            • Conversion of Commuted leave to HPL: When a Govt. servant intends to resign/retire
            After
            availing commuted leave, it should be converted into HPL and HPL salary should be
            recovered. An undertaking should be taken from employee whenever it is sanctioned
            (G.O.Ms.No.300, Fin., Dt.18.11.65).
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>LEAVE NOT DUE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Authority: AP LR Rule 15-C and 18-C  Eligibility: All permanent employees 
            Availment: When HPL is not at credit, it may be sanctioned on Medical Certificate only.

            • Effect: Deducted from future credit of HPL account

            • Leave Salary: Same as in HPL

            • Limitation: 180 days during entire service.

            • Recovery: If any employee resigns / retires voluntarily after availing this leave and
            before wiping off the minus balance, the leave salary paid for minus balance should be
            recovered. In case of medical invalidation / death, recovery will not be insisted.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>EXTRAORDINARY LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted when no other leave is admissible, but it can also be granted
            even when other leave being admissible.

            • Authority: FR 85, Rule 16,19,23(a)(ii) of APLR

            • Admissibility: Temp./ Permanent

            • Period: Not more than 5 years

            • Availment:On personal affairs/on medical grounds

            • Leave Salary: No salary

            • Effect: EOL on MC counts for increment,pension EOL on pvt. Affairs – not count for
            increment, counted up to 3 years for pension, EL account will be deducted by 1/10th.

            • Sanctioning Authority: Up to 6months – HOD above that – Govt.

            • For Temporary Employees: EOL can be sanctioned for

            (a) 3 months ordinarily in one occasion

            (b) 6 months on MC by Govt.(3 yrs of service)

            (c) 18 months for treatment of TB/Leprosy (1yr of service)

            (d)12 months for treatment of Cancer, mental illness

            (e) 24months for prosecuting studies certified to be in public interest and to employees
            of SC and ST to join pre examination training course at center notified by Govt.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>SPECIAL DISABILITY LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted to a Govt. Servant who is disabled/injured or met with road
            accidents while on duty

            • Authority: FR 83, 83A

            • Eligibility: Temp. / Permanent employees

            • Period: Upto 24 months

            • Availment:

            1.On producing MC For Gazetted- Medical Board NGOs - Civil Surgeon If it is
            below 2 months all – Govt.Medical Officer
            (G.O.Ms.No.40, Fin.,Dt.03.06.61)

            2. Availed in combination with other leave.

            3. Disability - manifested itself within 3 months of occurrence Relaxation: President
            of India

            4. If the disability is aggravated, it may be granted more than once.

            • Effect: Counts for increment, pension No debit of any leave.

            • Leave Salary: For Permanent upto 180 days – on full pay after 180 days- on half pay
            For temporary upto 30 days – on full pay after 30 days- on half pay.

            • Sanctioning Authority: Govt. Only For Police Personnel Upto 12 months – DGP
            (G.O.Ms.No.232, Home, Dt.22.08.98)

            •Limitations:

            1. The period shall not exceed 24months

            2. Not admissible for road accidents while going to office from residence and
            vice versa.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>STUDY LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted for the study of Scientific, technical or similar problems or
            to undergo special courses of instruction.

            • Authority: FR 84 • Admissibility: For permanent Gazetted employees of min 5 years of
            service and 3 yrs of left over service Very exceptional for NGOs.

            • Availment:
            (1).May be granted for 12 months at a time and 2 years in entire service.
            (2). May be combined with other leave.

            • Effect: counts for increment, pension.

            • Leave salary: Salary on half pay.

            • Sanctioning Authority: Govt. Only.

            • Limitations: If it is combined with leave with allowances, the period of leave should
            not exceed 28 months.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>MATERNITY LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted to female married Govt. servant having less than 2 surviving
            children (G.O.Ms.No.348, F and P(FWFR.I), Dt.05.11.77, G.O.Ms.No.219,F and P(FWFR.I),
            Dt.25.06.84,G.O.Ms.No.38, F and P, Dt.18.03.92)

            • Authority: F.R. 101  Admissibility: Temp./ Permanent  Period: 180 days
            G.O.Ms.No.152,Fin(FR.I),Dt.04.05.10

            • Availment: (prior to the date of delivery)* or after delivery , Can be combined with
            other leave with MC.

            • Leave Salary: Full Pay + All allowances.

            • Sanctioning Authority: H.O.O./ as delegated

            • Note:

            1. Extended to aided institutions (G.O.Ms.No.69,Sch.Edn(PS.I),Dt.06.06.03)

            2.For contract employees 45 days with salary (G.O.Ms.No.197,WDCW and Dis.
            Wel.,Dt.14.05.03)

            3.For Contract employees in Govt.Degree colleges 60
            days(G.O.Ms.No.88,H.Edn(CE.I.1),Dt.09.08.11) without remuneration

            4.For Contract employees in Govt. Jr.colleges 60
            days(G.O.Rt.No.94,H.E.(I.E.-I),Dt.10.12.10)
            without remuneration.

            5.For contract Pachayat Secretaries- 120days (G.O.Ms.No.254, PR and RD(Mdl.II),
            Dt.31.05.07) without remuneration.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>MISCARRIAGE / ABORTION LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted to female Govt. servant to take hospitalization for miscarriage
            / abortion.

            • Period: Max. Of 6 weeks.

            • Authority: FR 101(a) and G.O.Ms.No.129,Fin,Dt.13.08.85

            • Admissibility: Temp./Permanent employees

            • Availment: on production of MC from RMP

            • Effect: Counts for increment, pension

            • Leave salary: salary on full pay

            • Sanctioning Authority: H.O.O./ as delegated.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Leave for Hysterectomy Operation :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: To undergo hysterectomy operation for female Govt. servant and
            hospitalization

            • Period: 45 days

            • Authority: G.O.Ms.No.52, Fin(FR.I),Dt.01.04.2011

            • Admissibility: Temp./Permanent employees

            • Availment: on production of MC from Civil Surgeon

            • Effect: counts for increment, pension

            • Leave Salary: Salary on full pay

            • Sanctioning Authority: H.O.O./ as delegated.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>HOSPITAL LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted to the employees specified in SR 2 under FR101(b) i.e. risk
            born duties

            • Period: Not exceeding 6 months in every 3 years of service

            • Authority: FR 101 (b)

            • Admissibility: Only Permanent employees

            • Availment: on combination with any
            other leave

            • Effect: counts for increment, pension

            • Leave salary: first 3 months on full pay and next 3 months on half pay

            • Sanctioning Authority: as delegated.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>ABROAD LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted to Govt. servant who desires to work at abroad

            • Period: Not exceeding 5 years

            • Authority:1.G.O.Ms.No.214,F and P(FW.FRI), Dt.03.09.96 2.U.O.Note No.13127-A/113/FR
            I/98, Fin Dept.,Dt.10.05.98.

            • Admissibility: Permanent employees

            • Availment: Upto 5 years in entire service in single stretch or in different spells
            (G.O.Ms.No.756,Fin(FR.I),Dt.07.08.02)
            Samples of materials shall be furnished at the contractor’s expense to the Executive
            Engineer when called for in the tender notice or ordered to be furnished by the
            Executive Engineer prior to execution of any work.

            • Effect: Treated as EOL Not counted for increment/pension Counted for pension if the
            foreign employer pays pension contribution  Leave salary: No salary

            • Sanctioning authority: Govt. Only.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>PATERNITY LEAVE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            • Concept: Leave granted to male married Govt. servant having less than 2 surviving
            children to take care of his wife.

            • Period: 15 days

            • Authority: G.O.Ms.No.231,Fin(FR.I), Dt.16.09.05.

            • Admissibility: Temp./permanent employees

            • Availment: 1.Prior to date of delivery 2.below 6 months after date of delivery on
            production of MC (Memo No.20129-C/454/FR I/2010,Fin,Dt21.07.10)

            • Effect: counts for increment/pension  Leave salary: on full pay

            • Sanctioning Authority: as delegated.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>MISCELLANEOUS RULES :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            As per G.O.Ms.No:155: Fin (FR – i) Dept.,Dt:45-2010 Ex-Gratia Allowance to Government
            Employees on EOL for treatment for Leprosy/TB/Cancer Mental Illness /Heart
            Deceases/Kidney failure.

            (a) NGOs (Non Gazetted Officers) Pay not exceeding Rs 4550/- an ex-gratia allowance
            equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 1520/- and Max. of Rs 2190/- per month
            .whose drawing pay in R.P.S.1999.

            (b) (Non-Gazetted Officers) Pay not exceeding Rs 6675/- an ex-gratia allowance equal to
            half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 2960 and Max of Rs 4050/- per month. Whose
            drawing pay in R.P.S.2005.

            (c) Non Gazetted Officers Pay not exceeding Rs 11,860/- an ex-gratia allowance equal to
            half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 5770/- and Max of Rs 7490/- per month. Whose
            drawing pay in R.P.S.2010

            Class IV Employees:

            (a) Ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min
            of Rs 1270/- and Max of Rs 1920/- per month. (whose drawing pay in revised pay scales
            1999).

            (b) Ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 2335/-
            and Max of Rs 3515/- per month. (whose drawing pay in revised pay scales 2005

            (c) Ex-gratia allowance equal to half of his pay subject to a Min of Rs 4295/- and Max
            of Rs 6430/- per month. (whose drawing pay in revised pay scales 2010
        </para_desc>
    </para>

</Ebook>
