<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Ebook>

    <para>
        <para_name Color="RED">Rule No.01 --


            SHORT TITLE, SCOPE AND RELATION TO SPECIAL RULES :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) These Rules may be called the Andhra Pradesh State and Subordinate Service Rules
            1996.


            (b) The gazetted and non-gazetted posts under the State Government shall be
            constituted into various State and Subordinate Services and they shall be governed by
            the Andhra Pradesh State and Subordinate Service Rules (General Rules) and the Special
            Rules as well as adhoc rules issued by the Government.


            (c) These rules shall apply to
            the State and Subordinate Services and to the holders of posts, whether temporary or
            permanent included in any State or Subordinate Service except to the extent otherwise
            expressely provided:-

            (i) by or under any law for the time being in force;

            (ii) in respect of holders of any post, appointed by contract or agreement subsisting
            between
            such holders and the State Government.


            (d) Relation to Special Rules: If any provision
            in these rules are repugnant to the provisions in the special rules applicable to any
            particular service in regard to any specific matter, the latter shall, in respect of
            such service and such specific matter, prevail over the provisions in these rules.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.02 --


            DEFINITONS:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            In these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context:-

            (1) Adhoc Rules:- “Adhoc rules” means rules issued to govern:

            (i) a temporary post in a Service,
            Class or Category which is not covered by any Special Rules; or

            (ii) all or some of the
            services in regard to issues of common applicability of all such services.


            (2) Appointed to a Service:- A person is said to be “appointed to a service” when, in
            accordance with
            these rules, except under rule 10 and in accordance with the Special Rules or adhoc
            rules applicable to such service he discharges for the first time, the duties of a post
            borne on the cadre of such service or commences the probation, instruction or training
            prescribed for members thereof. Explanation:- The appointment of a person holding a post
            borne on the cadre of one service to hold additional charge of a post borne on the cadre
            of another service or same service or to discharge the current duties thereof does not
            amount to appointment to the latter service or post in the same service, as the case may
            be,


            (3) Approved candidate:- “Approved candidate” means a candidate whose name appears
            in an authoritative list of candidates approved for appointment to any service, class or
            category.


            (4) Approved probationer:- “Approved probationer” in a service, class or
            category means a member of that service, class or category who has satisfactorily
            completed his probation in such service, class or category.


            (5) Appointment or Recruitment by transfer: A candidate is said to be appointed or
            recruited by transfer to
            a service:-

            (a) If, at the time of his first appointment thereto he is an approved
            probationer in the Andhra Pradesh High Court Service or Andhra Pradesh Legislature
            Service or in any other service, the rules for which prescribed a period of probation
            for members thereof: or

            (b) in case at the time of his first appointment thereto he is
            the holder of a post which has been included in another service but for which no
            probation has been prescribed, if he has put in that post, satisfactory service for a
            total period of two years on duty within a continuous period of three years.


            (6) Armed
            Forces of the Union:- “Armed Forces of the Union” means the Army, Naval or Air Force of
            the Union.


            (7) Backward Classes:- “Backward Classes” mean the communities mentioned in
            Part-C of Schedule-I.


            (8) Cadre:- “Cadre” means the posts in various classes, categories
            and grades in a service.


            (9) Commission:- “Commission” means the Andhra Pradesh Public
            Service Commission.


            (10) Confirmed Member:- “Confirmed Member” means a member of a
            service who has been confirmed in a service under the State Government in accordance
            with rule 21.


            (11) Date of Regular Appointment:- “Date of Regular Appointment” means the
            date of commencement of probation, i.e., the date from which the service rendered by a
            person after appointment to a service, class or category counts for probation..


            (12) Departmental Promotion Committee:- “Departmental Promotion Committee” means a
            Committee
            constituted to advise the appointing authority in regard to the persons to be included
            in the panel for being appointed by promotion or by transfer to a selection post not
            within the purview of the Commission. Provided that the Departmental Promotion Committee
            may be required to prepare adhoc panels also for appointment to any service by promotion
            or by transfer even on temporary basis.


            (12-A) Screening Committee:- “Screening
            Committee” means a Committee constituted by Head of the Department to recommend the
            names for inclusion in the panel to the second level Gazetted Posts which are within the
            purview of the Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission: and also to indicate the order
            in which the persons concerned should be included in the panel. The list of persons so
            prepared by the said Committee shall be forwarded to the Commission for its concurrence,
            by the competent authority.


            (13) Discharge of a probationer:- “Discharge of a
            probationer” means, in case the probationer is confirmed or is an approved probationer
            or probationer of another service, class or category or is an approved probationer or
            probationer of another post in the same service, reverting him to such service, class or
            category and in every other case, dispensing with his service.


            (14) Duty:- A person is
            said to be „on duty‟ as a member of a service;

            (a) When he is performing the duties of a post borne on the cadre of such service or is
            undergoing the probation, instruction or training prescribed for such service, or is
            deputed by the competent authority for higher studies or for undergoing training in
            India or abroad; or

            (b) When he is on joining time; or

            (c) When he is absent from duty during vacation or on authorized holidays or on casual
            leave taken in accordance with instructions regulating such leave, issued by the State
            Government, having been on duty immediately before and immediately after such absence:
            or

            (d) When he is absent from duty during the period of training for courses of instruction
            and the period spent in camps as a member of the Auxiliary Air Force and also during the
            period spent for interview or for attending medical examination at the time of
            recruitment or commissioning; or

            (e) when he is absent from duty during the period of training including the period spent
            in transit as a member of the Indian Fleet Reserve or as a Reservist of the Army or Air
            Force (excluding the Reserve Officers); or

            (f) when he is absent from duty during the period of training in the Territorial Army
            including the period spent in transit for undergoing annual training in the said army;
            or

            (g) when he is absent from duty as a member of Air Defence Reserve, when called upon for
            service in the aid of the Civil Power or for Air Force Service, or during the period of
            annual training exceeding one month in the case of permanent and temporary Government
            servant and person on work-charged establishments or during the period of training in
            Air Defence Reserve or Air Force Service in the case of probationers; or

            (h) when he is absent from duty for service in the N.C.C. or during the period of
            training including the period spent in transit thereof.

            Explanation:- Participation of a Government servant in the ceremonial parade on special
            occasions like the Territorial Army Day, Republic Day, visit of a Minister and the like
            in his capacity as a member of the Air Defence Reserve, shall be treated as part of his
            training; or (i) when he is absent from duty to attend the annual day celebrations of
            the Home Guards Organisation or when called upon for duty in times of emergency as a
            member of the Home Guards Organisation.


            (15) Direct Recruitment:- A candidate is said to be recruited direct to a post, class or
            category in a service, in case his first
            appointment thereto is made otherwise than by the following methods:-

            (i) by promotion from a lower post, category or class in that service or from a lower
            grade of any such post, category or class, or

            (ii) by transfer from any other class of that service, or

            (iii) by appointment by transfer from any other service, or

            (iv) by re-employment of a person in case he had
            retired from service of Government prior to such appointment, or

            (v) by appointment by agreement or contract.


            (16) Ex-servicemen:-“Ex-Servicemen” means a person who has served in any rank (whether
            as a combatant or as a non-combatant) in the Regular Army, Navy and Air Force of the
            Indian Union but does not include a person who has served in the Defence Security Corps,
            the General Research Engineering Force, Lok-Sahayak Sena and the para-military forces,
            i.e., Border Security Force, Central Reserve Police Force, Indo-Tibetan Border Police,
            Central Industrial Security Force, Central Secretariat Security Force, Assam Rifles and
            Railway Protection Force and

            (i) who has retired from such service after earning his/her
            pension; or

            (ii) who has been released from such service on medical grounds attributable
            to military service or circumstances beyond his control and awarded medical or other
            disability pension; or

            (iii) who has been released, otherwise than on his own request,
            from such service as a result of reduction in establishment or

            (iv) who has been
            released from such service after completing the specific period of engagement, otherwise
            than at his own request or by way of dismissal or discharge on account of misconduct,
            inefficiency and has been given a gratuity and includes personnel of the Territorial
            Army of the following categories; namely:- (a) pension holders for continuous embodied
            services; (b) person with disability attributable to military services; and (c)
            gallantry award winners.

            Explanation:- The persons serving in the Armed Forces of the Union, who on retirement
            from service, would come under the category of ex-servicemen, may be permitted to apply
            for re-employment one year before the completion of the specified terms of engagement
            and avail themselves of all concessions available to ex-servicemen but shall not be
            permitted to leave the uniform until they complete the specified term of engagement in
            the Armed Forces of the Union.


            (17) General Rules:- “General Rules” means the Andhra
            Pradesh State and Subordinate Service Rules.


            (18) Member of a Service:- “Member of a
            Service” means a person who has been appointed to that service and who has not retired
            or resigned, or who has not been removed or dismissed, or substantively transferred or
            reduced to another service, or who has not been discharged otherwise than for want of a
            vacancy. He may be a probationer, an approved probationer or confirmed member of that
            service.


            (19) Meritorious Sportsman:- “Meritorious Sportsman” means a sportsman who has
            represented the State or the Country in a national or international competition or
            Universities in the Inter-University tournaments conducted by the Inter-University
            Boards or the State School team in the national sports/games for schools conducted by
            the All India School Games Federation in any of the games, sports, mentioned below; and
            any other games/sports as may be specified by the Government from time to time:

            (a) Atheletics (including Track and Field events)
            (b) Badminton
            (c) Basketball
            (d) Cricket
            (e) Hockey
            (f) Football
            (g) Swimming
            (h) Volleyball
            (i) Table Tennis
            (j) Tennis
            (k) Weightlifting
            (l) Wrestling
            (m)Boxing
            (n) Cycling
            (o) Gymnastics
            (p) Judo
            (q) Rifle Shooting
            (r) Kabbadi
            (s) Kho Kho
            (t) Ball Badminton
            (u) Archery
            (v) Equistrain Sports
            (w)Hand Ball
            (x) Rowing
            (y) Chess
            (z) Taek wondo
            (aa) Carroms


            (20) Officiating Appointment:- A person is said to be officiating in a post, if his
            appointment has been made after his inclusion in the relevant panel, but whose
            appointment has not been regularised.


            (21) Panel:- “Panel” means the authoritative list of candidates approved for regular
            appointment to any service, class or category drawn
            up by the Commission or by the Government or by the appointing authority concerned, but
            does not include the panel or list prepared for temporary appointment by the appointing
            authority pending preparation of a panel for regular appointment in accordance with the
            rules.


            (22) Physically handicapped person: “Physically handicapped person” means a
            person who is blind, deaf or orthopaedically handicapped. Explanation:- A person is said
            to be, (i) blind, if he is suffering from total absence of sight or visual acquity not
            exceeding 3-60 or 10/200 (snellen) in the better eye with correcting lenses; (ii) deaf,
            if his sense of hearing is fully non-functional for the ordinary purposes of life; (iii)
            orthodpaedically handicapped, if he has a physical defect or deformity which causes so
            much interference as to significantly impede normal functioning of the bones, muscles
            and joints.


            (23) Presidential Order: “Presidential Order” wherever it occurs in these rules shall
            mean the Andhra Pradesh Public Employment (Organization of Local Cadres and Regulation
            of Direct Recruitment) Order, 1975 issued by the President of India under Article 371-D
            of the Constitution of India.


            (24) Probation: “Probation” means the period during which a fresh entrant to a service
            or a person appointed to a higher post for the first time
            either by promotion within the service or by transfer from any other service, is put on
            test for determining his fitness to hold the post in a service, class or category.


            (25) Probationer: “Probationer” means a member in a service class or category who has
            not
            completed his probation.


            (26) Promotion: “Promotion” means the appointment a member of any category or grade of
            service or a class of service to a higher category, grade, of
            such service or such class of service.


            (27) Schedule: “Schedule” means the schedule to these rules.


            (28) Scheduled Castes:- “Scheduled Castes” mean the communities mentioned
            in Part-A of Schedule-I. Explanation: No person who professes a religion different from
            Hinduism shall be deemed a member of scheduled caste. However, Scheduled Caste converts
            to Buddhism deemed to be Scheduled Caste.


            (29) Scheduled Tribes:- “Scheduled Tribes” means the communities mentioned in Part-B of
            Schedule-I.


            (30) Service:- “Service” means a post or a group of posts or categories of posts
            classified by the State Government as
            State or Subordinate Service, as the case may be. Provided that for the purpose of
            recruitment, probation and transfer, each class included in the Andhra Pradesh General
            Service and the Andhra Pradesh General Subordinate Service shall be regarded as a
            separate service. Note:- Where the context so requires „Service‟ means the period during
            which a person holds a post in accordance with these rules, special or Ad-hoc rules
            except rule 10 or a lien on a post or is a member of a service as above defined.


            (31) Special Rules:- “Special Rules” mean the rules applicable to each service or class
            or
            category of a service, which include adhoc rules applicable to temporary posts in a
            service, or class or category, which are not covered by the special rules. Explanation:-
            The words importing either gender in these or special rules shall be taken to include
            those of the other gender if circumstances so require.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.03 A --


            CONDITIONS OF SERVICE:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The Fundamental Rules, the rules regulating the Scales of Pay, the Andhra Pradesh Civil
            Services (Conduct) Rules, Andhra Pradesh Civil Services (CCA) Rules 1991, the Andhra
            Pradesh Leave Rules, the Andhra Pradesh Government Life Insurance Fund Rules, the Andhra
            Pradesh Revised Pension Rules and any other Acts, Rules or Regulations enacted, issued
            or as may be issued by Government or other competent authority, for the time being in
            force in respect of the service conditions, shall in so far as they may be applicable
            and except to the extent expressly provided in these rule, govern members of every
            service and persons appointed to any post in any service, whether appointed regularly or
            on temporary basis, in the matter of their pay and allowances, leave, leave salary, Life
            Insurance, Pension and other conditions of Service. Provided that;

            (i) Where any such member has elected to be governed by the provisions of the Civil
            Services Regulations,
            those provisions shall apply to him.

            (ii) save as otherwise expressly provided in the Special Rules nothing contained in this
            rule shall affect the operation of the
            provisions of the Article 526 of the Civil Service Regulations or any other rule similar
            thereto, for the time being in force, relating to the fixation of pay of a member of a
            service who is in receipt of a military pension; and

            (iii) a person appointed in a department performing functions entrusted to him under
            clause (1) of Article 258 of the
            Constitution of India shall be governed in the matter of his leave and pension by the
            rules issued by the Central Government in that behalf; Provided further that the said
            rules and regulations shall, in their application to the members of the Secretariat and
            the staff of the Governor, be construed as if the functions of the State Government
            under those rules and regulations were the functions of the Governor respectively.
            Provided also, that the member of service of the former Hyderabad Government allotted to
            the State of Andhra Pradesh, shall continue to be governed by such orders as may be
            applicable to him in the matter of pay, leave rules, the Andhra Pradesh Government Life
            Insurance Fund Rules, Pension and Provident Fund.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.03 B --


            APPLICATION OF RULES :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Any rules made under the proviso to Article 309 of the Constitution of India in respect
            of any service or any class or category thereof shall be applicable to all persons
            holding the posts intended to be held by members of that service, class or category on
            the date on which such rules were made applicable. Provided that nothing in any such
            rules shall, unless a contrary intention is expressly indicated therein, operate to
            deprive any such person of any right or privilege to which he is entitled by or under
            any rule or order made applicable to him prior to the making of such rule.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.04 --


            METHOD OF APPOINTMENT :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Appointment to any service, class or category shall be by one or more of the methods
            indicated below as may be specified in the Special Rules applicable to the relevant
            post:-
            1. Direct Recruitment
            2. Recruitment / Appointment by transfer
            3. Promotion or
            4. Contract / Agreement / Re-employment


            (b) Direct Recruitment: - Where the normal method of recruitment to any service, class
            or category includes direct recruitment, the proportion in which the special rules may
            require vacancies to be filled by persons recruited direct shall be applicable to all
            substantive vacancies and direct recruitment shall be made only against the substantive
            vacancies.

            Explanation :-

            (i) For the purpose of this rule, notwithstanding anything
            contained in these rules or special or adhoc rules, substantive vacancies shall mean all
            vacancies in the permanent cadre and all vacancies in the posts which have been in
            existence for more than 5 years.

            (ii) The posts earmarked for direct recruitment in the
            Special Rules / Adhoc Rules shall be filled by direct recruits strictly and not by any
            other method.

            (iii) The percentage earmarked for direct recruitment should not fall
            short of 33 1/3% in respect of posts in State Service and 30% in respect of posts in
            Subordinate Service. (G.O. Ms. No. 142, G.A. (Ser-D) Dept., dt: 13.3.2008)

            (iv) If the special rules specify more than one method of appointment, a provision shall
            be made in
            the special rules indicating the cycle or order in which vacancies shall be filled by
            such different methods of appointments.


            (c) Re-allotment of candidates selected by the
            Public Service Commission:- The reallotment of candidates selected by the Andhra Pradesh
            Public Service Commission for appointment, from one unit to another unit, either in the
            same service and District / Zone or in any other service of district / Zone shall be
            made with the mutual consent of the appointing authorities concerned and with the prior
            concurrence of the Commission. The order of re-allotment shall be issued by the
            appointing authority to whose unit the candidate was first allotted by the Commission.
            Provided that such re-allotment shall be strictly in conformity with the provisions of
            the Presidential Order.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.05 --


            SELECTION POSTS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) All first appointments to a State Service and all promotions / appointment by
            transfer in that service shall be made on grounds of merit and ability, seniority being
            considered only where merit and ability are approximately equal, by the appointing
            authority as specified in sub-rule (a) of rule 6 from the panel of candidates. Such
            panel shall be prepared as laid down in rule 6 by the appointing authority or any other
            authority empowered in this behalf.

            (b) Non-selection posts :- No non-gazetted post should be treated as selection post.
            Promotion and appointment by transfer to higher posts other than those mentioned in
            sub-rule (a) shall be made in accordance with seniority-cum-fitness, unless.

            (i) such promotion or appointment by transfer of a member has been with held as a
            penalty; or

            (ii) a member is given special promotion for conspicuous merit and ability.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.06 --


            METHOD OF PREPARATION OF PANELS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) The panel of approved candidates referred to in sub-rule (a) of rule – 5 shall be
            prepared by the appointing authority or any other authority empowered in this behalf, in
            consultation with, the Departmental Promotion Committee in respect of posts outside the
            purview of the Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission and Screening Committee in
            respect of the posts within the purview of the Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission
            to recommend the names to the Commission. The appointing authority shall make
            appointments of candidates from such panel/list, in the order in which the candidates in
            such panel are arranged in their order of preference. (b) The panel of candidates for
            appointment by transfer to a service or a class of service in any case, where the
            Commission is not consulted on the suitability of candidate for such appointment under
            sub-clause


            (b) of Clause (3) of Article 320 of the Constitution of India or for
            promotion, shall be prepared ordinarily during the month of September every year on the
            basis of estimate of vacancies sent in terms of sub-rule (d). First September of the
            year shall be reckoned as the qualifying date to determine the eligibility of a
            candidate for such appointment, which shall cease to be inforce on the afternoon of the
            31st December of the succeeding year or till the next panel is prepared whichever is
            earlier and for the purpose of preparing the said panel, the zone of consideration shall
            be in the ratio of 1:3. The period from 1st September of the year to the 31st August of
            the succeeding year shall be reckoned for purpose of determining the number of vacancies
            during the panel: Provided that for promotion in respect of Scheduled Caste and
            Scheduled Tribe candidates only, the zone of consideration in the ratio of 1:3, shall
            not be applicable in respect of posts whose total cadre strength is more than five.
            (Amended in G.O. Ms. No. 123, G.A. (Ser-D) Dept., dt: 19.4.2003) Provided further that
            if the number of candidates to be included in the panel falls short of the number of
            vacancies estimated such shortfall shall be made good by considering the claims of the
            other qualified and eligible candidates, if any, in the seniority list place immediately
            below. Provided also that the panel of candidates so prepared shall be reviewed after a
            period of six months reckoned from the date of approval of the panel, for the purpose of
            considering the cases of such other persons whose names were not included in the panel
            prepared earlier for not passing the prescribed tests or for not having special
            qualifications prescribed under the rules, if they have subsequently passed those tests
            or acquired the said qualifications and are otherwise found suitable for inclusion in
            the panel of the year. No such review of list of approved candidates shall, however, be
            undertaken where no tests or special qualifications are prescribed under the rules as
            condition precedent for promotion or appointment by transfer: Provided also that no
            panel of candidates need be prepared;

            (i) if vacancies are not available for the particular panel period subject to the
            appointing authority recording a certificate to that effect; or

            (ii) where the appointing authority does not consider it necessary.

            Provided also that the Government may order preparation of panel of candidates as
            frequently as may be
            necessary in the exigencies of administration.


            (c) The panel of candidates for promotion or appointment by transfer to a service or
            class of a service, in any case where it is necessary to consult the Commission on the
            suitability of candidates for such appointment shall be prepared ordinarily in the month
            of September every year reckoning 1st September of the year as the qualifying date to
            determine the eligibility of a candidate for such appointment, which shall cease to be
            in force on the afternoon of 31st December of the succeeding year or till the next panel
            is prepared whichever is earlier. The period from first September of the year to 31st
            August of the succeeding year shall be reckoned for purpose of determining the number of
            vacancies during the panel.


            (d) The panel of candidates under sub rule (b) or sub-rule (c) shall consist of such
            number of candidates as is equal to the number of vacancies which are estimated to arise
            on the following basis during the currency of that list; (i) the existing vacancies,
            including the vacancies which were not filled up in the previous years for any reason:
            (ii) (1) vacancies to arise owing the retirement; (2) consequential vacancies due to
            promotion or appointment by transfer; Provided, that when the number of qualified and
            eligible candidates to be included in the panel of candidates is less than the number of
            vacancies estimated to arise during the currency of that list, such number of candidates
            eligible and found fit only shall be included in the panel irrespective of the number of
            vacancies.


            (e) A panel of candidates shall also be prepared taking into account the vacancies not
            exceeding 10% of the total estimate of vacancies, ignoring fraction of less than half or
            0.5 and rounding of fraction of ½ or more i.e. 0.5 and above to the next nearest number
            as reserve to fill up the vacancies likely to last for more than 2 months on account of
            :- (i) deputation; (ii) training; (iii) long leave; or Provided also that the candidates
            kept in reserve in the approved list shall be not less than one, where the estimate of
            vacancies is five or less than five.


            (f) Inclusion of a candidate‟s name in any panel of candidates of any State Service,
            class or category shall not confer on him any right for appointment to such service,
            class or category.


            (g) The following persons shall be considered for inclusion in any panel prepared under
            sub-rules (b) and (c).

            (i) Persons who are qualified on the qualifying date including
            those who had been included in the previous panel of approved candidates but who have
            not commenced their probation.

            (ii) Persons who had not possessed the prescribed
            qualifications at the time of preparation of the previous panel, but who have since
            acquired such qualification and are qualified as on the qualifying date.

            (iii) Persons who were qualified but were considered unsuitable for inclusion in the
            previous panel
            and who continue to possess the prescribed qualifications.

            Explanation:- In considering the inclusion of persons, who had been included in the
            previous panel but who had not
            commenced their probation, in the current panel it shall not be necessary to carry
            forward their names without having regard to their relative merit and ability with
            reference to the relative merit and ability of other candidates coming up for fresh
            consideration. If such candidates are included in the current panel it shall not be
            necessary to arrange them in the same order in which they had been arranged in the
            previous panel.


            (h) Persons included in more than one panel:- Where a candidate‟s name has been included
            in different panels of approved candidates for more than one service, the cadre
            controlling authority of the panel in which the candidate‟s name is included, should
            intimate the cadre controlling authority of the other panel of the inclusion of the name
            of the candidate in the former panel and it shall be the duty of the cadre controlling
            authority of the parent cadre to intimate the inclusion of the candidate‟s name to such
            other cadre controlling authority, if any, in whose panel the same candidate‟s name had
            been sponsored for inclusion by the cadre controlling authority, of the parent cadre.
            The cadre controlling authority of the parent cadre to intimate the inclusion of the
            candidate‟s name to such other cadre controlling authority, if any, in whose panel the
            same candidate‟s name had been sponsored for inclusion by the cadre controlling
            authority of the parent cadre. The cadre controlling authority of the parent cadre shall
            require the candidate to initiate the service to which the candidate wishes to be
            appointed. On receipt of such intimation, the cadre controlling authority of the parent
            cadre shall inform the other cadre controlling authorities and such candidate‟s name
            shall be removed by such cadre controlling authority from the panel or panels of
            approved candidates for such service or services to which the candidate does not wish to
            be appointed.


            (i) Non Selection Posts:- For non selection posts referred to in sub rule (b) of rule 5
            the appointing authority shall prepare a list of eligible employees every year i.e. from
            first September of the year to 31st August of the succeeding year after considering the
            record sheet and the qualifications prescribed for the said post in the relevant Special
            Rules for promotion to next higher category of non selection post.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.07 --


            APPOINTING AUTHORITY :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            “State Service: Unless otherwise stated in the Special rules, the regional officer shall
            be the appointing authority in respect of the initial categories of Gazetted posts in a
            State service where regional offices exists; and the Head of the Department shall be the
            appointing authority for the second level gazetted posts in a State Service as well as
            in respect of the initial categories of the Gazetted posts in a State Service where no
            regional offices exists; and the Government shall be the appointing authority for the
            third level gazetted posts and above in the State Service.”

            [Amended in G.O.Ms.No.401, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt. 30-9-1999 w.e.f. 22-5-1999].
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.08 --


            ELIGIBILITY FOR PROMOTION OR APPOINTMENT BY TRANSFER :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            For appointment to a higher post either by promotion from one category to another within
            a service or by appointment by transfer from one service to another service, a member of
            a service or class of a service, shall have satisfactorily completed his probation in
            the category from which he is proposed to be promoted or appointed by transfer to such
            higher post.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.09 --


            APPOINTMENT BY AGREEMENT OR CONTRACT :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) (i) Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules or special rules it shall be
            open to the State Government to make appointment to any post in a service, class or
            category, otherwise than in accordance with these rules or special rules and to provide
            by agreement or contract with the person(s) so appointed, for any of the matters in
            respect of which, in the opinion of the State Government, special provisions are
            required to be made and to the extent to which such provisions are made in the agreement
            or contract, nothing in these rules or the special rules shall apply to any person so
            appointed in respect of any matter for which provision is made in the agreement or
            contract. Provided that in every agreement or contract made in exercise of the powers
            conferred by these rules, it shall further by provided that in respect of any matter in
            which no provision has been made in the agreement or contract, provisions of these rules
            or special rules relatable to the post shall apply.

            (ii) The agreement or contract may
            inter alia include provisions in respect of conditions of service, pay and allowances,
            discipline, contract period of appointment notice period for termination of appointment
            by either party and other relevant matters.

            (iii) The Government may, by order,
            prescribe the form of such agreement or contract.


            (b) A person appointed under sub-rule (a) shall not be regarded as a member of the
            service, in which the post to which he is appointed, is included and shall not be
            entitled by reason only of such appointment, to any preferential right to any other
            appointment in that or in any other service.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.10 --


            TEMPORARY APPOINTMENT INCLUDING APPOINTMENTS BY DIRECT RECRUITMENT, RECRUITMENT /
            APPOINTMENT BY TRANSFER OR BY PROMOTION :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Where it is necessary in the public interest to fill emergently a vacancy in a post
            borne on the cadre of a service, class or category and if the filling of such vacancy in
            accordance with the rules is likely to result in undue delay the appointing authority
            may appoint a person temporarily, otherwise than in accordance with the said rules,
            either by direct recruitment or by promotion or by appointment by transfer, as may be
            specified as the method of appointment in respect of that post, in the special rules.


            (b) No appointment under sub-rule (a) shall be made of a person who does not possess the
            qualifications, if any, prescribed for the said service, class or category. Provided
            that where, in the exigencies of service and where persons with the prescribed
            qualifications are not available, a person who may not possess all or some of the
            prescribed qualifications may be appointed on temporary basis. Every such person who
            does not possess such qualifications and who has been or is appointed under sub-rule(a)
            shall be replaced as soon as possible, by a person possessing such qualifications.


            (c) A person appointed under sub-rule (a) shall not be regarded as a probationer in such
            service, class or category or be entitled by reason only of such appointment to any
            preferential claim to future appointments to such service, class or category.


            (d) A person temporarily appointed under sub-rule (a) shall, whether or not he possesses
            the qualifications prescribed for the service, class or category to which he is
            appointed, be replaced as soon as possible by the member of the service, who is entitled
            to the appointment under the rules.


            (e) The appointing authority shall have the right to terminate the service of a person
            who has been appointed under sub-rule(a), at any time, without assigning any reason and
            without any notice, if appointed by direct recruitment, revert to a lower category or
            grade, if promoted, or revert to the post from which such appointment by transfer was
            made, if appointed by transfer.


            (f) A person appointed to any part-time post, created in lieu of a whole time post borne
            on the cadre of a service, class or category shall not be regarded as a probationer in
            such service nor shall he be entitled by reason only of such appointment to any
            preferential claim to future appointments to such service, class or category.


            (g) No person appointed under sub-rule (a) shall be eligible to an increment in the time
            scale of pay applicable to him, unless he possess the tests, complete the training or
            acquires the qualifications prescribed in the Special Rules, as a condition for the
            grant of increment to a member of the service, class or category.


            (h) The practice of making incharge arrangements on own scale of pay of the incumbent
            concerned is totally prohibited and whenever filling up of vacant posts is considered
            expedient in the exigencies of administration, action may be taken to fill the post
            following the relevant Special/ Adhoc Rules, duly placing the proposals before the DPC /
            Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission as the case may be or by making full additional
            charge arrangements as provided for in the Fundamental Rules.


            (i) Temporary posts requiring special qualifications Notwithstanding anything contained
            in these rules or special rules, if and when, a temporary post is created as an addition
            to the cadre of any service, class or category and the holder thereof is required by the
            State Government to possess such qualifications, knowledge or experience, any person who
            possesses such qualifications, knowledge or experience and who is considered to be the
            most suitable person to discharge the duties of such post may, irrespective of other
            considerations, be appointed temporarily to that post by the appointing authority; but
            the person so appointed shall not, by reason only of such appointment, be regarded as a
            probationer in such service, class or category nor shall be acquire thereby any
            preferential right to future appointment to such service, class or category.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.11 --


            THE LIMIT FOR JOINING EITHER OF FIRST SELECTION OR ON PROMOTION OR ON APPOINTMENT BY
            TRANSFER:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Direct recruitment :- A candidate selected for appointment by direct recruitment
            either through the Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission or through any other agency,
            shall be required by the appointing authority to join in the post for which he has been
            selected within a period of 30 days taking the date of despatch (by registered post with
            acknowledgement due) of the appointment order as crucial date for reckoning the time
            limit. If he does not join the post within the stipulated period of 30 days, the offer
            of appointment shall be treated as automatically cancelled and the name of the candidate
            shall be deemed to have been omitted from the list of approved candidates.
            (Amended in G.O. Ms. No. 340, G.A. (Ser-D) Dept., dt: 23.7.1999)


            (b) Time to join a post on appointment / temporary appointment under rule 10 including
            appointments by transfer or by promotion otherwise than by direct recruitment:- A person
            on appointment / temporary appointment on adhoc basis under rule 10 including
            appointment by transfer or by promotion otherwise than by direct recruitment, shall be
            allowed a joining time of fifteen (15) days to join the post from the date of receipt of
            the order of appointment sent to the candidates by Registered Post with Acknowledgement
            due or by any other means. An employee who does not join the post within the stipulated
            time or evades to join the post by proceeding on leave, shall lose his promotion right /
            offer for the current panel year and the name of the candidate shall be placed before
            the next Departmental Promotion Committee for consideration in the next year panel
            subject to availability of vacancy. In case of non-selection posts, the name of the
            candidate who does not join within the stipulated time in the promotion posts shall be
            considered for promotion again after a period of one year from the date of offer of
            appointment subject to availability of vacancy”.
            [Amended in G.O.Ms.No.145, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 15-06-2004]
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.12 --


            QUALIFICATIONS FOR DIRECT RECRUITMENT :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (1) (a) No person shall be eligible for appointment to any service by direct recruitment
            unless he satisfies the selection authority as well as the appointing authority, that;

            (i) he is of sound health, active habits and free from any bodily defect or infirmity
            rendering him unfit for such service;

            (ii) his character and antecedents are such as to
            qualify him for such service;

            (iii) he possesses the academic and other qualifications
            prescribed for the post; and

            (iv) he is a citizen of India; Provided that no candidate
            other than a citizen of India may be appointed except with the previous sanction of the
            State Government and except in accordance with such conditions and restrictions as they
            may be laid down. Such sanction shall not be accorded unless the State Government are
            satisfied that sufficient number of citizens of India, who are qualified and suitable
            are not available.

            (v) No person shall be eligible for direct recruitment if he is less
            than 18 years of age and unless otherwise specified in the special or adhoc rules and if
            he is more than 34 years of age as on the 1st day of July of the year in which the
            notification for selection to the relevant post, category or class or a service is made.
            [Amended in G.O.Ms.No.759, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 6-10-2007 ] Provided that nothing in
            this sub-rule shall apply for direct recruitment to all the categories and posts in the
            Andhra Pradesh Police Subordinate Service and in the Andhra Pradesh Special Armed Police
            Service.


            (b) The maximum age limit prescribed in the Special Rules for direct recruitment to a
            post shall be raised:- (i) Uniformity by 5 years in the case of candidates belonging to
            the S.Cs or S.Ts or B.Cs. specified in Schedule-I of these rules: First Proviso omitted
            [vide G.O.Ms.No.759, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 6-10-2007 ] N.B.: The age concession in
            favour of B.Cs will be in force with effect from the 23rd September, 1990 to till the
            end of May, 2011. (vide G.O.Ms.No.147 G.A.(Ser. D) dt:16.05.2003 w.e.f.01-06-2001.)
            Second Proviso omitted [vide G.O.Ms.No.759, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 6-10-2007 ] Provided
            that in the case of S.Cs and S.Ts., the maximum age limit prescribed for other
            communities in the Special rules shall be raised uniformly by 10 years for the purpose
            of limited direct recruitment.
            [Amended in G.O.Ms.No.759, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 6-10-2007]

            N.B. This concession shall be in force during the period between the 28th March, 1967 to
            till the end of May, 2011. (vide G.O.Ms.No.309 G.A.(Ser. D) dt:28.09.2004 w.e.f.
            01-06-2001.) (ii) Uniformly by 10 years in the case of Physically handicapped persons:
            N.B: This concession shall be inforce during the period between the 28th March, 1967 to
            the end of May, 2011. [vide G.O.Ms.No. 147, G.A.(Ser. D) dt: 16.05.2003 w.e.f.
            01-06-2001.] (iii) In the case of widows, divorced women and women judicially separated
            from their husbands, who are not remarried, the maximum age limit for direct recruitment
            to posts carrying a scale of pay equal to Junior Assistants or less, shall not exceed 40
            years in the case of S.Cs and S.Ts candidates and 35 years in the case of others.
            Provided that for compassionate appointment to the spouse of deceased Government
            employee, the upper age limit shall be 45 years irrespective of the community. [Amended
            in G.O.Ms.No.144, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 15-6-2004. w.e.f.11.12.2003]


            (c) When direct recruitment is to be made to any State or Subordinate Service by
            examination or Selection:

            (i) a person who worked in the armed forces of the Indian
            Union, shall be allowed to deduct from his age a period of three years in addition to
            the length of service rendered by him in the armed forces for purposes of the maximum
            age limit;

            (ii) a person who was recruited as a whole-time Cadet Corpse Instructor on or
            after the 1st January, 1963 on his discharge from the NCC either before or after the
            expiry of the initial or extended tenure of his office in NCC having served for a period
            of not less than six months prior to his release from the NCC shall, subject to the
            production of a certificate to effect that he has been released from the NCC be allowed
            to deduct from his age a period of three years in addition to the length of service
            rendered by him in the NCC for purposes of maximum age limit; Provided that the person
            referred to in sub-rules (i) and (ii) above shall, after making the deductions referred
            on in the sub-rules shall not exceed the maximum age limit prescribed for the post.

            (iii) a person already in service of the State Government, who has been appointed
            regularly shall be allowed to deduct from his age the length of regular service under
            the State Government upto a maximum of five years for purposes of the maximum age limit
            and in the case of a person who has rendered minimum temporary service of six months in
            the Census Department (Organisation) of this State and who has been retrenched during
            1991 shall be allowed to deduct from his age a period of three years for purpose of
            computing the maximum age limit.


            (2) The minimum General Educational qualifications wherever referred to, in these or
            special rules shall be the qualifications prescribed in Schedule-II of these rules.


            (3) (a) A candidate should possess the academic qualifications and experience including
            practical experience prescribed, if any for the post on the date of the notification for
            direct recruitment issued by the concerned recruiting agency. (vide amendment in
            G.O.Ms.No.464,G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 10-11-1997).

            (b) No person shall be eligible for
            appointment to a post by promotion or appointment by transfer unless he possesses the
            academic qualifications and technical or other qualification and has passed the
            departmental and other tests and has satisfactorily completed any course or training
            prescribed in the special rules as a prerequisite qualification, for the post, to which
            he is to be appointed by promotion or by transfer.


            (4) Disqualification for appointment:-

            (a) A candidate shall be disqualified for
            appointment if he himself or through relations or friends or any others has canvassed or
            endeavored to enlist for his candidature extraneous support, whether from official or
            non-official sources for appointment to any State or Subordinate Service.

            (b) No person who has more than one wife living or who has spouse living, marries in any
            case, in
            which such marriage is void by reason of its taking place during the life time of such
            spouse, shall be eligible for appointment by direct recruitment to any State or
            Subordinate Service.

            (c) No woman whose marriage is void by reason of the husband having
            a wife living at the time of such marriage or who has married a person who has a wife
            living at the time of such marriage, shall be eligible for appointment by direct
            recruitment to any State or subordinate Service.

            (d) No person who has been dismissed from a State or Central Government service or from
            the service of Central or State
            Government undertaking or local or other authorities or who has been convicted by a
            court of law for an offence involving moral turpitude shall be eligible for appointment
            to any State or Subordinate Service.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.13 --


            LANGUAGE TEST IN TELUGU :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Every person appointed to a service, shall, within the period of probation, pass the
            Language test in Telugu, failing which his probation shall be extended and increments in
            the time scale of pay shall be postponed without cumulative effect till he passes the
            test. First proviso omitted (vide G.O. Ms. No. 31, G.A. (Ser-D) Dept, dt: 24 -1-2006)
            Provided that a person, who has completed the age of 45 years or who has been on
            deputation in this State from any other State or from the Government of India, or who
            being an officer of the erstwhile Government of Hyderabad has passed the language test
            in Telugu or has been exempted from passing the said test by virtue of his having passed
            an examination of equivalent standard in that language test under the Hyderabad Regional
            Language Examination Rules or who is holding a post for which no educational
            qualification is prescribed for initial recruitment, shall not be required to pass the
            language test aforesaid:

            Provided further that a person who is exempted from passing the language test in telugu
            on reaching the age of 45 years, but the pay to which such person is entitled to draw
            after reaching the age of 45 years shall be the pay which he would have been eligible
            to, without arrears, had the language test in Telugu not been prescribed at all and the
            increments not postponed.


            (b) The standard of the test referred to in sub-rule (a), above shall be a pass in the
            Second (Class) Language Test in Telugu for holders of the posts for which the
            educational qualification prescribed is the minimum General Educational Qualification
            referred to in the schedule to rule 12(2), or equivalent or higher academic
            qualification and a pass is the Third Class Language Test in Telugu for all others.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.14 --


            LANGUAGE TEST – EXEMPTION :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) A person who has passed the SSC or its equivalent examination or any other higher
            examination with Telugu as the medium of instructions and examination or with Telugu as
            one of the subjects, shall be exempted from passing the 2nd class language test in
            Telugu.


            (b) A person who has passed the 7th or 8th Class examination with Telugu as a subject or
            medium of instruction shall be exempted from passing the 3rd class Telugu Language Test.


            (c) A person who has crossed the age of 45 years.


            (d) Other Linguistic qualification :- (i) If in the opinion of an appointing authority,
            a candidate with an adequate knowledge of a particular language or languages is
            necessary for holding a specified post in any service, class or category, it may declare
            that such post, specified in the declaration, is reserved for a candidate with such
            knowledge. When such a declaration has been made, the required number of qualified
            candidates who possess such knowledge shall be selected in preference to those who do
            not possess it and notwithstanding anything contained in these rules but without
            prejudice to the rule of reservation of appointments, any such post shall be filled only
            by a member of the service or an approved candidate who possesses such knowledge. (ii)
            The State Government shall have power to declare that any proportion of posts in any
            service, class or category for which recruitment is made at the same time, shall be
            filled by candidates with an adequate knowledge of a particular language or languages
            and when such a declaration has been made, the rule of reservation of appointments shall
            apply separately in regard to the proportion of posts in respect of which such a
            declaration has been made.

            Explanation:- For the purpose of this rule a candidate will
            be considered to have adequate knowledge of the particular language, if he has acquired
            knowledge of that language in the High School or higher courses or satisfies the
            appointing authority that he has adequate knowledge in speaking, reading and writing in
            that language.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.15 --


            TIME TO PASS NEWLY PRESCRIBED TESTS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Where a test is newly prescribed by the special rules of a service for any class,
            category, or post thereof, a member of the service who has not passed the said test, but
            is otherwise qualified and suitable for promotion to such category or post may be
            promoted thereto and he shall be required to pass the said test or tests within the
            period of probation or within one year or in one of the first two examinations held
            24 after such promotion, whichever is later. If he fails to pass the tests he shall be
            reverted to the class, category, or post from which he was promoted and he shall not
            again be eligible for consideration for promotion unless he passes the tests. A person
            who is so reverted shall not by reason only of his promotion under this rule, be
            regarded as entitled to any preferential claim to future promotion to the category,
            grade or post, as the case may be, to which he had been promoted under this rule.

            Explanation:- This rule shall be applicable even to appointment by transfer in the
            direct line, for example, for appointment by transfer of Superintendents to the post of
            Assistant Director (Administration), for appointment to which the passing of
            departmental tests has been newly prescribed as a pre-requisite qualification.

            Note: This concession will be available only for a period of three years from the date
            on
            which the test has been newly prescribed.


            (b) Concessions regarding passing of Tests and Examinations on grounds of age:-
            Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules or in the Special rules, except the
            Andhra Pradesh Treasuries and Accounts Service Rules, Andhra Pradesh Treasuries and
            Accounts Subordinate Service Rules, Andhra Pradesh Pay and Accounts Service Rules,
            Andhra Pradesh Pay and Accounts Subordinate Service Rules, Andhra Pradesh Local Fund
            Audit Service Rules and Andhra Pradesh Local Fund Audit Subordinate Service Rules:-

            (i) Where no test have been prescribed in the Hyderabad Cadre and Recruitment Rules for
            promotion, an employee of the erstwhile Government of Hyderabad allotted to the State of
            Andhra Pradesh under section 115 of the States Reorganization Act, 1956 Central Act 37
            of 1956 need not pass the tests prescribed for promotion or recruitment by transfer on
            or after the 1st November, 1956, to a post one stage above that held by him prior to the
            said date. The employee so promoted shall not be affected either by reversion or by
            stoppage of increment for failure to pass such test.

            (ii) Where tests have been prescribed in the Hyderabad Cadre and Recruitment Rules, as a
            condition precedent for promotion, an employee of the erstwhile Government of Hyderabad
            referred to in clause
            (i) may be appointed by transfer or promotion to a post one stage above that held by him
            prior to the 1st November, 1956 subject to his passing the common departmental tests
            prescribed by the Government of Andhra Pradesh within four years from the date of such
            appointment by transfer or promotion, whichever is later, except where a longer period
            than four years has already been allowed to all; Provided that such an employee, on
            completion of the age of 45 years, shall not be required to pass tests referred to in
            this clause; either for the first stage promotion or for appointment by transfer or
            promotion to a post which is second or subsequent stage above that held by him prior to
            the said date.


            (c) The provisions in sub-rule (b) shall mutatis mutandis apply to an employee of the
            former Andhra State continuing in Andhra Pradesh for his appointment by transfer or
            promotion to a post above the one held by him prior to the 1st November, 1956, where:
            (i) new tests are prescribed in the Andhra Pradesh State after the said date for
            appointment by transfer or promotion to such post; or Provided that such employee, who
            on completion of the age of 45 years is not required to pass the tests for his
            appointment by transfer or promotion to a post above the one held by him prior to the
            said date, need not pass the same test if prescribed for appointment by transfer or
            promotion to a post which is second or subsequent stage above the one held by him prior
            to the said date. Explanation, sub-rule (b) shall be inforce till 31.10.1996.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.16 --


            COMMENCEMENT OF PROBATION FOR DIRECT RECRUITS:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) A person appointed in accordance with
            the rules, otherwise than under rule 10, by direct recruitment shall commence his
            probation from the date of his joining the duty or from such other date as may be
            specified by the appointing authority: Provided that a person having been appointed
            temporarily under rule-10 to a post in any service, class or category or having been so
            appointed otherwise than in accordance with the rules governing appointment to such
            post, is subsequently appointed to the same post, in the same service or class or
            category, in the same unit of appointment, in accordance with the rules, shall commence
            his probation from the date of such subsequent appointment or from such earlier date as
            the appointing authority may determine, subject to the condition that his commencement
            of probation from an earlier date shall not adversely affect any person who has been
            appointed earlier or simultaneously, to the same service, class or category in the same
            unit.


            (b) Minimum service for commencement of probation: A person appointed to a service,
            class or category, in accordance with the rules otherwise than by direct recruitment,
            shall, if he is required to be on probation in such service, class or category be deemed
            to have commenced his probation in such service, class or category from the date from
            which he has been continuously on duty in such service, class or category for a period
            of not less than 60 days from the date of joining duty after having been appointed to
            such service, class or category on a regular basis in accordance with rules: Provided
            that this rule shall not apply to a person appointed to a post in a service, class or
            category whose appointment is made in consultation with the Andhra Pradesh Public
            Service Commission or D.P.C. or any other agency for recruitment specified by
            Government.


            (c) Period of Probation:- Unless otherwise stated in the special rules or in these
            rules, the period of probation shall be as follows:-

            (i) Every person appointed by
            direct recruitment to any post shall, from the date on which he commences his probation
            be on probation for a period of two years on duty within a continuous period of three
            years.

            (ii) Every person appointed to any post either by promotion or by transfer (not
            by transfer on tenure) shall, from the date on which he commences his probation, be on
            probation for a period of one year on duty within a continuous period of two years.

            (iii) A probationer in any category, class or service shall be eligible to count for
            probation his service in a higher category of the same service or class, as the case may
            be, or in any other service (State or Subordinate Service) towards his probation in the
            former service, to the extent of the period of duty performed by him in the latter
            service during which he would have held the post in the former service but for such
            appointment in the latter service.


            (d) In regard to the persons appointed to any class or category of a service by
            promotion or appointment by transfer, in respect of whom the special rules of the
            service applicable to the higher post do not prescribe a period of probation, in the
            class or category to which they have been promoted or appointed by transfer, the
            provisions in this part shall be construed as if the expression “probation” and
            “probationer” / ”approved probationer” mean “officiating service” and “person
            officiating” respectively.


            (e) Tests to passed during probation: A person who has commenced his probation in a
            service, class or category shall, within the period of probation, if so required in the
            special rules or these rules, pass such tests or acquire such qualifications as may be
            prescribed in these rules or in the special rules applicable to such service, class or
            category.


            (f) (i) If within the period of probation a candidate fails to pass such test or acquire
            such qualifications as may be prescribed in these rules or in the special rules, the
            appointing authority shall, by order, discharge him form the service unless the period
            of probation is extended under the sub-rule (b) of rule 17 and if within such extended
            period also, the candidate fails to pass such tests or acquire such special
            qualifications, the appointing authority shall discharge him from service.

            (ii) If within the period of probation or within the extended period of probation, as
            the case
            may be, a probationer has appeared for any such test or any examination in connection
            with the passing of such prescribed tests or with the acquisition of the prescribed
            qualifications and the results of such tests or examinations for which he has so
            appeared are not known before the expiry of the probation period, he shall continue to
            be on probation until the publication of results of such tests or examinations for which
            he has appeared, or the first of them in which he fails to pass, as the case may be.

            (iii) In case the probationer fails to pass any of the tests or examinations for which
            he has so appeared, the appointing authority shall, by an order, discharge him from
            service. Any delay in the issue of the order discharging the probationer under clause
            (i) or clause (iii) of this sub-rule shall not entitle him to be deemed to have
            satisfactorily completed his probation.


            (g) Exemption from special qualifications to be acquired or special tests to be passed
            during probation:- Where a probationer has, before he commenced his probation, already
            acquired any special qualification or passed any special test prescribed in these or in
            the special rules, or has acquired such other qualification as may be considered by the
            State Government or by the appointing authority, with the approval of the State
            Government, to be equivalent to the said Special qualification or special test, he shall
            not be required to acquire the said special qualification or to pass the said special
            test again, after the commencement of his probation.


            (h) Change of date of commencement of probation:- Notwithstanding anything contained in
            the special rules or sub-rule(a) and (b) of rule 33, a probationer who does not pass the
            prescribed tests or acquire the prescribed special qualifications within the period of
            probation or within the extended period of probation under rule 17 and whose probation
            is further extended by the Government by an order under rule 31, till the date of his
            passing such tests or acquiring such qualifications, shall be deemed to have commenced
            the probation with effect from the date to be fixed by the Government, which would be
            anterior to a date to his passing such tests or acquiring such special qualifications,
            so, however, that the interval between the two dates shall be equivalent to the
            prescribed period of probation, whether on duty or otherwise and seniority of such
            probationer shall be determined with reference to the date so fixed. Provided that
            nothing in this sub-rule shall apply in the cases of persons appointed to the class,
            category or grade in a service prior to the 9th March, 1981 and whose seniority in the
            said class, category or grade was fixed under sub-rule(b) of Rule 33, prior to the said
            date.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.17 --


            SUSPENSION, TERMINATION ON EXTENSION OF PROBATION :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) (i) The appointing authority may, at any time, before the expiry of the prescribed
            period of probation, suspend the probation of a probationer and discharge him from
            service for want of vacancy.

            (ii) The appointing authority may, at any time, before or
            after the expiry of the prescribed period of probation either extend by not more than
            one year, whether on duty or otherwise, the period of probation of a probationer, in
            case the probation has not been extended under sub-rule (b) of this rule or terminate
            his probation and discharge him from service after giving him one month‟s notice or one
            month‟s pay in lieu of such notice, on account of unsatisfactory performance or progress
            during training or unsatisfactory performance of duties or unsatisfactory conduct or for
            any other sufficient reason to be recorded in writing.

            (iii) The appointing authority may, at any time, before the expiry of the prescribed
            period of probation, post the
            probationer under another officer in order to make sure that the previous report made on
            his performance or conduct by a superior officer is not a biased one.


            (b) In the case of any probationer failing to pass the tests or acquire the prescribed
            qualifications, the appointing authority may extend his probation to enable him to pass
            the prescribed tests or acquire special qualifications, as the case may be. Such
            extension by the appointing authority shall not exceed one year, whether on duty or
            otherwise in such service, class or category.


            (c) (i) In cases where the probation of a probationer is extended, his increment shall
            be postponed until he completes his probation satisfactorily, by the period by which his
            probation is extended. Such postponement of increment shall not, however, be treated as
            a penalty but only as a condition of extension of probation and shall not have the
            effect of postponement of future increments after he completes his probation
            satisfactorily.

            (ii) However, in the case of a person whose probation is one year on duty and whose
            increment is biennial, the increment shall be postponed until he completes his
            probation, but shall not be postponed, if it falls due after he completed his probation
            satisfactorily.


            (d) Penalty on a member on the maximum of his pay Scale for failure to pass prescribed
            tests: Where the special rules or these rules prescribe postponement of increments as a
            penalty for failure to pass a special test or acquire a special qualification prescribed
            in these rules, such failure shall, in the case of a member who has reached the maximum
            of the time scale of pay applicable to him, render him liable to the penalty of
            reduction to the next lower stage in his time-scale.


            (e) Appeal against discharge of a probationer:-


            (i) A probationer, who is discharged
            under clause (i) or clause (iii) or sub-rule (f) of rule 16, shall be entitled to
            appeal, within a period of 30 days from the date of receipt of the order of discharge,
            against the order of discharge passed by the competent authority to the authority to
            which an appeal would lie against the order of dismissal passed by the competent
            authority against the member of a service. Provided that in the case of a probationer in
            a State service who is discharged from service by an authority subordinate to the State
            Government, an appeal would lie only to the State Government.


            (ii) The authority
            competent to entertain an appeal under clause (i) may, either of its own motion or
            otherwise, revise any order discharging a probationer under any of the provisions
            referred to in the said clause within one year of the date of such order. Note: The
            period between the date of discharge of a probationer and date of restoration shall be
            excluded for calculating the period of two years or three years as the case may be
            referred to in clause (i) and (ii) in sub-rule (c) of rule 16.


            (iii) Where the appellate
            or revisionary authority sets aside an order discharging a probationer on the ground
            that his discharge was wholly unjustified and the probationer is restored to the
            service, the period on and from the date of discharge to the date of such restoration,
            shall be treated.

            (a) Where the said authority is of the opinion that the discharge of the probationer was
            wholly unjustified, as on duty, except for the purpose of probation;

            (b) in any other case, not as on duty, unless the said authority directs that it shall
            be so treated for any specified purpose.


            (iv) Such probationer shall be given for the period such order of discharge as has been
            in force:

            (a) In the case where the discharge of the probationer has been held as fully
            unjustified, the full pay and allowances to which he would be entitled, had that order
            of discharge not been issued.

            (b) In any other case, such pay and allowances, as the authority passing the order shall
            determine.


            (v) The period of probation undergone by a probationer discharged under clause (i) and
            (iii) of sub-rule (a) of this rule, before his discharge shall, upon such restoration,
            count towards the period of probation prescribed by the rules applicable to him.

        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.18 --


            DECLARATION OF PROBATION :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) At the end of the prescribed or extended period of probation, as the case may be,
            the appointing authority shall consider whether the probationer should be considered to
            have satisfactorily completed his period of probation and after taking a decision in
            this regard, he shall issue an order declaring the probationer to have satisfactorily
            completed his probation.


            (b) (i) The decision whether the probationer has satisfactorily completed his probation
            or whether his probation should be extended, shall be taken soon after the expiry of the
            prescribed period of probation. If any lapses are noticed during the period of probation
            by the appointing authority or a higher authority, such lapses should be communicated to
            the probationer, as soon as such lapse is noticed, so as to enable the probationer to
            rectify such lapses. A decision whether a probationer could be considered to have
            satisfactorily completed his probation or his probation should be extended or discharged
            or suspended shall be taken within a period of 8 weeks after the expiry of the
            prescribed period of probations. (ii) If no order as referred to in sub-rule (a) is
            issued within one year from the date of expiry of the prescribed or extended period of
            probation, the probationer shall, subject to other provisions of these rules, be deemed
            to have completed satisfactorily his probation with retrospective effect from the date
            of expiry of the prescribed or extended period of probation and a formal order to that
            effect may be issued for purpose of record: Provided that nothing in this sub-rule shall
            apply to a probationer who has been communicated a memorandum of charges during the
            prescribed or extended period of probation or who has failed to acquire the special
            qualifications or to pass the special tests, if any prescribed in the special rules or
            to acquire such other qualifications, as may be declared by the State Government or by
            the appointing authority with the approval of the State Government, to be equivalent to
            the said special qualifications or special tests, within the said period of probation.
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.19 --


            RIGHTS OF A PROBATIONER AND APPROVED PROBATIONER FOR RE-APPOINTMENT :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) A vacancy in a service, class or category shall not be filled by appointment of a
            person who has not yet commenced his probation in such service, class or category when
            an approved probationer or probationer is available for such appointment.

            (b) (i) Discharge of a probationer or approved probationer:- A probationer or an
            approved probationer shall be discharged from service, in the event of non-availability
            of a vacancy, in the following order:-

            1. The probationers in the order of juniority
            2. The approved probationers in the order of juniority:
            Provided that where, in course of discharge of persons appointed to a service, class or
            category consequent on the retrenchment of the posts in any administrative unit, the
            representation of the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes in that unit falls, short
            of the percentage of posts reserved for those Castes or Tribes, the persons belonging to
            the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes, as the case may be, shall be discharged in
            the order of juniority, only after all other persons appointed in that unit belonging to
            these castes or Tribes are discharged, that is to say, the discharge of persons in any
            administrative unit consequent on the retrenchment of posts, shall be in the following
            order:-
            First ……… Persons, other than those belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled
            Tribes,
            appointed temporarily, in the order of juniority;

            Second ………. Probationers, other than those belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the
            Scheduled
            Tribes, in the order of juniority;

            Third ……….. Approved probationers, other than those belonging to the Scheduled Castes
            and the
            Scheduled Tribes, in the order of juniority;

            Fourth ………… Persons belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes,
            appointed
            temporarily in the order of juniority;


            Fifth ……….. Probationers belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes, in
            the order of
            juniority;

            Sixth ……….. Approved probationers belonging to the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled
            Tribes, in the
            order of juniority.

            (ii) For the purpose of this rule, the posts borne on the cadre of a service, class or
            category in respect of recruitment to which the principle of reservation of appointments
            is made applicable, shall be deemed to have been reserved so as to secure fifteen
            percent of the posts for the Scheduled Castes and six percent of the posts for the
            Scheduled Tribes.


            (c) Right of re-appointment / promotion / appointment by transfer of an approved
            probationer on foreign service or on deputation: The absence of an approved probationer
            from a post in a service, class or category whether on leave or on foreign service or on
            deputation or for any other reason, if his lien on such service, is not terminated or
            suspended, shall not, if he is otherwise eligible and qualified, render him ineligible
            in his turn:-

            (i) for re-appointment to the post on which he is an approved probationer;

            (ii) for promotion from a lower to the higher category in such service;

            (iii) for appointment to a post in a class or category in another service for which he
            may be an approved candidate, as the case may be, in the same manner as if he is not
            absent. He shall be entitled to all the privileges in respect of appointment, seniority,
            which he would have enjoyed but for his absence: Provided that a member of service who
            is appointed to another service and if he is a probationer in the later service shall
            not be appointed to any other service for which he may be an approved candidate, unless
            he relinquishes his right in such latter service in which he is a probationer: Provided
            further that the absence of a member of a service from duty in such service, whose lien
            in a post borne on the cadre of such service is deemed to have been terminated on
            account of being an approved probationer in a class, or category in any other service
            shall not be eligible:-

            1) for re-appointment to a regular post, whether permanent or temporary in the former
            service in which he was an approved probationer; or

            2) for promotion from a lower to a higher category in such former service.

            Note:- This provision shall not be applicable to a person who is a member of two
            services where one of them is normally a feeder service or category to the other.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.20 --


            EXERCISE OF CERTAIN POWERS OF APPOINTING AUTHORITIES IN RESPECT OF PROBATIONERS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The power exercisable by the appointing authority other than the State Government, may
            be exercised also by any higher authority to whom such appointing authority is
            administratively subordinate, whether directly or indirectly, in the following cases
            namely:- (1) discharge of a probationer under sub-rule (f) of rule 16 or clause (ii) of
            sub-rule (a) of rule 17; and (2) extension of probation under sub-rule (a) or (b) of
            rule 17.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.21 --


            CONFIRMATION :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Confirmation of a member of service :- As soon as a person appointed initially in a
            service or class of a service is declared to have satisfactorily completed his probation
            or deemed to have satisfactorily completed his probation, he shall be confirmed as a
            member of that service, by the appointing authority. The seniority of the person shall
            however be regulated in terms of rule 33 of these rules.

            Explanation :-

            (1) For the purpose of the rule “appointed initially” means appointment
            of a person for the first time to any post in the civil service in the State or Civil
            post in the service of the State of Andhra Pradesh.

            (2) A member of a service or a class
            of a service shall be confirmed in such service or class of a service irrespective of
            whether there is a permanent or substantive post or vacancy available in that service.

            (3) A person appointed to a Government service shall be confirmed in any service, only
            once during his service in Government at the entry grade, irrespective of whether
            subsequently he is promoted within the same service or appointment by transfer to some
            other service or class of service, from time to time.


            (b) A person confirmed in a particular category, class or service shall not be confirmed
            in any other category, class or service.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.22 --


            SPECIAL REPRESENTATION (RESERVATION) :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            1 Reservations may be made for appointments to a service, class or category in favour of
            Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, Backward Classes, Women, Physically handicapped,
            Meritorious Sportsman, Ex-Servicemen and such other categories, as may be prescribed by
            the Government from time to time, to the extent and in the manner specified hereinafter
            in these rules or as the case may be, in the special rules. The principle of reservation
            as hereinafter provided shall apply to all appointments to a service, class or
            category:- (i) by direct recruitment, except where the Government by a General or
            special order made in this behalf, exempt such service, class or category; (ii)
            otherwise than by direct recruitment the principle of reservation in the matter of
            promotion and appointment by transfer involving promotion in so far it relates to
            Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes only shall apply to such Services, Class or
            Category whose total cadre strength of the post is more than five. [Amended in
            G.O.Ms.No. 123, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt:19-04-2003 (w.e.f. 14-02-2003.)]


            2. (a) The unit of appointment for the purpose of direct recruitment shall be hundred
            vacancies of which fifteen shall be reserved for Scheduled Castes, six shall be reserved
            for Scheduled Tribes, twenty five shall be reserved for Backward Classes and remaining
            fifty four appointments shall be made on the basis of open competition and subject to
            Rule 22-A of these rules. (i) The unit of appointment for the purpose of reservation in
            the matter of promotion and appointment by transfer involving promotion shall be hundred
            vacancies of which fifteen shall be reserved for Scheduled Castes and six for Scheduled
            Tribe employees as per the roster points in sub-rule 2(e).

            A. In the case of appointments / promotions to the posts referred to in clause 2 (a) (i)
            above, the panels of eligible candidates for promotion, the names of eligible Scheduled
            Caste and Scheduled Tribe employees from the feeder Category have to be shown against
            the roster points earmarked for them irrespective of their seniority position in the
            feeder category.

            B. If a Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe employee gets a higher place in the eligible
            candidates list by virtue of his seniority in the feeder category he need not be
            adjusted in a lower position which is earmarked for an Scheduled Caste and Scheduled
            Tribe employees as per roster system. Such roster point has to be filled up by moving up
            an Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe employees who is below in the seniority list in
            the feeder category.

            C. Filling up the roster points shall continue till the required percentage of Scheduled
            Caste and Scheduled Tribe candidates is obtained. Once the required percentage is
            obtained by taking into account both the Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe candidates
            who are found in the list of candidates fit for promotion on account of their seniority
            in the feeder category and those who are moved up to fill up the required roster point,
            further adjustment of Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe employees against roster point
            has to be stopped.

            D. Unutilized roster points after the required Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribes
            percentage is met, shall lapse.

            E. If required number of Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe employees are not available
            in the feeder category to obtain the required representation in the promotion category.
            The vacancies earmarked for Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe employees according to
            the roster points will be carried forward.
            [Amended in G.O.Ms.No. 123 G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 19-04-2003 (w.e.f. 14-02-2003.)]


            (b) Out of fifty four appointments to be made on the basis of open competition, three
            appointments shall be reserved for direct recruitment of the physically handicapped
            persons.


            (c) In the case of appointments to clerical posts including the posts of typists i.e. in
            Group II and Group IV services in the case of posts in the Andhra Pradesh Police
            Subordinate Service, to which the principle of reservation of appointments applies, out
            of fifty four as the case may be, fifty one appointments to be made on the basis of open
            competition, two appointments shall be reserved for direct recruitment of Ex-servicemen.


            (d) In the case of appointments to the posts of Junior Assistants, Junior Stenographers
            and Typists in the offices of Heads of Departments, Assistant Section Officers,
            Typist-cum-Assistants and Junior Stenographers in the Secretariat to which the principle
            of reservation of appointment applies, out of fifty four, as the case may be, forty nine
            appointments to be made on the basis of open competition, one appointment shall be
            reserved for direct recruitment of meritorious sportsmen.
            [Amended in G.O.Ms.No. 147 G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 16-05-2003 w.e.f. 01-06-2001.]

            Provided that the claims of members of the Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, Backward
            Classes, Women and the Physically handicapped persons or the Ex-servicemen as the case
            may be, shall also be considered for the remaining appointments which shall be filled on
            the basis of open competition, the number of appointments reserved for that category
            shall in no way be affected during the period the reservation for that category is in
            force.


            (e) Appointments under this rule shall be made in the order of rotation specified below
            in a unit of hundred vacancies:-

            1) Open Competition ---- Women

            2) Scheduled Castes ---- Women

            3) Open Competition

            4) Backward Class (Group-A) ---- Women

            5) Open Competition

            6) Visually Handicapped ---- Women
            Amended in G.O. Ms. No. 252, GA (Ser-D) Dept., dt: 28.8.2004 w.e.27.11.2003

            7) Scheduled Castes

            8) Scheduled Tribes --- Women

            9) Open Competition

            10) Backward Class (Group-B) --- Women

            11) Open Competition

            12) Open Competition --- Women

            13) Open Competition

            14) Backward Class (Group-C) --- Women
            In every 3rd cycle of 100 point roster (vide GO Ms. No. 476. GA (Ser.D) Dept., dt:
            15.11.97

            15) Open Competition

            16) Scheduled Castes

            17) Open Competition --- Women

            18) Backward Class (Group-D) -- Women

            19) Open Competition

            20) Backward Class (Group-A)

            21) Open Competition

            22) Scheduled Castes --- Women

            23) Open Competition --- Women

            24) Backward Class (Group-B)

            25) Scheduled Tribes

            26) Open Competition

            27) Scheduled Castes

            28) Open Competition

            29) Backward Class (Group-A)

            30) Open Competition --- Women

            31) Hearing Handicapped (Open)
            Amended in G.O. Ms. No. 252, GA (Ser-D) Dept., dt: 28.8.2004 w.e.f. 27.11.2003

            32) Open Competition

            33) Scheduled Tribes

            34) Open Competition --- Women

            35) Backward Class (Group-B)

            36) Open Competition

            37) Open Competition

            38) Open Competition --- Women

            39) Backward Class (Group-D)

            40) Open Competition

            41) Scheduled Castes

            42) Open Competition

            43) Backward Class (Group-D)

            44) Open Competition --- Women

            45) Backward Class (Group-A) --- Women

            46) Open Competition

            47) Scheduled Castes --- Women

            48) Open Competition

            49) Backward Class (Group-B) --- Women

            50) Open Competition --- Women

            51) Open Competition

            52) Scheduled Castes

            53) Open Competition

            54) Backward Class (Group-A)

            55) Open Competition --- Women

            56) Orthopaedically Handicapped (Open)
            Amended in G.O. Ms. No. 252, GA (Ser-D) Dept., dt: 28.8.2004 w.e.f. 27.11.2003

            57) Open Competition

            58) Scheduled Tribes --- Women

            59) Open Competition --- Women

            60) Backward Class (Group-B)

            61) Open Competition

            62) Scheduled Castes

            63) Open Competition

            64) Backward Class (Group-D) --- Women

            65) Open Competition --- Women

            66) Scheduled Castes --- Women

            67) Open Competition

            68) Backward Class (Group-D)

            69) Open Competition

            70) Backward Class (Group-A)

            71) Open Competition --- Women

            72) Scheduled Castes

            73) Open Competition

            74) Backward Class (Group-B)

            75) Scheduled Tribes

            76) Open Competition

            77) Scheduled Castes

            78) Open Competition --- Women

            79) Backward Class (Group-A)

            80) Open Competition

            81) Backward Class (Group-B) --- Women

            82) Open Competition

            83) Scheduled Tribes

            84) Open Competition --- Women

            85) Backward Class (Group-B)

            86) Open Competition

            87) Scheduled Castes --- Women

            88) Open Competition

            89) Backward Class (Group-D)

            90) Open Competition --- Women

            91) Scheduled Castes

            92) Open Competition

            93) Backward Class (Group-D)

            94) Open Competition

            95) Backward Class (Group-B)

            96) Open Competition --- Women

            97) Scheduled Castes

            98) Open Competition

            99) Backward Class (Group-B) --- Women

            100) Open Competition


            Provided that :- (i) in the case of appointments to a post referred to in sub-rule (c),
            the 13th and 37th turns in each unit of hundred vacancies shall be reserved for
            ex-servicemen. Out of 13th and 37th roster points, preference to one of the two points
            for women can be given and if women candidates are not available, both the points with
            men shall be considered. However, wherever the special or adhoc rules provide that there
            shall be no reservation for ex-servicemen or if a qualified and suitable candidate is
            not available from ex-servicemen, the turn allotted to ex-servicemen shall be deemed to
            be allotted to Open Competition. (Amended in G.O.Ms.No.310, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt:
            19-7-2005 w.e.f. 10.2.2005) “(ii) In the second cycle of 100 roster points the following
            points shall be reserved as follows:- “106. (Visually Handicapped) (Open) 131. (Hearing
            Handicapped) (Women) 156. (Orthopaedically Handicapped) (Open)” In the third cycle of
            100 roster points the following points shall be reserved as follows:- “206. (Visually
            Handicapped) (Open) 231. (Hearing Handicapped) (Open) 256. (Orthopaedically Handicapped)
            (Women)” The 6th, 31st and 56th points in each cycle of 100 vacancies shall be allotted
            to the Visually Handicapped, Hearing Handicapped and Orthopaedically Handicapped persons
            respectively as stated above and where qualified and suitable candidates are not
            available from among them, the turn allotted for them in the unit referred to above
            shall be carried forward for three succeeding recruitment years. In the third succeeding
            recruitment year, if disabled candidates from any category are not available for
            appointment in the turn allotted, the vacancy shall be filled by next group of disabled
            in rotation by effecting interchange and the reservation shall cease thereafter”.
            (Amended in G.O. Ms. No. 252, G.A. (Ser-D) Dept. dt: 28.8.2004 w.e.f 27.11.2003) (f) The
            reservation in the case of Backward Classes (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the
            case may be (Group-D) and Physically Handicapped persons shall be in force for the
            period commencing from the 23rd September, 1990 to 31st May, 2011 [Amended in G.O. Ms.
            No. 147 G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 16-05-2003 w.e.f.01-06-2001.]

            (g) If in any recruitment, qualified candidates belonging to the Scheduled Castes,
            Scheduled Tribes, Backward Classes (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may
            be (Group-D) and women are not available for appointment to any or all the vacancies
            reserved for them, a limited recruitment confined to candidates belonging to them shall
            be made immediately after the general recruitment to select and appoint qualified
            candidates from among the persons belonging to these communities to fill such reserved
            vacancies.


            (h) (I) If in any recruitment, qualified candidates belonging to Scheduled Castes or,
            Scheduled Tribes or, Backward Classes (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case
            may be (Group-D) or women are not available for appointment to all or any of the
            vacancies reserved for them even after conducting a limited recruitment as specified in
            sub-rule (g), such vacancies or vacancy may be allotted to the Open Competition after
            obtaining the permission of the Government and may, thereafter, be filled by a candidate
            or candidates selected on the basis of Open Competition. (II) Where any vacancies
            reserved for the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes or, Backward Classes (Group-A),
            (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) or Women are so filled by
            candidates belonging to other communities, an equal number of vacancies shall be
            reserved in the succeeding recruitment for the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes or,
            Backward Classes or Women in addition to the vacancies that may be available for that
            recruitment for them and if in the said succeeding recruitment year also, qualified
            candidates belonging to the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes or, Backward Classes
            (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) or Women are not
            available for appointment all or any of the additional vacancies which are so reserved
            in the that succeeding recruitment year, an equal number of vacancies shall again be
            reserved in the next succeeding recruitment year for the Scheduled Castes or, Scheduled
            Tribes or, Backward Classes (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be
            (Group-D) or Women in addition to the number of vacancies that may be available for the
            next succeeding recruitment for the Scheduled Castes or, Scheduled Tribes or, Backward
            Classes (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) or Women.
            Provided that if in the said second succeeding recruitment also no qualified candidates
            belonging to the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes or Backward Classes (Group-A),
            (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) or Women are available for
            appointment to all or any of the additional vacancies which are so reserved in that
            succeeding recruitment year, an equal number of vacancies shall again be reserved in the
            next succeeding recruitment year for the Scheduled Castes or, Scheduled Tribes or,
            Backward Classes (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) or
            Women in addition to the number of vacancies that may be available for the next
            succeeding recruitment for the Scheduled Castes or, Scheduled Tribes or Backward Classes
            or Women. Provided further that in the third succeeding recruitment if qualified
            candidates belonging to the Scheduled Tribes or as the case may be Scheduled Castes are
            not available, a vacancy reserved to be filled by a candidate belonging to Scheduled
            Tribes may be filled by a candidate belonging to Scheduled Castes and a vacancy reserved
            to be filled by a candidate belonging to Scheduled Castes may be filled by a candidate
            belonging to Scheduled Tribes and if a qualified candidate belonging to a particular
            group of Backward Classes (Group-A), (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be
            (Group-D) is not available for appointment, the vacancy reserved to that group shall
            accrue to the next group.

            Third Proviso omitted (G.O. Ms. No. 236, G.A. (Ser-D) Dept., dt: 25.6.1998)

            (III) If any additional vacancy or vacancies reserved in favour of candidates belonging
            to the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes or Backward Classes (Group-A), (Group-B),
            (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) or Women in any recruitment in accordance
            with the provisions in clause (II), appointments thereto shall be made before the
            appointments in the order of rotation for the relevant recruitments are made.


            (i) At no selection for recruitment other than any limited recruitment made in
            accordance with the provisions of sub-rule (g), the number of reserved vacancies
            including the additional vacancies reserved under sub-rule (h), shall exceed 52% of the
            total number of vacancies for the selection; and all vacancies in excess of 52% of the
            total number of vacancies for which recruitment is made on any particular occasion
            shall, notwithstanding anything in this rule, be treated as unreserved: Provided further
            that the carry forward vacancies and current reserved vacancies in a recruitment year
            shall be available for utilisation even where the total number of such reserved
            vacancies exceeds 52% of the vacancies filled in that recruitment, in case the overall
            representation of the Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, Backward Classes (Group-A),
            (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) and Women in the total strength of
            the concerned grade or cadre, has not reached and prescribed percentage of reservation
            of 15% for the Scheduled Castes, 6% for the Scheduled Tribes, 7% for Backward Classes
            (Group-A), 10% for Backward Classes (Group-B), 1% for Backward Classes (Group-C), 7% for
            Backward Classes (Group-D) respectively.


            (j) Where there is only a single solitary post borne on the class, or category of a
            service, the rule of special representation shall not apply for appointment to such
            post, not withstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-rules. Provided that the
            rule of special representation shall be applicable for appointment if the number of
            posts borne on the cadre, category of grade is more than one, even though selection is
            to be made against only one vacancy at any recruitment other than limited recruitment.


            (k) In respect of appointments by promotion or recruitment by transfer from Subordinate
            Service to State Service, where such appointments or recruitment by transfer is required
            to be made on the principle of merit and ability, seniority being considered only where
            merit and ability are approximately equal, the claims of any members of the Scheduled
            Castes and Tribes shall be considered for such appointment on the basis of seniority
            subject to fitness. Provided that a member of the Scheduled Caste or the Scheduled Tribe
            possessing superior merit and ability shall be allowed to supersede not only others but
            also the members of Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes as the case may be. Note:-

            1) The principle of carry forward of vacancies in respect of Backward Classes (Group-A),
            (Group-B), (Group-C) and as the case may be (Group-D) shall be with effect from the 18th
            March, 1996.

            2) The principle of carry forward of vacancies in respect of women shall be with effect
            from the 28th October, 1996.

            3) The principle of roster points for women candidates shall be with effect from the 1st
            August, 1996.
            (As amended in G.O.Ms.No.65, Genl. Admn. Dept., (Ser. D) Dept., dt:15-2-1997)

        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.22 A --


            WOMEN RESERVATION IN APPOINTMENTS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Not withstanding anything contained in these rules or special rules or Adhoc rules:- (1)
            In the matter of direct recruitment to posts for which women are better suited than men,
            preference shall be given to women: Provided that such absolute preference to women
            shall not result in total exclusion of men in any category of posts. (2) In the matter
            of direct recruitment to posts for which women and men are equally suited, there shall
            be reservation to women to an extent of 33 1/3% of the posts in each category of Open
            Competition, Backward Classes (Group-A), Backward Classes (Group-B), Backward Classes
            (Group-C), Backward Classes (Group-D), Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and Physically
            Handicapped and Ex-servicemen quota. (3) In the matter of direct recruitment to posts
            which are reserved exclusively for being filled for women, they shall be filled by women
            only.

            NOTE:- (1) The principle of reservation for women candidates to the extent of 30% in the
            matter of direct recruitment shall be from 02-01-1984 to 27-05-1996 (G.O.Ms.No.928,
            General Administration (Services D) Department, dated 06-10-1995). (2) The principle of
            reservation for women candidates to the extent of 33 1/3 % in the matter of direct
            recruitment shall be with effect from the 28th May, 1996 (G.O.Ms.No.237, General
            Administration (Services D) Department, dated 28-5-1996). (As amended in G.O.Ms.No.65,
            General Administration (Services D) Department Dt:15-2-1997).
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.23 --


            APPEAL, REVISION AND REVIEW OF ORDERS OF APPOINTMENT (INCLUDING PROMOTION) TO HIGHER
            POSTS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            An order appointing a member of a service or class of service or category, to a higher
            post by transfer or by promotion may, within a period of six months from the date of
            such order, be revised by an authority to which an appeal would lie against the order of
            dismissal passed against a member of a service, class or category, such revision may be
            made by the appellate authority aforesaid, either on its own motion or on an appeal
            filed by the aggrieved member of the service, class or category:

            Provided that the Government may, irrespective or whether they are the appellate
            authority or not, revise such order of appointment after the expiry of the period of six
            months aforesaid, for special and sufficient reasons to be recorded in writing: Provided
            further that no order or revision under this rule shall be passed unless the person
            likely to be affected by such revision is given an opportunity of making his
            representation against the proposed revision. Provided also that a member of service may
            submit a revision petition against the order of the Appellate Authority, within three
            months of the order passed by the Appellate Authority, to the Government. [ Amended in
            G.O.Ms.No. 76, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 11-3-2003. (3rd proviso added)]
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.24 --


            REVISION OF LISTS OF APPROVED CANDIDATES (PANELS) OR LIST OF ELIGIBLE CANDIDATES FOR
            APPOINTMENT BY PROMOTION OR BY TRANSFER :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) The State Government shall have the power to revise in any manner they consider
            suitable, any panel of approved candidates for appointment by transfer or by promotion
            to any category class or service, prepared by a Head of the Department or any other
            authority subordinate to the Head of the Department, in exercise of the powers conferred
            on them by the special rules or these rules: Provided that before revision of the panel
            is under taken the cases for review should be placed before the D.P.C/Review D.P.C/
            Screening Committee and their recommendations obtained: Provided that where the panel is
            prepared by an authority subordinate to a Head of the Department, in exercise of the
            powers conferred on him by the special rules, the aforesaid power of revision may be
            exercised by the Head of the Department. This will not preclude the State Government
            from exercising the powers of the revision aforesaid, against the orders either of the
            Head of the Department or of any other subordinate authority aforesaid.


            (b) The State Government and the Head of the Department shall have power to revise in
            any manner they consider suitable, any list of eligible candidates for promotion to any
            category, class or service in respect of the subordinate service, prepared in accordance
            with rule-5. The aforesaid power of revision by the State Government could be exercised
            by them in respect of an order passed by the Head of the Department or by any other
            subordinate authority.


            (c) The aforesaid power or revision mentioned in sub rule (a) and sub-rule (b), may be
            exercised by the State Government or by the Head of the Department on their own motion,
            at any time, or on an application made by the aggrieved person, within a period of six
            months from the date of order of appointment or promotion of a person junior to the
            aggrieved person: Provided that the time limit of six months aforesaid may, for good and
            sufficient reasons to be recorded in writing, be waived by the State Government Provided
            further that where the panel referred to in sub-rule (a) has been partially utilized,
            any order of revision likely to affect a person who has already been appointed from such
            panel shall be given an opportunity of making his representation against the proposed
            revision, before any order of revision is passed. Provided also that if any revision of
            list of eligible candidates mentioned in sub-rule (b) is likely to affect a person
            already promoted from the aforesaid list of eligible candidates, he shall be given an
            opportunity of making a representation against the proposed revision before any order of
            revision is passed. Provided also that where a panel has been prepared on the basis of
            the recommendations made by a DPC / Screening Committee any revision of such panel shall
            be made only after consultation with such D.P.C / Screening Committee.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.25 --


            REVIEW :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The State Government may, of their own motion or otherwise, review any original order
            passed by them, promoting a member of a service or class, to a higher post or approving
            a panel of candidates for appointment or promotion to any category, class or service,
            prepared by them, or any order of revision passed by them under rule 24, if it was
            passed under any mistake, whether of fact or of law, or in ignorance of any material
            fact or for any other sufficient reason. Provided that no order of review under this
            rule shall be passed unless the person affected or likely to be affected thereby is
            given an opportunity of making his representation against the proposed review.
        </para_desc>
    </para>


    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.26 --


            APPEAL AGAINST SENIORITY OR OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Except where other-wise provided in these or the special rules, an appeal shall lie
            against an order fixing the seniority of a person or affecting any conditions of
            service, passed by the appointing authority, to the authority to whom an appeal would
            lie against an order of dismissal passed against the member of the service, class or
            category.

            (b) The powers in sub-rule(a) shall be exercised by the Head of the
            Department, if he is not the appellate authority, or by the State Government on its own
            motion, or on an appeal received by the Head of the Department or the State Government,
            as the case may be.

            (c) The appellate authority, if it is not the Head of the Department
            or the Government, shall dispose of such appeal within a maximum period of one year. If
            the appeal has not been disposed of within the aforesaid period, the Head of the
            Department or the State Government may intervene in the matter, for sufficient reasons
            to be recorded in writing and take such action as may be considered necessary by them in
            the matter.

            (d) No appeal for restoration of seniority or assignment of notional
            seniority on par with his junior shall be entertained by the appellate authority after a
            period of 90 days from the date on which junior was promoted.

            (e) A member of service
            may submit a revision petition against the order of the Appellate Authority, within
            three months of the orders passed by the Appellate Authority, to the Government.
            [Amended in G.O.Ms.No.76, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 11-03-2003.]
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.27 --


            APPOINTMENT OF ALL INDIA SERVICE OFFICERS AND APAS OFFICERS TO POSTS IN THE STATE
            SERVICES :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules or the special rules an
            officiating or permanent member of the All India Services may be appointed to any post
            in any state service subject to the provisions of the All India Service Rules. Such an
            officer shall not by reason of such appointment, cease to be a member of the All India
            Service concerned.

            (b) Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules or the special
            rules an officiating or permanent member of the APAS may be appointed to any post in any
            State service subject to the provisions of the APAS rules. Such an officer shall not by
            reason of such appointment cease to be a member of the APAS.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.28 --


            RELINQUISHMENT OF RIGHTS BY MEMBERS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Any member of a service may, in writing, relinquish any right or privilege to which he
            may be entitled to, under these rules or the special rules, if, in the opinion of the
            appointing authority such relinquishment is not opposed to public interest. Such
            relinquishment once made will be final and irrevocable. Nothing contained in these rules
            or the special rules shall be deemed to require the recognition of any right or
            privilege to the extent to which it has been so relinquished: Provided that no
            conditional relinquishment or relinquishment of right for a temporary period shall be
            permitted.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.29 --


            RE-EMPLOYMENT OF MEMBERS OF SERVICE DISCHARGED ON ACCOUNT OF THEIR SUFFERING FROM T.B.
            ETC.,:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) A member of the State or Subordinate Service discharged on account of his suffering
            from T.B. or such other diseases as may be specified by the Government from time to
            time, shall be eligible for re-appointment to the post held by him prior to his
            discharge as aforesaid or to a post of the same rank and status in the department
            concerned, if he is declared non-infective and medically fit for Government service by
            the Medical authority, authorized for this purpose by the State Government.

            (b) For the purpose of determining whether any such member possesses the age
            qualification, where
            such age qualifications are prescribed in the special rules or these rules the period of
            his service in the post held by him prior to his discharge shall be deducted from the
            actual age and if the age so computed does not exceed the prescribed age limit by more
            than three years, he shall be deemed to be with the prescribed age limit.

            (c) On re-appointment of any such member the actual service rendered by him prior to his
            discharge from service, shall count for purposes of seniority and pay, to the extent to
            which it would have been counted for the said purposes had he not been discharged. The
            break in service between the date of discharge and the date of reappointment shall not,
            however, count for any purpose, but his service shall, otherwise, be regarded as
            continuous. On re-appointment of such a member to the same post or to a post of the same
            rank and status the service which has not been counted for increments before, upto a
            maximum of one year and any leave to his credit under the leave rules by which such
            member was governed at the time of his discharge, shall also be allowed to be carried
            over to his account.

            (d) The provisions of this rule shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in
            these rules or the special rules applicable to the concerned members of a service.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.30 --


            RESIGNATION :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) A member of a service may resign his appointment and the acceptance of his
            resignation by the appointing authority shall take effect:-

            (i) in case he is on duty,
            from the date on which he is relieved of his duties in pursuance of such acceptance.

            (ii) in case he is on leave, from the date of communication of such acceptance to the
            member or if the said authority so directs, from the date of expiry of leave; and

            (iii) in any other case, from the date of communication of such acceptance to the member
            or
            from such other date, not being earlier than the date on which he was last on duty, as
            the said authority may, having regard to administrative exigencies, specify.

            Provided that the resignation of a member of a service shall not be accepted against
            whom
            disciplinary proceedings are instituted as per the provisions of the Andhra Pradesh
            Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1991 or investigation,
            inquiry or trial is initiated. [Amended in G.O.Ms.No. 250, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt:
            14-07-2000.] Provided further that a member of a service may withdraw his resignation
            before it takes effect. Provided also that no withdrawal of resignation shall be
            permitted except with the sanction of the Government, if the withdrawal is made after
            the resignation takes effect.

            (b) If the resignation of a member of service has been accepted, but has not taken
            effect and he withdraws his resignation before it has taken effect, he should be deemed
            to be continuing in service. If the person is permitted to withdraw his resignation
            after it has taken effect and is re-appointed to the post from which he resigned, such
            reappointment shall be subject to the conditions specified in sub-rules (c) and (d).

            (c) A member of service, shall, if he resigns his appointment, forfeit not only the
            service rendered by him in the particular post held by him at the time of resignation
            but all his previous service under the Government,

            (d) The reappointment of a person, who has resigned from Government service and who is
            re-appointed to any service, shall be treated in the same way as a first appointment to
            such service by direct recruitment and all rules governing such appointment shall apply;
            and on such re-appointment, he shall not be entitled to count any portion of his
            previous service for any benefit or concession admissible under any rule or order.
            Provided that nothing contained in this rule shall affect the operation of clause (b) of
            Article 418 or Article 422 of the Civil Services Regulations or of any other rules
            similar thereto for the time being in force.

            (e) Where a member of a service is selected for appointment by direct recruitment to
            another post, category or class in the same or different service and is appointed to it,
            his lien on the service or his probationary right, if any, in the post of the service
            under the State Government, which he was holding prior to such appointment by direct
            recruitment, shall be retained for a period of three years or until he becomes an
            approved probationer in the post, category or class in the same or different service of
            this State Government, to which he has been selected, whichever is earlier; and if
            before the expiry of three years he is not an approved probationer in the post to which
            he was selected for appointment by direct recruitment, in the same or different service
            of the Government, unless he reverts to the parent Department, he shall be deemed to
            have resigned from the service of which he was a member prior to such appointment by
            direct recruitment with effect from the date on which the three years period expires.

            Provided that nothing in this sub-rule shall affect the benefits accrued to such member
            of a service or services in the previous post or posts, except the lien or probationary
            right, as the case may be, on such post or posts. Provided further that where a member
            of a service is selected for appointment by direct recruitment to a post under the
            service of the Government of India or any other State Government, his lien on a post or
            probationary right, if any, in the State Government shall be retained for a period of
            three years or until he becomes an approved probationer in the service of the Government
            of India as the case may be, whichever is earlier, and if before the expiry of three
            years he is not an approved probationer in any post under the service of that other
            Government as the case may be, unless he reverts to the services of the State
            Government, he shall be deemed to have resigned from the service of which he was a
            member prior to such appointment by direct recruitment, with effect from the date on
            which the three years period expires.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.31 --


            RELAXATION OF RULES BY THE GOVERNOR :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules or in the special rules, the Governor
            shall have the power to relax any rules contained in these rules or special rules, in
            favour of any person or class of persons, in relation to their application to any member
            of a service or to any person to be appointed to the service, class or category or a
            person or a class of persons, who have served in any civil capacity in the Government of
            Andhra Pradesh in such manner as may appear to be just and equitable to him, where such
            relaxation is considered necessary in the public interest or where the application of
            such rule or rules is likely to cause undue hardship to the person or class of persons
            concerned.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.32 --


            RELAXATION OF RULES BY THE HEAD OF THE DEPARTMENT :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules or in the special rules and
            without prejudice to the power of the Governor under rule 31, the Head of the Department
            shall also have the power to relax any rule or rules in these rules or in the special
            rules in favour of any person or class of persons or category of persons for being
            appointed to or of any person or class of persons who have served or are serving in any
            civil post or posts carrying a scale of pay less than that of Junior Assistant in his
            department in so far as such cases relate to transfer, promotion or the service
            conditions governed by these rules or special rules in such manner as may appear to him
            to be just and equitable in the public interest or where he considers the application of
            such rule or rules would cause undue hardship to the person or persons concerned.
            Provided that nothing in this sub-rule shall apply in regard to the appointment by
            transfer of a person who is not qualified for such appointment to the post of Junior
            Assistant or equivalent post in the A.P. Ministerial or any other Subordinate Service.

            Explanation :- This rule shall be applicable to posts which carry a scale of pay or pay
            less than that of a Junior Assistant and not to posts of Junior Assistants or any other
            post carrying an equivalent scale of pay.


            (b) Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 31 or sub-rule (a), the State Government,
            may, of their own motion or otherwise, review
            the orders of relaxation issued in rule 31, or sub rule (a) or cancel any such
            relaxation orders, within a period of six (6) months from the date of issue of such
            relaxation orders, if it is found that the said orders were passed under any mistake,
            whether of fact or of law, or in ignorance of any material fact or for any other
            sufficient cause to be recorded in writing: Provided that no order consequent on such
            review, or an order to cancel the relaxation orders, under this sub-rule, shall be
            issued unless the person affected thereby is given an opportunity of making his
            representation against the proposed review or cancellation.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.33 --


            SENIORITY :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) The seniority of a person in a service, class, category or grade shall, unless he
            has been reduced to a lower rank as a punishment, be determined by the date of his first
            appointment to such service, class, category or grade. Provided that the seniority of a
            probationer or approved probationer in a service, class or category from which he stood
            reverted on the 1st November, 1956 or prior to that date, shall be determined in the
            state wide gazetted posts and the non-gazetted posts in the Departments of the
            Secretariat and the offices of the Heads of Departments with reference to the notional
            date of continuous officiation with or without breaks in that service, class or category
            prior to the 1st November, 1956 to the date of re-appointment made thereafter, but it
            shall not disturb the inter-seniority which obtained in the Andhra State. (This proviso
            shall be in force till 31st October, 1996).


            (b) The appointing authority may, at the time of passing an order appointing two or more
            persons simultaneously to a service, fix either for the purpose of satisfying the rule
            of reservation of appointments or for any other reason the order of preference among
            them; and where such order has been fixed, seniority shall be determined in accordance
            with it. Provided further that the order of merit or order of preference indicated in a
            list of
            selected candidates prepared by the Public Service Commission or other selecting
            authority, shall not be disturbed inter-se with reference to the candidates position in
            such list or panel while determining the seniority in accordance with this rule and
            notional dates of commencement of probation to the extent necessary, shall be assigned
            to the persons concerned, with reference to the order of merit or order of preference
            assigned to them in the said list.

            (c) Whenever notional date of promotion is assigned, such date of notional promotion
            shall be taken into consideration for computing the qualifying length of service in the
            feeder category for promotion to the next higher category and that the notional service
            shall be counted for the purpose of declaration of probation also in the feeder
            category.

            (d) The transfer of a person from one class or category of a service to another class or
            category of the same service, carrying the same pay of scale of pay shall not be treated
            as first appointment to the latter class or category for purpose of seniority and the
            seniority of a person so transferred shall be determined with reference to the date of
            his regular appointment in the class or category from which he was transferred. Where
            any difficulty arises in applying this sub-rule, seniority shall be determined by the
            Government, if they are the appointing authority and in other cases, the authority next
            higher to the appointing authority shall determine the seniority.

            (e) Where a number of a service, class or category is reduced for a specific period, to
            a lower service, class or category or grade:- (i) in cases where the reduction does not
            operate to postpone future increment, the seniority of such member on re-promotion
            shall, unless the terms of the order of punishment provides otherwise, be fixed in the
            higher service, class or category at which it would have been fixed but for his
            reduction; (ii) in cases where the reduction operates to postpone future increment, the
            seniority of such member on re-promotion shall, unless the terms of the order of
            punishment provide otherwise, be fixed by giving credit for the period of service
            earlier rendered by him in the higher service, class or category.

            (f) Seniority of a retrenched and reappointed person: The seniority of a member of a
            service, who is re-appointed after having been retrenched, owing to reduction of staff
            as a measure of economy, shall be determined in accordance with the date of such
            reappointment. Provided that the inter-se-seniority of such members absorbed in the same
            service, class or category shall be determined. (i) in any case in which re-appointment
            of such members was made in consultation with Public Service Commission or the other
            selecting authority, in accordance with the order of merit or the order of preference
            indicated by the said Public Service Commission or other selecting authority; and (ii)
            in any other case, in accordance with the total length of service, in the same
            equivalent or higher service, class or category put in by such member prior to
            retrenchment.

            (g) The seniority of an approved candidate, who takes up military service before joining
            his appointment to any service, class or category shall, on his appointment to such
            service, class or category, on his return from the said military service, be determined
            in accordance with the order of preference shown in the authoritative list of candidates
            approved for appointment to the service, class or category.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.34 --


            PREPARATION OF INTEGRATED OR COMMON SENIORITY LIST OF PERSONS BELONGING TO DIFFERENT
            UNITS OF APPOINTMENT :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Where as integrated or common seniority list of a particular class, or category or grade
            in any service belonging to different units of appointment has to be prepared for the
            purpose of promotion or appointment by transfer, to a class or category having different
            units of appointment or for any other purpose, such an integrated or common seniority
            list shall be prepared with reference to the provision of sub-rule (a) of rule 33,
            provided that the seniority list of the persons inter-se belonging to the same units
            shall not be disturbed. Explanation: The principle specified in this rule shall be
            applicable even where a common integrated list is required to be prepared for categories
            in different services classes or categories.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.35 --


            FIXATION OF SENIORITY IN THE CASE OF TRANSFERS ON REQUEST OR ON ADMINISTRATIVE GROUNDS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) The seniority of a member of a service, class or category transferred from one unit
            of appointment to another unit of appointment, on administrative grounds, shall be,
            determined with reference to the date of seniority of such member in the former unit.
            (b) The seniority of a member of a service, class or category, who is transferred on his
            own request from one unit of appointment to another unit of appointment shall be fixed
            with reference to the date of his joining duty in the latter unit of appointment.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.36 --


            INTER-SE-SENIORITY WHERE THE DATES OF COMMENCEMENT OF PROBATION ARE SAME :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The seniority of the persons in the service shall be determined as follows:-
            (i) In respect of the candidate selected by the Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission
            or other selecting authorities by direct recruitment, shall be with reference to their
            ranking assigned irrespective of the date of commencement of their probation in that
            category.

            (ii) In respect of the persons promoted or appointed by transfer (involving
            promotion) the dates from which they were placed on their probation;

            (iii) In respect of persons covered under item (ii) above, in case the date of
            commencement of probation is the same, whoever is aged shall be the senior;

            (iv) In respect of the persons appointed on transfer on administrative grounds, shall be
            from the date on which the individual was placed on probation in the original
            department; and

            (v) In respect of the persons appointed on request transfer; the date of joining of such
            person in the new department / unit.

        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.37 --


            SENIORITY OF DIRECTLY RECRUITEED CANDIDATES, RE-ALLOTTED IN CONSULTATION WITH
            A.P.P.S.C.:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            The candidates re-allotted under sub-rule (c) of rule-4 shall be assigned seniority
            below the last regular candidate in the concerned class or category in the unit to which
            such candidates is re-allotted.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.38 --


            POSTINGS AND TRANSFERS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) A member of a State Service or class of a State Service may be posted to any post
            borne on the cadre of such service or class of service anywhere in the State. Provided
            that such postings and transfers shall be limited to the territorial jurisdiction of the
            local cadres specified in accordance with or in pursuance of the Presidential Order,
            where applicable, or to the units of appointment, if any, specified in the Special
            Rules.

            (b) A member of a Subordinate Service or a class of such service may be posted to
            another post borne on the cadre of such service or class of such service, within the
            unit of appointment specified in the special rules and subject to the provisions of the
            Presidential Order.

            (c) All transfers and postings of a member of State or Subordinate Service shall be made
            subject to sub-rules (a) and (b) by the appointing authority or such other authority
            subordinate to the appointing authority, specified in the special rules or to whom the
            appointing authority has delegated such powers of postings and transfers:

            (i) Provided that such power will be exercised by the appointing authority or the
            authority to whom
            the power has been delegated, within their respective jurisdiction but subject to the
            units of appointment under the Presidential Order, applicable to the relevant post.

            (ii) Provided further that the Head of the Department may transfer a member of a service
            from
            the unit of one appointing authority to the unit of another appointing authority, where
            the Presidential Order is not applicable.

            (iii) Provided also that where the appointing authority is not the State Government, any
            authority to whom the appointing authority is administratively subordinate will, in
            respect of any post within the jurisdiction of the appointing authority, also be
            competent to effect transfers and postings to a post within the jurisdiction of such
            appointing authority within the units of appointment specified in the special rules and
            subject to the provisions of the Presidential Order.

            (iv) Provided also that where the State Government are the appointing authority in
            respect of the members of the State Services, the Head of the Department who is
            competent to grant leave to such members under F.R.66 or H.C.S.R.374 shall also be
            competent to issue reposting order in respect of those members on return from leave.

            (v) Provided also that unless otherwise stipulated in any special rules or adhoc rules,
            the State Government may, on its own motion or on a proposal received from a Head of the
            Department, Order, for sufficient reasons to be recorded in writing, the transfer of
            members of the State or Subordinate Services from the local cadres organised in
            pursuance of the Presidential Order to the office of the concerned Head of the
            Departments and offices notified under the said Order as State Level Offices or Special
            Offices or Major Development projects and vice-versa. The seniority of any member of the
            service who is so transferred on administrative grounds shall be fixed in the unit to
            which he is transferred with reference to the date of his appointment in the office from
            which he is transferred and the seniority of any member of the service who is
            transferred at his own request shall be fixed with reference to the date of his joining
            in the unit to which he is transferred.

            (vi) Notwithstanding anything in these Rules, or the special or the ad-hoc rules,
            transfer of a person holding post in a category organised into local cadre, under
            paragraph 3 of the Andhra Pradesh Public Employment (Organisation of Local Cadres and
            Regulation of Direct Recruitment) Order, 1975, as amended, from one local cadre to
            another may be made by the Government:- (a) against a vacancy where no qualified or
            suitable person is available in the latter cadre or where such transfer is otherwise
            considered necessary in the public interest; and (b) on reciprocal basis, subject to the
            condition that transferee shall be assigned seniority with reference to the date of
            transfer in the cadre to which he is transferred.” Provided also that the Head of the
            Department may transfer on tenure, from a local cadre to a post to which the
            Presidential Order does not apply, where such posts are required to be filled on tenure
            basis from such local cadres and retransfer him to his local cadre.


            (d) A member of a State or Subordinate Service or a class of such service may be
            required by the appointing authority or any other authority superior to such appointing
            authority, to serve in any post borne on the cadre of any body wholly or substantially
            owned or controlled by the Government.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>Rule No.39 --

            SAVINGS :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (a) (i) Unless a contrary intention is expressly indicated therein, nothing contained in
            these rules shall adversely affect any person who was a member of any service on the
            date of the coming into force of these rules. (ii) Unless a contrary intention is
            expressly indicated therein, nothing contained in any amendments to any special rules
            governing a service, shall adversely affect any person who was a member of such service
            on the date of the coming into force thereof.

            (b) Subject to the provisions of sub-rules (c) and (d) where these rules or the Special
            rules would adversely affect in respect of any matter, a person who was a member of any
            service before the date of coming into force thereof, he shall, in respect of the post
            held by him immediately prior to such date be governed by the rules and orders, if any,
            which were applicable to him immediately prior to such date.

            (c) A person who was on duty, otherwise than in a substantive capacity in a post, which
            was subsequently included in a service shall be regarded as a probationer or, as the
            case may be, as an approved probationer in the service or the class or category thereof
            in which the post is included and in the lower category, if any, in which he would have
            been on duty but for his being on duty in a higher category, if he:- (i) was on duty in
            such post on the date of issue of the special rules for that service; or (ii) was absent
            from duty in such post on that date, on leave granted by a competent authority, having
            been on duty in such post immediately before and immediately after such absence.
            Provided that if there were no rules or orders prescribing the period of probation for
            such post at the time of his first appointment thereto, the provisions of these rules
            and of the special rules regarding probation shall apply to him and any period of duty
            rendered by him in such post before the date of issue of such rules shall count towards
            probation, if any to the extent such service would have counted had these rules and the
            special rules come into force at the time of such first appointment.

            (d) A person, who, before the issue of the special rules for a service had officiated in
            a post which was subsequently included in the service, class or category thereof, but
            who is not entitled to be regarded as probationer or as an approved probationer under
            sub-rule (c) shall, if he is again appointed to such post, after the issue of the
            special rules without contravening any orders of the State Government, be entitled to
            count his previous service in such post towards the prescribed period of probation.
            Provided that such previous service shall not count towards probation if there was an
            interval of a continuous period of two years or more during which he was not holding a
            post in the same or higher category.

            Explanation:- The re-appointment of a person under this sub-rule shall not, for the
            purposes of these rules regulating recruitment, be regarded as first appointment to the
            service, class or category concerned


            (e) If, before the issue of the Special Rules, a person had been exempted under the
            orders then in force, from the possession of any qualification or the passing of such
            test prescribed by such special rules, they shall not apply to such person to the extent
            and in respect of the category, grade or post, specially covered by the order of
            exemption.


            (f) Where a person appointed to a post in accordance with the provisions of rule 4 of
            the Hyderabad General Recruitment Rules, was holding such post immediately before the
            first day of November, 1956 he shall continue to be governed by the provisions of the
            Hyderabad Cadre and Recruitment Rules and Hyderabad Probationary Rules. The provisions
            of this sub-rule shall be deemed to have come into force on the first day of November,
            1956 and shall be in force upto 31-10-1996.


            (g) (i) Nothing in these rules or in the Special Rules shall disqualify or shall be
            deemed to have ever disqualified an employee of the erstwhile Government of Hyderabad
            who was allotted to the State of Andhra Pradesh under section 115 of the States
            Reorganisation Act, 1956, on promotion or recruitment by transfer, on or after the 1st
            November, 1956, to a post one stage above that held by him prior to the said date, if in
            the opinion of the appointing authority such person would have been qualified for
            promotion or for appointment to any such post under the Hyderabad Cadre and Recruitment
            Rules applicable thereto, had recruitment to such post been regulated by the last
            mentioned rules.

            (ii) The promotion or recruitment by transfer on or after the 1st
            November, 1956 of an employee of the erstwhile Government of Hyderabad under these rules
            or the special rules of the Hyderabad Cadre and Recruitment Rules, to a post one stage
            above that held by him prior to that date, shall not in any way affect the protection
            given in favour of such employee in respect of the beneficial pay scale of promotion or
            transfer, upto one stage, drawal of increments, pension and other similar matters under
            the Hyderabad Civil Services Rules.

            (iii) The appointment of an employee of the erstwhile Government of Hyderabad, either to
            an intermediary post for which there was no
            corresponding post under that Government or to a post by way of second and subsequent
            promotion on or after the 1st November, 1956, shall be governed only by these rules or
            the special rules, as the case, may be, and the protection to be afforded to such
            employee to opt to the beneficial scale of pay on promotion to an intermediary post,
            which was either in existence on that date or created subsequently in the regular line
            of promotion, and which is lower than the one to which such employee would have been
            promoted in the pre-reorganised set up, shall in each case be determined after obtaining
            the approval of the Government of India.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>SCHEDULE –I (See definition 27 of Rule 2)


            PART – A:
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            (Substituted with effect from 27th July, 1977 through G.O.Ms.No.838, G.A. (Services D)
            Dept., dt.15.12.1977) Scheduled Castes (Definition 28 of rule 2)
            1. Adi Andhra

            2. Adi Dravida

            3. Anamuk

            4. Aray Mala

            5. Arundhatiya

            6. Arwa Mala

            7. Bariki

            8. Bauri

            9. Bedajanagam/ Budga Jangam

            10.Bindla

            11.Byagara

            12.Chachati

            13.Chalavadi

            14.Chamar, Mochi, Muchi,

            15.Chambhar

            16.Chandala

            17.Dakkal, Dokkalwar

            18.Dandasi

            19.Dhor

            20.Dom, Dombara, Paidi, Pano

            21.Ellamalwar, Yellammalawandlu

            22.Ghasi, Haddi, Relli, Chachandi

            23.Godagali

            24.Godari

            25.Gosangi

            26.Holeya

            27.Holeya Dasari

            28.Jaggali

            29.Jambuwulu

            30.Kolupulvandlu

            31.Madasi Kuruva, Madari Kuruva

            32.Madiga

            33.Madiga Dasu, Mashteen

            34.Mahar

            35.Mala

            36.Mala Dasari

            37.Mala Dasu

            38.Mala Hannai

            39.Malajangam

            40.Mala Masti

            41.Mala Sale Netkani

            42.Mala Sanyasi

            43.Mang

            44.Mang Garodi

            45.Manne

            46.Mashti

            47.Matangi

            48.Mahter

            49.Mitha Ayyalvar

            50.Mundala

            51.Paky, Moti, Thoti

            52.Pambada, Pambanda

            53.Pamidi

            54.Panchama, Pariah

            55.Relli

            56.Samagara

            57.Samban

            58.Sapru

            59.Sindhollu, Chindollu

            60.SC Converts to Buddhism Omitted vide G.O.Ms.No.476, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt:15.11.97
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>PART – B Scheduled Tribes (Definition 29 of rule 2) :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            1. Andh.

            2. Bagata.

            3. Bhil.

            4. Chanchu, Chenchwar.

            5. Gadabas.

            6. Gond, Naikpod, Rajgond.

            7. Goudu (in the Agency tracts)

            8. Hill Reddis.

            9. Jatapus.

            10.Kammara.

            11.Kattunayakan.

            12.Kolam, Mannervalu.

            13.Konda Dhoras.

            14.Konda Kapus.

            15.Konda Reddis.

            16.Kodhs, Kodi, Kodhu, Desaya, Kondhs, Dongria, Kondhs, Kuttiya, Khonds, Tikiria
            Khondhs, Yenity Khonds.

            17.Kotia, Bentheo, Oriya, Bartika, Dhulia, Dulia, Holva, Paika, Putiya, Sanrona,
            Sidhopaiko.

            18.Koya Goud, Rajah, Rasha Koya, Lingadhari Koya (Ordinary), Kottu Koya, Bhine Koya,
            Raja Koya.

            19.Kulia.

            20.Malis, (excluding Adilabad, Hyderabad, Karimnagar, Khammam, Mahabubnagar, Medak,
            Nalgonda, Nizamabad and Warangal Districts.)

            21.Manna Dhora.

            22.Nayaks (in the Agency tracts) .

            23.Mukha Dhora, Nooka Dhora.

            24.Pardhan.

            25.Porja, Parangi Perja.

            26.Reddi Dhoras.

            27.Rona, Rena.

            28.Savaras, Kapu Savaras, Maliya Savaras, Khutto Savaras. .

            29.Sugalis, Lambadis.

            30.Thoti (in Adilabad, Hyderabad, Karimnagar, Khammam, Mahabubnagar, Medak, Nalgonda,
            Nizamabad and Warangal Districts.)

            31.Valimiki (in the Agency tracts)

            32.Yenadis.

            33.Yerukulas
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>PART – C BACKWARD CLASSES ( Definition 7 of Rule 2) GROUP – A :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            1. Agnikulakshtriya, Palli, Vadabalija, Besta jalari, Gangavar, Gangaputra, Goondla,
            Vanyaakulakshatriya (Vannekapu, Vannereddi, Pallikapu, Pallireddy), Neyyala and Pattapu

            2. Balasanthu, Bahurupi

            3. Bandara

            4. Budabukkala

            5. Chopamari

            6. Dasari (formerly addicted to crimes and beggary)

            7. Dommara

            8. Gangiredlavari

            9. Gudala

            10.Jangam whose traditional occupation is begging.

            11.Jogi

            12.Joshinandiwalas

            13.Kaikadi

            14.Kanjara – Bhatta

            15.Katipapala

            16.Kepamora or Reddika

            17.Kalinga (Kinthala) (omitted vide G.O.Ms.No.701, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dated:12.11.1980
            w.e.f.7.3.80)

            18.Korecha

            18-A Kunapuli

            19.( ) Omitted in G.O.Ms.No.290, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept.,
            dated: 21.4.1978 w.e.f.27.7.1977, 19-A. ( ) Omitted in G.O.Ms.No. 472, G.A.(Ser. D)
            Dept., dt: 11-11-83

            20.Mandula

            21.Medari or Mahendra

            22.Mehator (Muslim)

            23.Mondipatta

            24.Mondivaru, Mondibanda, Banda

            25.Nakkala

            26.Nayi Brahmin (Mangali)
            Mangala Bhoganti

            27.Nokkar

            28.Odde (Oddulu, Vaddi, Vaddelu)

            29.Pambala

            30.Pamula

            31.Pardhi (Nirshikari)

            32.Pariki Muggula

            33.Peddammavandlu, Devaravandlu, Yellammavandu, Mutyalammavandlu

            34.Vamsa Raj

            35.Rajaka (Chakali, Vannar)

            36.Valmiki boya (Boya, Bedar, Kirataka, Nishadi, Yellapi Pedda Boya) Talayari and
            Chunduvellu

            37.Veeramushti (Nettikotala)

            38.Yata

            39.( ) Omitted in G.O.Ms.No.290, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt:21.4.78 w.e.f.27.7.1977.
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>GROUP-B (Vocational) :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            1. Achukatlavandlu

            2. Aryakshatriya, Muchi (Telugu Speaking), Chittari, Ciniyar, Chitrakara, Nakshas.

            3. Devanga

            4. Dudekula, Laddaf, Pinjari or Noorbash.

            5. Ediga, Gowda (Gamalla, Kalalee), Goundla. Settibalija of Vishakhapatnam, East
            Godavari, West Godavari and Krishna Districts.

            6. Gandla. Telikula

            7. Jandra

            8. Karikalabhakthula, Kaikolan or kaikala (Sengundam or sangunther)

            9. Karnabhakthula

            10.Kummara or Kulala  Salivahana

            11.Kuruba or Kuruma

            12.Nagavaddilu

            13.Neelakanthi

            14.Nossi or kurni

            15.Padmasali (sati, Salivan, pattusali, Sanapathulu, Shogata Sali)

            16.Patkar (Khatri)

            17.Perika (Perika, balija, Urasirikshatriya)

            18.Srisayana (segidi)

            19.Swakulasali

            20.Thogata, Thogati or thogataveerakshtriya

            21.Viswabrahmin Ausula or Kamsali, Kummari, Kanchari Vadla or Vadra or Vadrangi and
            Silpis
        </para_desc>
    </para>

    <para>
        <para_name>GROUP – C Scheduled Casts converts to Christianity and their progeny).
            (Substituted in G.O.Ms.No.159, G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt: 2.4.81). GROUP-D (Other Classes)
            :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            1. Agaru

            2. Arekatika, Katika

            3. Atagara

            4. Bhatraju

            5. Chippolu (Mera)

            6. Gavara

            7. Godaba

            8. Halkar

            9. Jakkala

            10. Jingar

            11. Kachi

            12. Surya Balija, Ganika

            13. Kandra

            14. Koppulavelama

            15. Kosthi

            16. Krishnabalija (Dasari, Bukka)

            17. Mali

            18. Mathura

            19. Mudiraj, Mustrasi, Tenugolu

            20. Munnurukapu (Telangana)

            21. Nagavamsam (Nagavamsa) vide G.O.Ms.No.53, BC Welfare Dept., dt:19.9.96

            22. Nelli

            23. Passi

            24. Polinativelmas of Srikakulam and Visakhapatnam Districts

            25. Poosala

            26. Rangrez or Bhavasarakshtriya

            27. Sadhu Chetty

            28. Satani (Chattadasrivaishnava)

            29. Tammali

            30. Turupukapus or Gajula Kapus of Srikakulam, Vizianagaram (inserted in G.O.Ms.No.700,
            G.A.(Ser. D) Dept., dt:12.11.80 w.e.f.1.6.1979) and Visakhapatnam Districts who are
            subject to Social customs or divorce and remarriage among their women.

            31. Uppara or Sagara

            32. Vanjara (Vanjari)

            33. Yadava (Golla)
        </para_desc>
    </para>
    <para>
        <para_name>SCHEDULE – II :
        </para_name>
        <para_desc>

            Minimum General Education Qualification Referred to in Rule 12(2) A candidate is said to
            possess the Minimum General Education Qualification if he has passed one of the
            following examinations:-
            1. Secondary School Certificate Examination conducted by the Board of Secondary
            Education, Andhra Pradesh, Hyd.

            2. Indian Army Special Certificate of Education.

            3. A pass in the Higher Education Test of the Royal Indian Navy.

            4. A pass in the Anglo – Vernacular School leaving Certificate (Burma Examination)

            5. A pass in the Burma High School Final Examination;

            6. A pass in the Matriculation Examination of the Rangoon University;

            7. A pass in the Secondary School Certificate Examination conducted by the Government of
            Bombay;

            8. A pass in the Admission Examination of the Benaras Hindu University;

            9. A pass in the Advanced Class (Indian Navy) Examination held in or before 1953;

            10.A Certificate granted by the East Bengal Secondary Education Board, Decca, in any of
            the following three Examinations conducted by it:-
            i) Matriculation Examination
            ii) Higher Madrasha Examination.
            iii) School Final (Science side examination)

            11.A pass in the Vidya Vinodini Examination conducted during the period commencing from
            the year 1946 and ending with May, 1964 by the Prayag Mahila Vidyapitha situated at 556,
            Daragan, Allahabad and 106, Howett Road, Allahabad, provided the candidate has taken
            “Advanced English” as one of the optional subjects and produces proof to the
            satisfaction of the Andhra Pradesh Public Service Commission in cases where appointment
            has to be made in consultation with it or the appointing authority in other cases, that
            the candidate has adequate knowledge of one of the language of the Andhra Pradesh State.

            12.Successful completion of two years course at the Joint Services Wing of the National
            Defence Academy provided that the Cadet‟s discontinuance of the course at the Academy on
            completion of the two years was not due to academic reasons;

            13.A pass in the High School Examination of the Aligarh University;

            14. Cambridge School Certificate Examination (Senior Cambridge);

            15.European High School Examination, held by the State Government

            16.Tenth Class Examination of the Technical Higher Secondary School Delhi Polytechnic;

            17.Pass in the preparatory Examination of the Delhi University;

            18.School leaving Examination of the Government of Nepal;

            19.A pass in the Vidyadhikari Examination of Gurukula Kanigiri – Viswa Vidyalaya.

            20. A pass in Ceylon Senior School Certificate Examination.

            21. A pass in the following French Examinations of Pondicherry;
            i. Brevet Elementaries;
            ii. Brevet D‟ Etudes dupremier Cycle;
            iii. Brevet D‟ enseighment Premaire Superior de languo Indienns, and
            iv. Brevet de langu Indienn (Vernacular).

            22. A Certificate of Post-Basic Education awarded by a post-Basic School.

            23. General Certificate of Education of Ceylon at Ordinary level, provided that the
            candidate has passed in six subjects including English, Mathematics and either Sinhaless
            or Tamil;

            24.A pass in the Secondary School leaving Certificate of Kerala State;

            25.A pass in the Secondary School Certificate Examination (New Pattern 1967) (10 years
            course) of Madhya Pradesh State;

            26.A pass in HSLC Examination conducted by the Board of Secondary Education, Manipur.

            27.A compartmental pass in SSLC Examination of Government of Kerala;

            28.A pass in the Matriculation Examination of Haryana State conducted by the Board of
            School Education, Haryana.

            29.A pass in the Secondary School Leaving Certificate Examination of Mysore State.

            30.A pass in any other examination declared as equivalent to SSC examination by the
            Government of Andhra Pradesh.

            31.A pass in HSC examinations conducted by the Board of School Examination of Nagaland
            (G.O.Ms.No. 982 Edn (K2) Dept., dt:6.10.77)
        </para_desc>
    </para>

</Ebook>
